North Coast Hydrologic RegionHappy Camp Town Area Groundwater BasinHappy Camp Town Area Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 1-15• County: Siskiyou• Surface Area: 2,770 acres (4 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Happy Camp Town Area Groundwater Basin is an irregularly shaped basin that follows a short reach of the Klamath River. The basin is bounded on the west by the western Jurassic belt of the Klamath Mountains consisting of Upper Jurassic marine metasedimentary rocks. The eastern half of the basin lies within the western Paleozoic and Triassic belt and is bounded by pre-Silurian metamorphic rocks. The basin is comprised of Quaternary non- marine terrace deposits (Wagner 1989; Strand 1963).Annual precipitation in the basin ranges from 51- to 57-inches.Hydrogeologic InformationHydrogeologic information was not available for the following:Water-Bearing Formations Groundwater Level Trends Groundwater StorageGroundwater Budget (Type B)Deep percolation of applied water is approximately 450 acre-feet based on a 1991 survey conducted by the California Department of Water Resources.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Groundwater QualityHydrogeologic information was not available.Well Production characteristics Well yields (gal/min)￼IrrigationDomestic IrrigationNKD – No known dataNKDTotal depths (ft)Range: 40 – 345￼Active Monitoring Data Agency ParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water qualityAverage: 165 (23 Well Completion Reports) 60 (1 Well Completion Report)Number of wells /measurement frequency NKDNKD￼￼Last update 2/27/04
North Coast Hydrologic RegionHappy Camp Town Area Groundwater BasinCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateSelected ReferencesThe County of Siskiyou adopted a Groundwater Management Ordinance in 1998.Happy Camp CSD￼￼￼Davis GA, Lipman PW. 1962. Revised Structural Sequences of Pre-Cretaceous Metamorphic Rocks in the Southern Klamath Mountains, California. Geological Society of America 73(12):1547-1552.Davis GA. 1966. Metamorphic and Granitic History of the Klamath Mountains. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190. 39-50 p.Irwin WP. 1960. Geologic Reconnaissance of the Northern Coast Ranges and Klamath Mountains, California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 179.Irwin WP. 1966. Geology of the Klamath Mountain Province. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190. 19-38 p.Irwin WP. 1981. Tectonic Accretion of the Klamath Mountains. In: Ernst WG, editor. The Geotectonic Development of California: Prentice Hall, Inc. p 29-49.Pessagno EA, Blome CD. 1990. Implications of New Jurassic Stratigraphic, Geochronometric, and Paleolatitudinal Data from the Western Klamath Terrane (Smith River and Rogue Valley Subterranes). Geology.Strand RG. 1963. Geologic Map of California [Weed Sheet]. Scale 1:250,000. California Division of Mines and Geology.Wagner, D.L. 1989. Geology of Del Norte and Siskiyou Counties and Adjacent Portions of Humboldt, Shasta, and Trinity Counties. California Geology. January 1989.BibliographyBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.Smith JG, Page NJ, Johnson MG, Moring BC, Gray F. 1982. Preliminary Geologic Map of the Medford 1 x 2 Degree Quadrangle, Oregon and California. USGS. OF-82-955.Strand RG. 1969. Geologic Atlas of California [Weed Sheet]. California Division of Mines and Geology.Wagner DL, Saucedo GJ. 1987. Geologic Map of the Weed Quadrangle, California, Regional Geologic Map Series 4A. California Division of Mines and Geology.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.Last update 2/27/04
North Coast Hydrologic Region California’s Groundwater Happy Camp Town Area Groundwater Basin Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04