North Coast Hydrologic Region Honeydew Town Area Groundwater BasinHoneydew Town Area Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 1-29• County: Humboldt• Surface Area: 2,370 acres (4 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Honeydew Town Area Groundwater Basin is part of the Mattole River system. The basin occupies a small alluvial valley along the Mattole River, which generally follows fault trends in the region. The basin is bounded on all sides by undifferentiated marine Cretaceous deposits of graywacke and shale. Basin deposits consist of Quaternary non-marine terrace deposits (Strand 1962). Annual precipitation ranges from 71- to 79-inches.Hydrogeologic InformationHydrogeologic information was not available for the following:Water-Bearing Formations Groundwater Level Trends Groundwater StorageGroundwater Budget (Type B)The estimate of groundwater extraction for the Honeydew Town Area Basin is based on a 1996 survey conducted by the California Department of Water Resources. The survey included landuse and sources of water. Groundwater extraction for agricultural use is estimated to be 17 acre-feet. Groundwater extraction for municipal and industrial uses is estimated to be 3 acre-feet. Deep percolation of applied water is estimated to be 4 acre-feet.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Groundwater QualityHydrogeologic information was not available.Well Production characteristics Well yields (gal/min)Municipal/Irrigation NKD￼Domestic Municipal/IrrigationNKD – No known dataActive Monitoring Data100 (2 Well Completion Reports)Number of wells /measurement frequency NKDNKD 1Total depths (ft)￼￼AgencyDepartment of Health ServicesParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water quality Miscellaneous water quality￼Last update 2/27/04
North Coast Hydrologic Region Honeydew Town Area Groundwater BasinCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateSelected ReferencesNo known groundwater management plans, groundwater ordinances, or basin adjudications.None None￼￼￼Strand RG. 1962. Geologic Atlas of California [Redding Sheet]: California Division of Mines and Geology.Fraticelli LA, Albers JP, Irwin WP, Blake MC. 1987. Geologic Map of the Redding 1 x 2 Degree Quadrangle, Shasta, Tehama, Humboldt, and Trintity Counties, California. USGS. OF-87-257.BibliographyBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.Last update 2/27/04