South Lahontan Hydrologic Region Goldstone Valley Groundwater BasinGoldstone Valley Groundwater BasinGroundwater Basin Number: 6-48County: San BernardinoSurface Area: 28,100 acres (43.9 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyGoldstone Valley Groundwater Basin underlies a north-trending valley in northwest San Bernardino County. Surface elevations range from 3,025 feet at Goldstone (dry) Lake to a maximum elevation of about 3,700 feet above mean sea level at the valley’s southern end. The basin is bounded by consolidated nonwater-bearing rocks of the Goldstone Hills on the west and southwest. On the north, east, and south, the basin is bounded by nonwater- bearing of unnamed low hills (DWR 1964; USGS 1986).Annual rainfall ranges from 4 to 8 inches. Runoff from the surrounding hills drains towards Goldstone Lake located in the north-central portion of the valley (DWR 1964).Hydrogeologic InformationWater Bearing FormationsQuaternary alluvium forms the principal water-bearing unit within the basin. This includes unconsolidated younger alluvial deposits and underlying unconsolidated to poorly consolidated older alluvial deposits. Thickness of the alluvium reaches at least 330 feet (DWR 1964).Recharge and Discharge AreasThe Goldstone Valley is a closed basin without external drainage. Recharge to the basin is derived primarily from the percolation of occasional runoff from the surrounding hills through alluvial fan deposits fringing the valley. There is no subsurface inflow to the basin. Groundwater in the younger and underlying older alluvium moves toward Goldstone Lake (DWR 1964).Groundwater Level TrendsDepth to water at a well in the southeastern part of the basin was measured at 230 feet in 1943 (DWR, 1964).Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. Total storage capacity is estimated to be about 210,000 af (DWR 1975).Groundwater in Storage. Unknown. Groundwater Budget (C)Groundwater budget information is not available.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. Groundwater from a well shows calcium-sodium chloride character (DWR 1964).California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
South Lahontan Hydrologic Region Goldstone Valley Groundwater BasinImpairments. Groundwater in the basin is rated as inferior for irrigation purposes and marginal for domestic use because of elevated concentrations of chloride, fluoride, and TDS. Water from a well in the southeastern part of the basin had a chloride concentration of 613 mg/L with TDS content of 1,820 mg/L. Fluoride concentration was 1.0 mg/L (DWR 1964).Well Production characteristics Well yields (gal/min)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationTotal depths (ft)￼Active Monitoring Data￼AgencyDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water qualityTitle 22 water qualityNumber of wells /measurement frequency￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management: Water agenciesPublic PrivateReferences Cited￼￼California Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1964. Ground Water Occurrence and Quality Lahontan Region. Bulletin No. 106-1. 439 p._____. 1975. California’s Ground Water. Bulletin No. 118. 135 p.U. S. Geological Survey. 1986. East of Goldstone, California. 7.5 Quadrangle. ProvisionalEdition. Scale 1: 24,000._____. 1986. Goldstone, California. 7.5 Quadrangle. Provisional Edition. Scale 1: 24,000._____. 1986. West of Nelson Lake, California. 7.5’ Quadrangle. Provisional Edition. Scale 1: 24,000.ErrataSubstantive changes made to the basin description will be noted here.Last update 2/27/04