South Lahontan Hydrologic Region Hidden Valley Groundwater BasinHidden Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 6-63• County: Inyo• Surface Area: 18,000 acres (28.1 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThis groundwater basin underlies Hidden Valley, Ulida Flat and Sand Flat in south central Inyo County and is bounded by impermeable rocks of the Panamint Range (Jennings 1958). Surface drainage flows toward a playa in Hidden Valley and a closed basin in San Flat (Jennings 1958). Average annual precipitation ranges from 6 to 8 inches.Hydrogeologic InformationWater Bearing FormationsGroundwater can likely be found in alluvium of Quaternary age. Alluvium typically consists of unconsolidated, fine- to coarse-grained sand, pebbles, and boulders with variable amounts of silt and clay.Restrictive StructuresUnknown.Recharge AreasThe principal source of recharge to the basin is likely percolation of runoff from surrounding mountains, with minor contribution from percolation of precipitation to the valley floor.Groundwater Level TrendsNo wells are known to exist in this basin.Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. Unknown. Groundwater in Storage. Unknown.Groundwater Budget (Type C)No information is available.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. Unknown. Impairments. Unknown.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
South Lahontan Hydrologic Region Hidden Valley Groundwater BasinWell Production characteristics Well yields (gal/min)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationActive Monitoring DataAgencyDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water qualityTitle 22 water qualityNumber of wells /measurement frequencyTotal depths (ft)￼￼￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management: Water agenciesPublic PrivateReferences Cited￼￼Jennings, C. W. 1958. Geologic Map of California, Death Valley Sheet. Single Map Sheet, scale 1:250,000.Additional ReferencesBedinger, M.S., Sargent, K.A., and Langer, W.H. 1989. Studies of Geology and Hydrology in the Basin and Range Province, Southwestern United States, for Isolation of High-Level Radioactive Waste- Characterization of the Death Valley Region, Nevada and California. U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 1370-F, 49 p.California Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1964. Ground Water Occurrence and Quality, Lahontan Region, Bulletin 106-1._____. 1975. California’s Ground Water, Bulletin 118. 135 p. ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.Last update 2/27/04