South Lahontan Hydrologic Region Rhodes Hill Area Groundwater BasinRhodes Hill Area Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 6-86• County: Inyo• Surface Area: 15,600 acres (24.4 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThis groundwater basin underlies an east-trending valley in the Black Mountains and Ibex Hills of southern Inyo County. The basin is bounded on the south, west, and north by the Black Mountains, on the northeast by the Calico Peaks, and on the southeast by the Ibex Hills and Sheephead Mountain (Jennings and others 1962). Surface water is drained westward to Death Valley by Rhodes Wash. Average annual precipitation ranges up to six inches.Hydrogeologic InformationWater Bearing FormationsGroundwater in the basin is likely found in alluvium of Quaternary age. Such alluvium likely consists of unconsolidated, fine- to coarse-grained sand, pebbles, and boulders with variable amounts of silt and clay.Restrictive StructuresAn unnamed southeast trending fault crosses through the central portion of the basin. It is unknown if this fault is a barrier to groundwater movement.Recharge AreasRecharge to the basin is most likely from percolation of precipitation and runoff from the surrounding mountains.Groundwater Level TrendsUnknown.Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. Unknown. Groundwater in Storage. Unknown.Groundwater Budget (Type C)No information is available.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. Unknown. Impairments. Unknown.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
South Lahontan Hydrologic Region Rhodes Hill Area Groundwater BasinWell Production characteristics Well yields (gal/min)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationActive Monitoring DataAgencyDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water qualityTitle 22 water qualityNumber of wells /measurement frequencyTotal depths (ft)￼￼￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management: Water agenciesPublic PrivateReferences Cited￼￼Jennings, C. W., J. L. Burnett, B. W. Troxel. 1962. Geologic Map of California: Trona Sheet. Olaf P. Jenkins Edition. California Department of Conservation, Division of Mines and Geology. Scale 1: 250,000.Additional ReferencesCalifornia Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1964. Ground Water Occurrence andQuality Lahontan Region. Bulletin No.106-1. 439 p. _____. 1975. California’s Ground Water. Bulletin 118. 135 p.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.Last update 2/27/04