Central Coast Hydrologic Region Hernandez Valley Groundwater BasinHernandez Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 3-31• County: San Benito• Surface Area: 2,860 acres (4 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyHernandez Valley is a sparsely populated elongate northwest-southeast trending basin in the Coast Range Mountains of San Benito County. The elevation ranges from approximately 2,300 to 2,600 feet. The basin is comprised primarily of Quaternary alluvium and a small area of Quaternary nonmarine terrace deposits. It is bounded to the northeast by Pliocene marine rocks, to the northwest by the Franciscan Formation, and to the north by Lower Miocene marine sediments. To the south and southwest are Upper Cretaceous marine sediments (Jennings and Strand 1958). The Hernandez Reservoir occupies most of the lower portion of the basin. It is interesting to note that the Hernandez Reservoir is operated primarily for groundwater recharge in the lower reaches of the San Benito River. The San Benito River and its tributaries drain the valley northwestward toward Hollister. Average precipitation values range from 19 to 21 inches.Hydrogeologic InformationWater Bearing FormationsNo specific published information on the water bearing deposits was found. San Joaquin District well completion report files contain logs for nine wells in the basin. These wells range in depth from 20 to 160 feet. They appear to only penetrate alluvial material.Restrictive StructuresThe fact that Hernandez Reservoir occupies most of the basin precludes the use of significant areas for groundwater development and likely acts as a significant recharge source for the remaining area.Groundwater Level TrendsNo data was found regarding water level trends. The only water level data found were in well completion report files for wells drilled in 1950 that reported groundwater levels at six feet below the surface.Groundwater StorageNo published information on groundwater storage was found. The potential for abundant recharge from Hernandez Reservoir would indicate the basin is at maximum capacity.Groundwater Budget (Type C)There is no information to provide an estimate of this basin’s budget.Groundwater QualityNo groundwater quality information was found in the published literature or in DWR files.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Central Coast Hydrologic Region Hernandez Valley Groundwater BasinWell Production characteristics Well yields (gal/min)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationTotal depths (ft)Range: 20-160￼Active Monitoring DataAverage: 58 (DWR well completion reports)Number of wells /measurement frequency NKDNKD 0None None￼AgencyDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsNKD: No Known DataParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water quality Title 22 water quality￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management: Water agenciesPublic PrivateReferences Cited￼￼California Department of Water Resources (DWR), San Joaquin District. Well completion report files.Jennings, Charles W. and Rudolph G. Strand (compilers). 1958. Santa Cruz Sheet of Geologic Map of California. California Division of Mines and Geology (CDMG). Scale 1:250,000.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.Last update 2/27/04