Central Coast Hydrologic Region Salinas Valley Groundwater BasinSalinas Valley Groundwater Basin, Seaside Area Subbasin• Groundwater Basin Number: 3-4.08• County: Monterey• Surface Area: 25,900 acres (40 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Salinas Valley –Seaside Area Subbasin includes the coastal communities of Seaside and Marina as well as the western portion of the former Fort Ord. The western boundary is the extent of Quaternary sand dunes which form the shoreline of Monterey Bay. The northeast boundary is the 180/400 foot aquifer subbasin which is in the Salinas Valley proper. The southeastern boundary is the Corral de Tierra subbasin which is roughly the extent of Quaternary sand (Jennings and Strand 1956). Surface drainage within the subbasin is primarily internal to small depressions between the sand dunes. Very few streams exit the area. Average annual precipitation is approximately 17 inches along the coast to 15 inches inland.Hydrogeologic InformationWater Bearing FormationsFrom oldest to youngest, the water-bearing units of the subbasin are the Miocene/Pliocene Santa Margarita Formation, the Pliocene Paso Robles Formation, the Pleistocene Aromas Formation, and Pleistocene and Holocene age alluvial deposits (GTC 1984). These units have an aggregate maximum thickness of more than 1,000 feet (Muir 1982). Surface outcrops within the area are limited to alluvial sands and terrace deposits (Jennings and Strand 1956).The Santa Margarita Formation is a poorly consolidated marine sandstone. This unit is an important water-bearing formation in the subbasin. It underlies the Paso Robles Formation and has a maximum thickness of 225 feet (GTC 1984).The Paso Robles Formation is the major water-bearing unit in the Seaside area and consists of sand, gravel and clay interbedded with some minor calcareous beds (GTC 1984).Within the subbasin the Aromas Formation is grouped together with the dune sand deposits and are difficult to differentiate between the units. These units consist of relatively clean red to yellowish-brown, well sorted sand and are estimated to range in thickness from 30 to 50 feet near the coast to up to 200 feet inland (GTC 1984).Restrictive StructuresTwo anticlines, three synclines and at least five faults exist within the Seaside subbasin (GTC 1984 and DWR 1970). No evidence was found to indicate that these geologic structures have any effect on the movement of groundwater. Differences between horizontal and vertical conductivity is reported to result in partial confinement (Muir 1982).California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/041
Central Coast Hydrologic Region Salinas Valley Groundwater BasinRecharge AreasGroundwater recharge is from deep percolation of local precipitation, subsurface inflow from the Corral de Tierra subbasin to the east, and seepage of minor amounts from creeks (Muir 1982 and GTC 1984).Groundwater Level TrendsGroundwater level monitoring in production and monitoring wells within the subbasin have generally shown declines in the period from the 1960’s to the present. One well which is considered representative of the Northern Coastal and former Fort Ord areas has shown a general trend of water level decline of approximately 1 foot per year from the 1950’s to at least 1997 (Fugro West 1997).Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. The storage capacity of the subbasin was estimated to be 1,000,000 af based on the storage of 630,000 af of groundwater in the southern half of the subbasin(Muir 1982).Groundwater Budget (Type B)There are not enough data in the referenced literature to provide a detailed estimate of the subbasin’s groundwater budget. The lack of complete data on inflow, outflow, and aquifer transmissivities allow only general estimates. For the period from 1962 to 1979 inflow to the groundwater reservoir from rainfall was estimated by Muir (1982) to range from 0 to 15,200 af. Subsurface inflow was estimated by Thorup (1976) to be about 2000 af per year. Average pumpage from 1962-1979 is estimated at 3,600 af/yr, and the subbasin yield is estimated to be more than 6,400 af/yr and less than 7,700 af/yr (Muir 1982).Groundwater QualityCharacterization. The groundwater in this subbasin is characterized as a sodium-chloride type in the southern end of the subbasin to a sodium- barcarbonate type in the northern portion (Muir 1982). TDS values range from 191 to 890 mg/L, with an average value of 420 mg/L (based on 28 wells, DWR 1959). Title 22 water quality standards report a TDS range of 180 to 610 mg/L, with an average value of 408 (based on 10 analyses). No average EC values were found in the referenced literature, but an extreme value of 1,450 μmhos/cm was noted in one well.Impairments. Water from the Santa Margarita Formation is high in hydrogen-sulfide gas (Furgro 1997, Muir 1982). High levels of iron were found south of the City of Seaside (Muir 1982). Seawater intrusion is an ongoing problem in this subbasin.Water Quality in Public Supply WellsCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Constituent Group1Number of wells sampled2Number of wells with a concentration above an MCL3 13￼Inorganics – Primary 19 Radiological 21Last update 2/27/042
Central Coast Hydrologic Region Salinas Valley Groundwater BasinNitratesPesticidesVOCs and SOCs Inorganics – SecondaryCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼21                    020                    020                    019                    6￼1 A description of each member in the constituent groups and a generalized discussion of the relevance of these groups are included in California’s Groundwater – Bulletin 118 by DWR (2003).2 Represents distinct number of wells sampled as required under DHS Title 22 program from 1994 through 2000.3 Each well reported with a concentration above an MCL was confirmed with a second detection above an MCL. This information is intended as an indicator of the types of activities that cause contamination in a given basin. It represents the water quality at the sample location. It does not indicate the water quality delivered to the consumer. More detailed drinking water quality information can be obtained from the local water purveyor and its annual Consumer Confidence Report.Well CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationRange: – 100-3500Total depths (ft)Range: 32-1550 Range: 60 - 1090Average: 1,000 (DWR well records)Average: 326 (DWR well records) Average: 361 (DWR well records)￼Active Monitoring Data￼AgencyDWR (Including Cooperators) Department of Health Services and cooperatorsParameter Number of wells /measurement frequencyGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous 7 Annually (DWR 1967) water qualityTitle 22 water 24 Variesquality￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateThe Marina Coast Water District (MCWD) joined zone 2 and 2A of the Monterey County Water Resources Agency (MCWRA) in 1966Monterey County Water Resources Agency (MCWRA), Marina Coast Water District (MCWD), City of Seaside, Presidio of Monterey Annex.Marina Del Mar Water System, Messick Road WS#1￼￼Last update 2/27/043
Central Coast Hydrologic Region DRAFT Salinas Valley Groundwater BasinReferences CitedCalifornia Department of Water Resources. 1967. Monterey County Water Quality Investigation.Prepared for the Central Coastal Regional Water Quality Control Board. 150 p. plus plates.California Department of Water Resources. 1970. Sea Water Intrusion, Lower Salinas Valley. DWRProgress Report. 28 p. plus plates.Fugro West, Inc. 1997. Hydrogeologic Assessment, Seaside Coastal Groundwater Subareas, Phase IIIUpdate. Monterey County, California. 44 p. plus plates.Geotechnical Consultants, Inc. (GTC). 1984. Hydrogeologic Update: Fort Ord Military Reservation andVicinity. Monterey County, California. Prepared for the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers.Jennings, C.W. and Strand, R.G. 1956. Geologic Map of California, Santa Cruz Sheet. Scale 1:250,000.Muir, K.S. (U.S. Geological Survey). 1982. Ground Water in the Seaside Area, Monterey County,California. Water Resources Investigations 82-10. 37 p.Thorup, R.R., 1976, Groundwater Study of Highway 68; Monterey, California. 57p.Additional ReferencesAli Taghavi Associates (ATI). 2000. Update of the Historical Benefits Analysis (HBA), HydrologicInvestigation in the Arroyo Seco Cone Area. Final Technical Memorandum. Prepared for theMonterey County Water Resources Agency (MCWRA).California Department of Water Resources, San Joaquin District. 1973. Sea Water Intrusion, LowerSalinas Valley, Monterey County. 91 p. plus plates.California Department of Water Resources, San Joaquin District. 1984. Land and Water Resources,Monterey County, District Report. 34 p.Montgomery Watson. 1994. Salinas River Basin Water Resources Management Plan, Task 1.09 SalinasValley Groundwater Flow and Quality Model Report. Prepared for the Monterey County WaterResources Agency (MCWRA).ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼4/15/04