Central Coast Hydrologic Region Salinas Valley Groundwater BasinSalinas Valley Groundwater Basin, Eastside Aquifer Subbasin• Groundwater Basin Number: 3-4.02• County: Monterey• Surface Area: 57,500 acres (90 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Eastside Aquifer subbasin extends from approximately five miles north of the city of Salinas to twenty-five miles south to the town of Gonzales along the eastern side of the lower Salinas Valley. The subbasin is bounded to the north by the Pleistocene Aromas Red Sands of the Salinas Valley – Langley Area Subbasin. To the south, the subbasin shares a boundary with Quaternary Alluvium and Terrace deposits of the Salinas Valley – Lower Forebay Aquifer Subbasin. The western subbasin boundary generally coincides with the northeastern limit of confining conditions in the adjacent 180/400-Foot Aquifer subbasin (DWR 1946a) and with the location of State Highway 101. The eastern boundary is the contact of Quaternary Terrace deposits with granitic rocks of the Gabilan Range. The subbasin boundaries are generally correlative with those of the East Side subarea of the Monterey County Water Resources Agency (MCWRA). Intermittent streams such as Natividad, Alisal, Quail, Parsons, Muddy and Johnson Creeks drain the western slopes of the Gabilan Range and flow across the Subbasin toward the Salinas River on the west side of the Valley. Average annual precipitation is 13 inches.Hydrogeologic InformationThe Salinas Valley is surrounded by the Gabilan Range on the east, by the Sierra de Salinas and Santa Lucia Range on the west, and is drained by the Salinas River, which empties into Monterey Bay on the north. The King City (Rinconda-Reliz) Fault (Durbin 1978) generally follows the western margin of the Valley from King City in the south to Monterey Bay in the north. Valley-side down, normal movement along the fault allowed the deposition of an asymmetric, westward thickening alluvial wedge. The Salinas Valley has been filled with 10,000 to 15,000 feet of Tertiary and Quaternary marine and terrestrial sediments that include up to 2,000 feet of saturated alluvium (Showalter 1984). Above the generally non-water bearing and consolidated granitic basement, Miocene age Monterey and Pliocene age Purisima Formations are water bearing strata within the Plio-Pleistocene age Paso Robles Formation and within Pleistocene to Holocene alluvium.Water Bearing FormationsThe primary water-bearing units of this subbasin are the same units that produce water in the adjacent 180/400-Foot Aquifer subbasin – namely, the 180-Foot Aquifer and the 400-Foot Aquifer. However, the near-surface confining unit (Salinas Aquitard) does not extend into the Eastside or other subbasins. Groundwater in the Eastside Aquifer subbasin is semi-confined to unconfined and occurs in lenses of sand and gravel that are interbedded with massive units of finer grained material (Durbin 1970).California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Central Coast Hydrologic Region Salinas Valley Groundwater BasinThe thickness of the 180-foot aquifer varies from 50 to 150 feet in the Salinas Valley, with an average 100 feet (MW 1994; DWR 1970). Because of the westward thickening of alluvial units in the Salinas Valley (Showalter 1984), the average thickness in the Eastside subbasin is probably less than that stated above. The 180-Foot Aquifer may be in part correlative to older portions of Quaternary terrace deposits or the upper Aromas Red Sands. The 180-Foot Aquifer is separated from the 400-Foot Aquifer by a zone of discontinuous sands and blue clays called the 180/400-foot Aquiclude (MW 1998) which ranges in thickness from 10 to 70 feet.More recent studies suggest the 400-Foot Aquifer exist not only in the 180/400-Foot Aquifer subbasin, but also in the Eastside Aquifer and Lower Forebay Aquifer subbasins (MW 1994). The 400-foot aquifer has an average thickness of 200 feet and consists of sands, gravels, and clay lenses (LHI 1985). The upper portion of the aquifer may be correlative with the Aromas Red Sands and the lower portion with the upper part of the Paso Robles Formation (MW 1994).Later reports term the 180-Foot Aquifer and the 400-Foot Aquifer the “shallow zone” and “deep zone”, respectively, in the Eastside and in the Upper and Lower Forebay subbasins (MW 1998).An additional a deeper aquifer (also referred to as the 900-Foot Aquifer or the Deep Aquifer) is present in the lower Salinas Valley. A blue marine clay aquitard also separates this aquifer from the overlying 400-Foot Aquifer. This deeper aquifer consists of alternating layers of sand-gravel mixtures and clays (up to 900 feet thick), rather than a distinct aquifer and aquitard (MW 1994). The Deep Aquifer has experienced little development except near the coast where it is used to replace groundwater from the 180- and 400-Foot Aquifers rendered unusable by seawater intrusion; water quality and yield data are scarce.MW (1994) estimated specific yields for the three main aquifers in the Salinas Valley for their Integrated Ground and Surface Water Model (IGSM). The estimated values for the 180-Foot, 400-Foot, and Deep Aquifers were 8-16 percent, 6 percent, and 6 percent, respectively. An average weighted specific yield of 8.8 percent was derived for three depth zones within the interval 20 to 200 feet below grade by the SWRB (1955). Yates (1988) estimated a storage coefficient of 0.0285 in the northern subbasin and 0.030 in the southern subbasin.Groundwater quality issues primarily stem from long-term agricultural production in the Salinas Valley that has contributed to an extensive non- point source nitrate problem. Nitrate concentrations in many wells in the Valley exceed drinking water standards (DWR 1970), including in wells throughout the Eastside Aquifer subbasin (MCWRA 1997).Restrictive StructuresGroundwater flow is generally in a down-valley direction but extensive pumping has created a long-lasting groundwater table depression near the Valley margin in the northern subbasin northeast of Salinas. Flow is now from the north, west and south into the depression. Average groundwaterCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Central Coast Hydrologic Region Salinas Valley Groundwater Basindepths at the depression were up to 50 feet below sea level from 1970 to 1981 (Yates 1988). During Fall 1995, the deepest portion of the depression was over 80 feet below sea level (MCWRA 1997). The linear depression may result from the restriction of groundwater flow caused by the presence of a northwest trending buried fault. Groundwater elevations decrease from the east to the west by over 130 feet within a distance of one mile as this buried structure is crossed (Showalter 1984).Recharge AreasHistorically, subbasin recharge was from percolation from stream channels that head on the west slopes of the Gabilan Range (DWR 1946a) and from subsurface inflow from rainfall percolated through the Aromas Red Sands deposits in the adjacent Langley Area subbasin to the north (Yates 1988). With the advent of large-scale groundwater pumping over the past 50 years, recharge now is primarily from subsurface flow from the subbasins to the south and west.Groundwater Level TrendsBetween 1964 and 1974, the amount of groundwater in storage increased 86,500 af. This increase slowed to 15,100 af between 1974 and 1984. From 1984 to 1994, the increasing trend reversed, and the amount of water in storage dropped by 155,000 af (MW 1998).Groundwater StorageCalculations made by DWR (2000) give an estimated total storage capacity of 3,690,000 af for the subbasin. As of 1994, there is approximately 2,560,000 af of groundwater in storage in this subbasin (MW 1998).Groundwater Budget (Type A)A detailed groundwater budget was available for this subbasin for 1994 (MW 1998). Natural recharge (including applied water recharge) is estimated to be 41,000 af. There is no artificial recharge. Subsurface inflow is approximately 17,000 af. Annual urban and agricultural extractions total 86,000 af. There are no other extractions or subsurface outflow.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. The water in this subbasin is of a sodium-calcium chloride type, with the salts derived from marine formations in the subbasin watershed (JSA 1990). Based on 129 analyses, TDS values range from 168 to 977 mg/L, with an average value of 450 (DHS 2000). The Department of Health Services monitors Title 22 water quality standards, and in 25 public supply wells they report TDS values ranging from 240 to 788 mg/L, with an average value of 413 mg/L (DHS 2000). DHS also report 128 analyses that give EC values ranging from 52 to 1,600 μmhos/cm, with an average value of 693 μmhos/cm (DHS 2000).Impairments. Of 68 wells sampled for nitrates in 1995, 32 exceeded the drinking water standard of 45 mg/L. The average concentration was 69 mg/L (MCWRA 1997).California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Central Coast Hydrologic Region Salinas Valley Groundwater BasinWater Quality in Public Supply WellsCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Constituent Group1Inorganics – Primary RadiologicalNitratesPesticidesVOCs and SOCs Inorganics – SecondaryNumber of wells sampled2 2830 28 30 30 28Number of wells with a concentration above an MCL3 00 2 0 0 4￼￼1 A description of each member in the constituent groups anddiscussion of the relevance of these groups are included in California’s Groundwater – Bulletin 118 by DWR (2003).2 Represents distinct number of wells sampled as required under DHS Title 22 program from 1994 through 2000.3 Each well reported with a concentration above an MCL was confirmed with a second detection above an MCL. This information is intended as an indicator of the types of activities that cause contamination in a given basin. It represents the water quality at the sample location. It does not indicate the water quality delivered to the consumer. More detailed drinking water quality information can be obtained from the local water purveyor and its annual Consumer Confidence Report.Well Production characteristics Well yields (gal/min)a generalized￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationTotal depths (ft)Range: 299 - 1,100Average: 610 (12 Well Completion Reports)￼Active Monitoring Data￼AgencyMCWRA MCWRADepartment of Health Services (incl Cooperators)ParameterGroundwater levelsMineral, nutrient, & minor element. Title 22 water qualityNumber of wells /measurement frequency 74 Varies (Geomatrix 2001)67 Annually (Geomatrix 2001) 53 Varies￼Last update 2/27/04
Central Coast Hydrologic Region Salinas Valley Groundwater BasinBasin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateReferences CitedCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼MCWRA requires annual extraction reports form all agricultural and municipal well operators; and has researched, developed and/or constructed projects to reduce seawater intrusion, manage nitrate contamination in the ground water, provide adequate water supplies to meet current and future needs, and tohydrologically balance the ground water basin in the Salinas Valley.Monterey County Water Resources AgencyCalifornia Water Service Co. (CWS)– Salinas; Alco Water Service; Gabilan Water Co.￼￼California Department of Health Services (DHS). 2000. California Water Quality Monitoring Database. Division of Drinking Water and Environmental Management, Sacramento [on CD-ROM].Department of Public Works, Division of Water Resources (DWR). 1946a. Bulletin 52, Salinas Basin Investigation. 230 p.________. 1970. Sea-Water Intrusion, Lower Salinas Valley. Progress Report. 28 p + maps.________. San Joaquin District unpublished calculation using specific yield and area data.Durbin, TJ, Kapple, GW, and Freckleton, JR. 1978. Two-Dimensional and Three- Dimensional Digital Flow Models of the Salinas Valley Ground-Water Basin, California. US Geological Survey. Water Resources Investigations Report 78-113. Prepared in cooperation with the US Army Corps of Engineers. 134 p.Geomatrix Consultants. 2001. Evaluation of the Salinas Valley Groundwater Monitoring Network and Proposed Redesign. Prepared for the Monterey County Water Resources Agency.Jones & Stokes Associates, Inc. (JSA). 1990. Salinas Valley Seawater Intrusion Program, Draft Environmental Impact Report/Environmental Impact Statement. Prepared for the Monterey County Water Resources Agency, the Monterey Regional Water Pollution Control Agency, and the U.S. Bureau of Reclamation.Leedshill-Herkenhoff, Inc.(LHI). 1985. Salinas Valley Seawater Intrusion Study, prepared for the Monterey County Flood Control and Water Conservation District.Monterey County Water Resources Agency (MCWRA). 1997. Water Resources Data Report, Water Year 1994-1995. 96 p.Montgomery-Watson Consulting Engineers (MW). 1994. Salinas River Basin Water Resources Management Plan Task 1.09 Salinas Valley Groundwater Flow and Quality Model Report. Prepared for Monterey County Water Resources Agency.________. 1998. Salinas Valley Historical Benefits Analysis (HBA), Final Report, April 1998. Prepared for the Monterey County Water Resources Agency.Showalter, P, Akers, J., and Swain, LA. 1983. Design of a Ground Water quality Monitoring Network for the Salinas River Basin, California. US Geological Survey Water Resources Investigation Report 83-4049. 74 p.State Water Resources Board (SWRB). 1955. Bulletin No. 19, Salinas River Basin Investigation. 225 p.Yates, EB. 1988. Simulated Effects of Ground-Water Management Alternatives for the Salinas Valley, California. US Geological Survey. Water Resources InvestigationsLast update 2/27/04
Central Coast Hydrologic Region Salinas Valley Groundwater BasinReport 87-4066. Prepared in cooperation with the Monterey County Flood Control and Water Conservation District. 79 p.Additional ReferencesBoyle Engineering Corporation. 1987. Salinas Valley Ground Water Model, Alternative Analysis, Final Report. Prepared for the Monterey County Flood Control and Water Conservation District.Department of Public Works, Division of Water Resources (DWR). 1946b. Bulletin 52-B, Salinas Basin Investigation, Summary Report. 46 p.________. 1969a. Geology of the Lower Portion, Salinas Valley Ground Water Basin. Office Report. Central District Office. 18 p.________. 1969b. Salinas River Basin Special Investigation, Water Quality Investigations Memorandum Report. Prepared for the Central Coastal Regional Water Quality Control Board. 67 p.________. 1971. Nitrates in Ground Waters of the Central Coast Area. Memorandum Report. San Joaquin District Office. 16 p.________. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. Bulletin 118-80.________. 1988. 1986 Monitoring Program for the Salinas Valley Ground Water Basin. Report to the State Water Resources Control Board. Task Order 1. Interagency Agreement 4-134-350. 28 p.________. 1994. Bulletin 160-93. California Water Plan Update, Vol. 1.Greene, HG. 1970. Geology of Southern Monterey Bay and its Relationship to the Ground-Water Basin and Seawater Intrusion. US Geological Survey Open File Report. 50 p.Jennings, Charles W and Rudolph G Strand (compilers). 1959. Santa Cruz Sheet of Geologic Map of California. California Division of Mines and Geology (CDMG). Scale 1:250,000.Johnson, MJ. 1983. Ground Water in North Monterey County, California. US Geological Survey Water-Resources Investigations Report 83-4023.Monterey County Water Resources Agency (MCWRA). 1996. Summary Report: 1995 Groundwater Extraction Data and Agricultural Water Conservation Practices. 8 p.State Water Resources Board (SWRB). 1953. Bulletin No. 5, Santa Cruz-Monterey Counties Investigation. 230 p.State Water Resources Control Board, Regional Water Quality Control Board, Central Coast Region (SWRCB). 1989. Water Quality Control Plan - Central Coast Basin.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04