Central Coast Hydrologic Region Rafael Valley Groundwater BasinRafael Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 3-46• County: San Luis Obispo• Surface Area: 2,990 acres (4.7 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyRafael Valley Groundwater Basin underlies Rafael Valley in southeastern San Luis Obispo County. This basin is bounded by Cretaceous and Miocene age marine rocks (Jennings 1958). The valley is drained by Rafael and San Juan Creeks. The basin is generally parallel to, and is crossed by the Chimeneas fault (Jennings 1958). Precipitation ranges from 8 to 10 inches per year.Hydrogeologic InformationWater Bearing FormationsQuaternary age alluvium is the principal water-bearing unit in this basin.Restrictive StructuresThe Chimeneas fault crosses the basin (Jennings 1958), but it is not known whether or not this fault is a groundwater barrier.Recharge AreasNo information is available.Groundwater Level TrendsNo information is available.Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. No information is available. Groundwater in Storage. No information is available.Groundwater Budget (Type C)No information is available.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. No information is available. Impairments. No information is available.Well Production characteristics Well yields (gal/min)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationRange: Average:Total depths (ft)Range: Average: Range: Average:￼Last update 2/27/04
Central Coast Hydrologic Region California’s Groundwater Rafael Valley Groundwater Basin Bulletin 118Active Monitoring Data￼￼AgencyDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsParameter Number of wells /measurement frequencyGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water qualityTitle 22 water quality￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management: Water agenciesPublic San Luis Obispo County - Department of Public WorksPrivateReferences CitedJennings, C.W. 1958. Geologic Map of California; San Luis Obispo Sheet. Olaf P. Jenkins edition. Scale 1:250,000.Additional ReferencesCalifornia Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1958. San Luis Obispo CountyInvestigation. Bulletin 18. 288 p., Southern District. 1986. San Luis Obispo County Master Water Plan Update.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.￼￼￼Last update 2/27/04