Central Coast Hydrologic Region Big Spring Area Groundwater BasinBig Spring Area Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 3-47• County: San Luis Obispo• Surface Area: 7,320 acres (11.4 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyBig Spring Area Groundwater Basin underlies a valley in southern San Luis Obispo County. The basin is bounded by Miocene age marine rocks (Jennings 1958). The valley is drained by a tributary to San Juan Creek. Precipitation ranges from 8 to 10 inches per year.Hydrogeologic InformationWater Bearing FormationsThe main water-bearing unit is Quaternary age alluvium.Restrictive StructuresNo information is available.Recharge AreasNo information is available.Groundwater Level TrendsNo information is available.Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. No information is available. Groundwater in Storage. No information is available.Groundwater Budget (Type C)No information is available.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. No information is available. Impairments. No information is available.Well Production characteristics Well yields (gal/min)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationRange: Average:Total depths (ft)Range: Average: Range: Average:￼Last update 2/27/04
Central Coast Hydrologic Region Big Spring Area Groundwater BasinActive Monitoring DataCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼AgencyDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water quality Title 22 water qualityNumber of wells /measurement frequency￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management: Water agencies￼Public San Luis Obispo County - Department of Public WorksPrivateReferences CitedJennings, C.W. 1958. Geologic Map of California; San Luis Obispo Sheet. Olaf P. Jenkins edition. Scale 1:250,000.Additional ReferencesCalifornia Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1958. San Luis Obispo CountyInvestigation. Bulletin 18. 288 p., Southern District. 1986. San Luis Obispo County Master Water Plan Update.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.￼￼Last update 2/27/04