Central Coast Hydrologic Region Montecito Groundwater BasinMontecito Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 3-49• County: Santa Barbara• Surface Area: 6,270 acres (9.8 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Montecito Groundwater Basin is bounded on the north by the Santa Ynez Mountains and the Arroyo Parida fault, on the east by consolidated rocks, on the southeast by the Fernald fault, and on the northeast by a surface drainage divide that separates the Montecito and Carpinteria Groundwater Basins (DWR 1999). The offshore Rincon Creek fault and the Pacific Ocean bound the basin on the south. An administrative boundary on the west separates the Montecito Groundwater Basin from the Santa Barbara Groundwater Basin. The area overlying the basin is drained by several small creeks that flow from the Santa Ynez Mountains south to the Pacific Ocean. Precipitation ranges from 17 to 21 inches per year.Hydrogeologic InformationWater Bearing FormationsThe primary water-bearing deposits in the Montecito Groundwater Basin are the unconsolidated alluvial deposits, and the Casitas and Santa Barbara Formations (Montecito Water 1998). The specific yield for unconfined materials in the basin is estimated at 11 percent (DWR 1999).Alluvial Deposits. Holocene age alluvium consists of lenses of gravel, sand, silt, and clay. These deposits occur along stream channels and range to 80 feet thick (DWR 1999). Pleistocene age alluvium is composed of boulders and reddish clay, which, where saturated, yields only modest amounts of water to wells (DWR 1999). Groundwater is generally unconfined within alluvial deposits.Casitas Formation. The Pleistocene age Casitas Formation consists of clay, silt, sand, and gravel. Groundwater is extracted mainly from the upper Casitas Formation, as it is the chief water-bearing deposit; the lower Casitas Formation is very fine-grained and displays poor water transmitting characteristics (Montecito Water 1998). Groundwater in this formation is partially confined along the north side of the Arroyo Parida fault in the northern part of the basin and also inland from the southern part of the basin (DWR 1999).Santa Barbara Formation. The Pliocene to Pleistocene age Santa Barbara Formation consists of marine sand, silt, and clay and has a maximum thickness of 1,200 feet in the southern part of the basin (Hoover 1980). Groundwater within the Santa Barbara Formation is generally confined (Freckleton 1989). This formation occurs only in a restricted area in the southwest portion of the basin and, thus, is of negligible use as a groundwater source (DWR 1999).California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Central Coast Hydrologic Region Montecito Groundwater BasinRestrictive StructuresThe offshore Rincon Creek fault is an effective barrier to seawater intrusion into the deeper water-bearing zones (Montecito Water 1998). The east- trending Arroyo Parida and Montecito faults are barriers to groundwater movement within the Montecito Groundwater Basin.Recharge AreasNatural recharge in the basin is derived from infiltration of precipitation over the basin, seepage from streams, and subsurface inflow from consolidated rocks (DWR 1999).Groundwater Level TrendsHydrographs show that water levels generally increased or remained steady from 1992 through 1998 (DWR 1999).Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. The storage capacity above sea level is estimated at 14,490 af (Montecito Water 1998). The total storage capacity of the basin has been estimated at 281,000 af (Muir 1968; DWR 1975).Groundwater in Storage. The amount of groundwater in storage is estimated at 14,400 af (SBCWA 2001).Groundwater Budget (Type A)Montecito Water District pumps about 700 af/yr of groundwater (Montecito Water 2001). However, the amount pumped by private well owners is unknown. Annual natural recharge is approximately 1,614 af/yr (Montecito Water 1998). The average annual stream seepage rate is estimated at 764 af/yr, and the average annual infiltration of rainfall is estimated at 500 af/yr (Montecito Water 1998). The long-term average subsurface inflow is approximately 250 af/yr. The long-term average deep percolation of irrigation water is estimated at 100 af/yr (Montecito Water 1998).Groundwater QualityCharacterization. The groundwater in the Montecito Basin is of two chemical types. South of the Arroyo Parida fault, groundwater has calcium bicarbonate character, however, north of the fault it has sodium sulfate character. TDS concentration ranges from 600 to 1,100 mg/L (Montecito Water 1998). Analyses of data from four public supply wells show an average TDS of 698 mg/L in the basin with a range from 526 to 778 mg/L.Impairments. Iron and manganese concentrations in wells exceed Federal standards (Montecito Water 1998). During 1990, some wells yielded groundwater samples containing high chloride concentrations that exceed State limits. However, no wells are confirmed to be affected by seawater intrusion (Montecito Water 1998).California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Central Coast Hydrologic Region Montecito Groundwater BasinWater Quality in Public Supply WellsCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Constituent Group1Inorganics – Primary RadiologicalNitratesPesticidesVOCs and SOCs Inorganics – SecondaryNumber of wells sampled2 1415 16 5 5 14Number of wells with a concentration above an MCL3 00 2 0 0 8￼￼1 A description of each member in the constituent groups anddiscussion of the relevance of these groups are included in California’s Groundwater – Bulletin 118 by DWR (2003).2 Represents distinct number of wells sampled as required under DHS Title 22 program from 1994 through 2000.3 Each well reported with a concentration above an MCL was confirmed with a second detection above an MCL. This information is intended as an indicator of the types of activities that cause contamination in a given basin. It represents the water quality at the sample location. It does not indicate the water quality delivered to the consumer. More detailed drinking water quality information can be obtained from the local water purveyor and its annual Consumer Confidence Report.Well Production characteristics Well yields (gal/min)a generalized￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationRange: to 1,000 gal/minTotal depths (ft)Range: 146 – 450 ft.Range: 420 – 634 ft.Average: 750 gal/min (DWR 1975)Average: 297 ft (8 well completion reports)Average: 504 ft (4 well completion reports)￼Active Monitoring Data￼AgencyMontecito Water DistrictUS Geological SurveyDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsParameterNumber of wells/measurement frequencyGroundwater levels 88/biannually Groundwater levels 2Title 22 water 4 quality￼Last update 2/27/04
Central Coast Hydrologic Region Montecito Groundwater BasinBasin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateReferences CitedCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼The Montecito Water District has adopted an AB3030 management plan (SBCWA 2001).Montecito Water District, Santa Barbara County Water Agency￼California Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1975. Sea-Water Intrusion in California: Inventory of Coastal Ground Water Basins. Bulletin 63-5., Southern District. 1999. Evaluation of Groundwater Overdraft in the Southern Central Coast Region, Part 2. Technical Information Record SD-99-2, 116 p.Freckleton, J. R. 1989. Geohydrology of the Foothill Ground-Water Basin Near Santa Barbara, California. U. S. Geological Survey Water-Resources Investigations Report 89- 4017.Hoover, M. F. 1980. Safe Yield Evaluation of the Montecito Basin and Toro Canyon Area: prepared for the Montecito Water District, 40 p. Quoted in (DWR 1999). Evaluation of Groundwater Overdraft in the Southern Central Coast Region, Part 2. Technical Information Record SD-99-2, 116 p.Montecito Water District (Montecito Water). 1998. Groundwater Basin Management Plan for the Montecito Water District. 70 p.. 2001. District Facilities: Sources of Water. http://www.montecitowater.com/Sources_of_water.htm (August 2001).Muir, K.S. 1968. Ground-Water Reconnaissance of the Santa Barbara-Montecito area, Santa Barbara County, California. U.S. Geological Survey Water Supply Paper 1859-A. Quoted in Toups Corporation (1974). Water Resources Management Study: South Coast – Santa Barbara County, a report prepared for the ad hoc committee on water supply: Santa Ana, California, Toups Corporation, 219 p.Santa Barbara County Water Agency (SBCWA). 2001. 2000 Santa Barbara Groundwater Report. 53 p.Toups Corporation. 1974. Water Resources Management Study: South Coast – Santa Barbara County, a report prepared for the ad hoc committee on water supply: Santa Ana, California, Toups Corporation, 219 p.Additional ReferencesCalifornia Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1975. California’s Ground Water. Bulletin 118.Frost, K. 1990. Montecito Water District Service Area. Scale 1:24,000, 1 map.Huber, W. L. 1927. Memoranda to California State Engineer on Progress of Construction of Buell Dam, Montecito County Water District, Santa Barbara County, California. 1 envelopeLippincott, J. B. 1913-1922. Reports and data concerning Montecito Valley water supply. Santa Barbara Resource Management Department. 1989. Montecito Water District Supply-Demand, (various pagings).Santa Barbara County Surveyor's Office, Map Dept. 1960. Map Showing Boundaries ofMontecito County Water District. Scale 1:15,000, 1 map.￼￼￼Last update 2/27/04
Central Coast Hydrologic Region Montecito Groundwater BasinSchuyler, J. D. 1888. Letter report to George H. Gould, President of Montecito Valley Water Company Regarding the Upper Reservoir. 1 leaf.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04