Central Coast Hydrologic Region Needle Rock Point Groundwater BasinNeedle Rock Point Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 3-52• County: Santa Cruz• Surface Area: 480 acres (1 square mile)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyNeedle Rock Point Groundwater Basin is comprised of marine terrace deposits generally seaward (south) of Highway 1 to the Pacific Ocean near Needle Rock Point. Elevation ranges from 60 to 100 feet above sea level. The marine terrace deposits are Pleistocene in age and are surrounded by Middle Miocene Marine rocks (Jennings 1958). The basin boundary confidence is considered low due to undetermined depth of the terrace deposits and the lack of information regarding groundwater occurrence or movement. Average precipitation values are approximately 29inches.Hydrogeologic InformationWater Bearing FormationsNo specific published information on the water bearing units was found. A review of San Joaquin District well completion report files found fourteen well reports in the basin. Depths of these wells ranged from 112 to 850 feet below the land surface and averaged 310 feet deep. The well records show unconsolidated material (sands, silts, clays and gravels) to an average depth of 250 feet with hard rock below this depth. Seven well reports listed well yields. These yields ranged from 200 to 450 gallons per minute and averaged 319 gallons per minute. Of the fourteen wells in the basin, eleven are reported as being used for irrigation, one for domestic uses and two were test holes.Groundwater Level TrendsWater level data found was limited to depth to water at the time wells were drilled and varied over the years. Water levels ranged from 20 to 145 feet. No information on the groundwater level trends is available.Groundwater StorageNo information on groundwater storage was found.Groundwater Budget (Type C)There is no information to provide an estimate of this basin’s budget.Groundwater QualityNo information on groundwater quality was found. Seawater intrusion is a likely hazard within this basin due to the proximity of the ocean.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Central Coast Hydrologic Region Needle Rock Point Groundwater BasinWell CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationRange: 200 – 450Total depths (ft)One well at 300 Range: 112 - 850Average: 320 (6 wells)Average:Average: 333 (11 wells)￼Active Monitoring Data￼AgencyDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water qualityTitle 22 water qualityNumber of wells /measurement frequency 00 0￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management: None Water agenciesPublic None Private NoneReferences Cited￼￼California Department of Water Resources (DWR), San Joaquin District. Well completion report files.Jennings, Charles W. and Rudolph G. Strand (compilers). 1958. Santa Cruz Sheet of Geologic Map of California. California Division of Mines and Geology (CDMG). Scale 1:250,000.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.Last update 2/27/04