Central Coast Hydrologic Region Foothill Groundwater BasinFoothill Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 3-53• County: Santa Barbara• Surface Area: 3,120 acres (4.9 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyFoothill Groundwater Basin consists of unconsolidated Pliocene and younger sedimentary deposits underlying the coastal plain near Santa Barbara. The basin is bounded on the north and northeast by Tertiary sedimentary rocks of the Santa Ynez Mountains, on the northwest by the Goleta fault, on the southwest by the Modoc and Mesa faults, on the south by the More Ranch fault, and on the southeast by the Mission Ridge fault. Consolidated marine sedimentary rocks underlie the groundwater basin (Freckleton 1989) and are nearly impermeable except where fractured (Martin and Berenbrock 1986). Precipitation varies across the basin from 17 to 19 inches. All subsequent information is derived from Freckleton (1989) except where noted.Hydrogeologic InformationWater Bearing FormationsThe primary unconsolidated water-bearing deposits are alluvium and the Santa Barbara Formation. It is estimated that the specific yield of saturated materials ranges from 7.5 to 17.5 percent in this basin (Muir 1968). In the unconfined portion of the basin, the average specific yield is estimated to be 9.7 percent (DWR 1999).Alluvium. Holocene age alluvium, which consists of gravel, sand, silt, and clay, extends along the major streams and adjoining canyons. Groundwater in the Holocene age alluvium is generally unconfined. Pleistocene age alluvium, which consists of gravel, sand, silt, and clay, reaches a thickness of 400 feet in the eastern part of the basin. Groundwater in the Pleistocene age alluvium is generally unconfined except along the southernmost margin of the basin.Santa Barbara Formation. The Late Pliocene to Early Pleistocene age Santa Barbara Formation, which is the main water-bearing unit, consists mainly of massive, unconsolidated marine deposits of sand, silt, and clay and ranges to 400 feet thick. It is overlain by alluvium everywhere except where it crops out south of the Goleta fault. Groundwater within the Santa Barbara Formation is generally confined except along the northern margins of the basin.Restrictive StructuresThe Modoc, Goleta, More Ranch, Mesa, and Mission Ridge faults act as barriers that impede groundwater flow in and out of the basin. However, the Modoc, Mesa, and Mission Ridge faults are not believed to restrict the flow of groundwater within the unfaulted Holocene alluvial deposits. In the Santa Barbara Formation, groundwater is confined by a zone of low permeability found in the upper part of the formation. The confining zone, which rangesCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Central Coast Hydrologic Region Foothill Groundwater Basinin thickness from a few feet to more than 100 feet, separates the water- producing zones in the Santa Barbara Formation from the water-bearing units in the overlying alluvium; groundwater is unconfined where the low permeability zone is missing.Recharge AreasNatural recharge in the basin is derived from infiltration of precipitation, seepage from streams, and subsurface inflow from consolidated rocks of the Santa Ynez Mountains. Water imported from Lake Cachuma provides additional recharge. Older alluvium, which is found in large portions of the recharge area, allows infiltration of water into the underlying Santa Barbara Formation.Groundwater Level TrendsGroundwater levels declined by more than 60 feet during periods of heavy pumping in the early 1950s, but rose from the mid-1950s through the late 1970s. Increased pumping during 1984 through 1987 likely caused a decline in water levels observed then. Hydrographs show a steady increase in groundwater levels for 1991 through 1996 (DWR 1999). Water levels remained relatively stable during 1996 and 1997, primarily because of the wet winters of 1993 and 1995 (SBCWA 2001). Shallow wells exhibited slight declines during the moderate winters of water years 1998 through 2000, but some deep wells continued to show a rise in water levels (SBCWA 2001) and levels reached historical highs in 2001 (Mack 2001).Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. No information is available. Groundwater in Storage. SBCWA (2001) estimated the available usablestorage to be 5,000 acre-feet per year for water year 1999 through 2000.Groundwater Budget (Type A)Streamflow recharge is estimated to range from 160 to 460 af/yr. Subsurface inflow is estimated to range from 25 to 300 af/yr. Groundwater pumpage for the Foothill Groundwater Basin ranged from 160 to 2,400 af/yr for the years 1935 through 1987. Groundwater discharge as underflow was estimated to be about 280 af in 1985. The pumpage of the basin is estimated to be 945 af/yr (SBCWA 2001). Recharge from infiltration of precipitation is estimated at 320 af/yr (Muir 1968).Groundwater QualityCharacterization. SBCWA (2001) cited the total dissolved solid concentrations as ranging from 610 to 1,000 mg/L in 7 wells. Analyses of data from 7 public supply wells show an average TDS of 228 mg/L in the basin with a range from 554 to 1,118 mg/L.Impairments. Two of the wells monitored by USGS in the Foothill Groundwater Basin exceeded the primary MCL of 10 mg/L for nitrate- nitrogen. Nitrate-nitrogen concentration ranged from less than 0.1 to 12 mg/L in wells. High sulfate levels were also found in six wells.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Central Coast Hydrologic Region Foothill Groundwater BasinWater Quality in Public Supply WellsCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Constituent Group1Inorganics – Primary RadiologicalNitratesPesticidesVOCs and SOCs Inorganics – SecondaryNumber of wells sampled2 78 7 7 7 7Number of wells with a concentration above an MCL3 01 0 0 1 1￼￼1 A description of each member in the constituent groups anddiscussion of the relevance of these groups are included in California’s Groundwater – Bulletin 118 by DWR (2003).2 Represents distinct number of wells sampled as required under DHS Title 22 program from 1994 through 2000.3 Each well reported with a concentration above an MCL was confirmed with a second detection above an MCL. This information is intended as an indicator of the types of activities that cause contamination in a given basin. It represents the water quality at the sample location. It does not indicate the water quality delivered to the consumer. More detailed drinking water quality information can be obtained from the local water purveyor and its annual Consumer Confidence Report.Well Production characteristics Well yields (gal/min)a generalized￼Municipal/Irrigation DomesticMunicipal/IrrigationRange:Total depths (ft)Range: 290 ft.Range: 500 – 610 ftAverage:Average: 290 ft (1 well completion report)(DWR 1999)Average: 540 ft (3 well completion reports)(DWR 1999)￼Active Monitoring Data￼AgencyCity of Santa BarbaraU. S. Geological SurveyDepartment of Health ServicesParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water qualityTitle 22 water qualityNumber of wells /measurement frequency8 wells 7 wells￼Last update 2/27/04
Central Coast Hydrologic Region Foothill Groundwater BasinBasin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateReferences CitedCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼The City of Santa Barbara manages the basin.City of Santa Barbara, Santa Barbara County Water AgencyLa Cumbre Mutual Water Company, Sunset Mutual Water Company￼￼California Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1999. Evaluation of Groundwater Overdraft in the Southern Central Coast Region, Part 2. Technical Information Record SD-99-2, 116 p.Freckleton, J. R. 1989. Geohydrology of the Foothill Ground-Water Basin Near Santa Barbara, California. U. S. Geological Survey Water-Resources Investigations Report 89-4017.Mack, Steve. City of Santa Barbara. 2001. Email to Jennifer Wong. July 2001.Martin, P., and C. Berenbrock. 1986. Ground Water Monitoring at Santa Barbara, California: Phase 3-Development of a Three-Dimensional Digital Ground-Water Flow Model for Storage Unit I of the Santa Barbara Ground-Water Basin. U.S. Geological Survey Water Resources Investigations Report 86-4103.Muir, K.S. 1968. Ground-water Reconnaissance of the Santa Barbara-Montecito area, Santa Barbara County, California. U.S. Geological Survey Water Supply Paper 1859-A. Quoted in Todd, D. K. 1978. Groundwater Basin Data: Status and Needs, a report to the city of Santa Barbara, California: Berkeley, California. David Keith Todd Consulting Engineers, Inc., 94 p.Santa Barbara County Water Agency (SBCWA). 2001. 2000 Santa Barbara Groundwater Report. 53 p.Additional ReferencesArney, J. A., and H. D. Wilson. 1952. Water Levels in Observation Wells in Santa Barbara, County, California in 1951. U.S. Department of the Interior, Geological Survey, Ground Water Branch, Open-File Report, 57 p.Bader, J. S. 1969. Ground-Water Data as of 1967: Central Coast Subregion California. U. S. Department of the Interior, Geological Survey, Water Resources Division, Open-File Report, 16 p.Evenson, R. E. 1958. Water Levels in Observation Wells in Santa Barbara County, California, in 1957. U.S. Department of the Interior, Geological Survey, 46 p.Freckleton, J. R., P. Martin, and T. Nishikawa. 1998. Geohydrology of Storage Unit III and a Combined Flow Model of the Santa Barbara and Foothill Ground-Water Basins, Santa Barbara County, California. U. S. Geological Survey Water-Resources Investigations Report: 97-4121.Hsieh, P. A., and J. R. Freckleton. 1993. Documentation of a Computer Program to Simulate Horizontal-Flow Barriers Using the U.S. Geological Survey's Modular Three- Dimensional Finite-Difference Ground-Water Flow Model. U.S. Geological Survey Open-file report 92-477.Hutchinson, C. B. 1979. Ground-Water Monitoring at Santa Barbara, California: Phase 1 – Coastal Monitor-Well Installation and Initial Measurements. U.S. Geological Survey, Open-File Report 79-923, 24 p.Lamb, C. E., and M. J. Mermod. 1973. Ground-Water Data in Santa Barbara and Southern San Luis Obispo Counties, California: Spring 1970 to Spring 1973. U. S. Department of the Interior, Geological Survey, Water Resources Division, Open-File Report, 131 p.Last update 2/27/04
Central Coast Hydrologic Region Foothill Groundwater BasinLaRocque, G. A., Jr., and others. 1950. Wells and Water Levels in Principal Ground-Water Basins in Santa Barbara County, California. U.S. Geological Survey Water Supply Paper 1068.McFadden, M. C., K. G. Polinoski, and P. Martin. 1991. Measurement of Streamflow Gains and Losses on Mission Creek at Santa Barbara, California, July and September 1987. U.S. Geological Survey Water Resources Investigations Report 91-4002.Merritt, P. M. 1961. Water Levels in Observation Wells in Santa Barbara County, California, in 1960. U.S. Department of the Interior, Geological Survey, Ground Water Branch, 51 p.Miller, G. A. 1959. Water Levels in Observation Wells in Santa Barbara, County, California, in 1958. U.S. Department of the Interior, Geological Survey, 1959. 47 p.Muir, K. S. 1959. Water Levels in Observation Wells in Santa Barbara County, California, in 1959. U.S. Department of the Interior, Geological Survey, Open-File Report 60-102, 46 p.. 1963. Water Levels in Observation Wells in Santa Barbara County, California, 1962. U.S. Department of the Interior, Geological Survey, Water Resources Division, Open-file report 63-103 4006847674, 55 p.. 1964. Water Levels in Observation Wells in Santa Barbara County, California, 1963. U.S. Department of the Interior, Geological Survey, Water Resources Division, Open-file report.Muir, K. S., and P. M. Merritt. 1956. Water Levels in Observation Wells in Santa Barbara County, California, in 1955. U.S. Department of the Interior, Geological Survey, 69 p.. 1957. Water Levels in Observation Wells in Santa Barbara County, California, in 1956. U.S. Department of the Interior, Geological Survey, 68 p.Santa Barbara County Water Agency (SBCWA). 1999. 1999 Groundwater Report. 63 p. Upson, J. E. 1951. Geology and Ground-water Resources of the South-Coast Basins of SantaBarbara County, California. U.S. Geological Survey Water Supply Paper 1108.Warner, J. W. 1971. Ground Water in Santa Barbara and Southern San Luis Obispo Counties, California: Spring 1968 to Spring 1969. U. S. Department of the Interior, Geological Survey, Water Resources Division, Open-File Report, 24 p.. 1972. Ground Water in Santa Barbara and Southern San Luis Obispo Counties, California: Spring 1969 to Spring 1970. U. S. Department of the Interior, Geological Survey, Water Resources Division, Open-File Report, 27 p.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼￼￼￼Last update 2/27/04