Central Coast Hydrologic Region Dry Lake Valley Groundwater BasinDry Lake Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 3-29• County: San Benito• Surface Area: 1,420 acres (2 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyDry Lake Valley is a sparsely populated valley along the upper reaches of the San Benito River in San Benito County. The basin is approximately four miles long and generally less than one half mile wide. The elevation ranges from approximately 1,200 to 1,400 feet. The basin is mapped as Quaternary nonmarine terrace deposits. Middle and or lower Pliocene marine rocks bound the basin on both sides, with upper Miocene marine rocks to the northwest. The Pine Rock Fault is associated with this valley (Jennings and Strand 1958). No information regarding groundwater occurrence or movement within the basin was found, therefore basin boundary confidence is considered low. The valley is occupied by the San Benito River, which drains it to the northwest. Average precipitation is 17 inches.Hydrogeologic InformationWater Bearing FormationsNo specific published information on the water bearing deposits was found. A review of San Joaquin District well completion report files showed only two reports for the basin. In both wells it was reported that no water was encountered. The wells were 260 feet and 115 feet deep and encountered alluvial materials to a depth of about 20 feet and consolidated sandstone and shale below that depth. From this very limited data it appears that the alluvial terrace material may be dry and thus is not a producing aquifer.Groundwater Level TrendsNo data was found regarding water level trends.Groundwater StorageNo published information on groundwater storage was found.Groundwater Budget (Type C)There is no information to provide an estimate of this basin’s budget.Groundwater QualityNo groundwater quality information was found in the published literature or in DWR files.Water Quality in Public Supply WellsCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Constituent Group1Inorganics – Primary RadiologicalNitratesPesticidesNumber of wells sampled2 00 2 0Number of wells with a concentration above an MCL3 00 0 0￼Last update 2/27/04
Central Coast Hydrologic Region Dry Lake Valley Groundwater BasinVOCs and SVOCs 0 0 Inorganics – Secondary 0 01 A description of each member in the constituent groups and a generalized discussion of the relevance of these groups are included in California’s Groundwater – Bulletin 118 by DWR (2003).2 Represents distinct number of wells sampled as required under DHS Title 22 program from 1994 through 2000.3 Each well reported with a concentration above an MCL was confirmed with a second detection above an MCL. This information is intended as an indicator of the types of activities that cause contamination in a given basin. It represents the water quality at the sample location. It does not indicate the water quality delivered to the consumer. More detailed drinking water quality information can be obtained from the local water purveyor and its annual Consumer Confidence Report.Well Production characteristics Well yields (gal/min)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationActive Monitoring DataTotal depths (ft)￼￼AgencyDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water quality Title 22 water qualityNumber of wells /measurement frequency NKDNKD 0None None￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management: Water agenciesPublic PrivateReferences Cited￼￼California Department of Water Resources (DWR), San Joaquin District. Well completion report files.Jennings, Charles W. and Rudolph G. Strand (compilers). 1958. Santa Cruz Sheet of Geologic Map of California. California Division of Mines and Geology (CDMG). Scale 1:250,000.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.Last update 2/27/04