Central Coast Hydrologic RegionArroyo De La Cruz Valley Groundwater BasinArroyo De La Cruz Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 3-34• County: San Luis Obispo• Surface Area: 750 acres (1.2 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Arroyo De La Cruz Valley Groundwater Basin is bounded on the west by the Pacific Ocean and on all other sides by impermeable rocks of the Jurassic to Cretaceous age Franciscan Group. The valley is drained by Arroyo De La Cruz. Precipitation ranges from 20 to 24 inches.Hydrogeologic InformationWater Bearing FormationsGroundwater is found in Holocene and late Pleistocene age alluvium that consists of sand, gravel, and clay and ranges to 130 feet thick (DWR 1975). Groundwater is largely unconfined, with water level elevations above sea level (DWR 1975). The specific yield for the basin is estimated at 18 percent (DWR 1958).Recharge AreasRecharge to the basin is largely by percolation of stream flow and, to a lesser extent, from percolation of precipitation in the valley and excess irrigation flow (DWR 1958).Groundwater Level TrendsNo information of groundwater level trends was found. Groundwater movement is generally westward.Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. The total storage capacity is estimated at 6,600 af (DWR 1975).Groundwater in Storage. Unknown. Groundwater Budget (Type C)No information is available.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. Analyses of groundwater from 4 wells in this basin taken during 1957 through 1985 show TDS content ranging from 211 to 381 mg/L. Impairments. No information is available.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Central Coast Hydrologic RegionArroyo De La Cruz Valley Groundwater BasinWell Production characteristics Well yields (gal/min)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationTotal depths (ft)Range: to 127 ft￼Active Monitoring DataAverage: 100 ft (DWR 1958)Number of wells /measurement frequency NKDNKD 0￼AgencyDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsNKD: No Known DataParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water quality Title 22 water quality￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management: Water agenciesPublic PrivateReferences Cited￼￼California Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1958. San Luis Obispo County Investigation. Bulletin 18. 288 p.. 1975. Sea-Water Intrusion in California: Inventory of Coastal Ground Water Basins. Bulletin 63-5.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.￼Last update 2/27/04