Hydrologic Region Groundwater BasinSan Joaquin Valley Groundwater Basin Eastern San Joaquin SubbasinGroundwater Basin Number: 5-22.01• County: San Joaquin, Stanislaus, and Calaveras• Surface Area: 707,000 acres (1,105 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe San Joaquin Valley comprises the southernmost portion of the Great Valley Geomorphic Province of California. The Great Valley is a broad structural trough bounded by the tilted block of the Sierra Nevada on the east and the complexly folded and faulted Coast Ranges on the west. The Eastern San Joaquin Subbasin is defined by the areal extent of unconsolidated to semiconsolidated sedimentary deposits that are bounded by the Mokelumne River on the north and northwest; San Joaquin River on the west; Stanislaus River on the south; and consolidated bedrock on the east.The Eastern San Joaquin Subbasin is bounded on the south, southwest, and west by the Modesto, Delta-Mendota, and Tracy Subbasins, respectively and on the northwest and north by the Solano, South American, and Cosumnes Subbasins. The Solano and South American are subbasins of the Sacramento Valley Groundwater Basin.The Eastern San Joaquin Subbasin is drained by the San Joaquin River and several of its major tributaries namely, the Stanislaus, and Calaveras, and Mokelumne Rivers. The San Joaquin River flows northward into the Sacramento and San Joaquin Delta and discharges into the San Francisco Bay. Annual precipitation within the subbasin ranges from about 11 inches in the southwest to about 25 inches in the northeast.Hydrogeologic InformationWater Bearing FormationsWater bearing formations of significance in the Eastern San Joaquin Subbasin consist of the Alluvium and Modesto/Riverbank Formations, Flood Basin Deposits, Laguna Formation, and Mehrten Formation. The Mehrten Formation is considered to be the oldest fresh water-bearing formation on the east side of the basin, even though the underlying Valley Springs Formation produces minor quantities. Information on water bearing units and groundwater conditions was taken primarily from (DWR 1967).Alluvium and Modesto/Riverbank Formations (Undifferentiated). These units are exposed within the subbasin along a band approximately 15 miles wide that extends from about Stockton eastward. These units are Recent to Late Pleistocene in age and consist primarily of sand and gravel in the fan areas while clay, silt, and sand are dominant in the interfan areas. These units range in thickness from a thin veneer on the east side of the basin to over 150 feet near the center of the basin. Groundwater occurs unconfined within these units. Well yields to 650 ± gpm are reported. Because these units are limited in thickness, most wells penetrate them in order to tap deeper aquifers in the area. Average specific yields in the 10- to 200-foot depth range vary from about 7 to 15 percent within the boundaries of theCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 1/20/06
Hydrologic Region Groundwater BasinTuolumne River Storage Unit (Davis et al. 1959). The average specific yield for fresh water bearing units in the San Joaquin County Groundwater Investigation area as defined in (DWR 1967) is 7.3 percent. The Victor Formation as defined in (DWR 1967) is correlative with these units.Flood Basin Deposits. This unit is exposed in the Delta area of the San Joaquin Valley. These deposits are basinward, fine-grained forms of the Laguna, Riverbank, Modesto, and Recent formations and, therefore, range in age from Pliocene to Recent. They are generally much finer grained with a higher percentage of fine sand and clays than their depositional equivalents to the east and west. Occasional gravel beds occur along the present waterways and are probably representative of the type of underlying lithology distribution. This unit ranges in thickness from 0 to 1,400 ± feet. Groundwater in this unit occurs under unconfined to confined conditions. The unit, in general, has low permeabilities and may create semi-confined to confined conditions when interfingered with the Alluvium and Modesto/Riverbank Formations. Occasional pockets of fresh water are found in the Delta deposits, but generally speaking the formation contains poor quality water. This unit is designated as Dos Palos Alluvium by (Wagner et al. 1990).Laguna Formation. The Laguna Formation is Plio-Pleistocene in age and consists of discontinuous lenses of stream laid sand and silt with lesser amounts of clay and gravel. There are no regionally significant fine-grained intervals that could cause water pressure conditions, although the heterogeneous nature of the sediments causes local confinement. From the Mokelumne River area, the formation thickens from approximately 400 feet to approximately 1,000 feet in the Stockton area. Regionally, yields of 1,500 gpm have been reported from highly permeable beds, but average yields are about 900 ± gpm. Groundwater occurs under unconfined to locally semiconfined conditions within this unit. Occasional minor perched water zones are encountered in this formation, particularly in the Mokelumne River area.Mehrten Formation. This formation is exposed in the easternmost part of the subbasin where it forms readily identifiable, nearly flat-topped hills. The formation is late Miocene to Pliocene in age and is composed of moderately to well indurated andesitic sand to sandstone interbedded with conglomerate, tuffaceous siltstone, and claystone. The Mehrten Formation is approximately 400 feet thick in eastern surface outcrops to over 600 feet thick in the subsurface near Stockton. It is reported to be 1,300 ± feet thick at McDonald Island. The top of the Mehrten Formation occurs at depths of approximately 800 to 1,000 feet in the Stockton area. Regional studies indicate that Mehrten Formation sands commonly yield on the order of 1,000 gpm from wells. The formation appears to be semiconfined at least locally in the Stockton area, due to the inferred extensive fine-grained beds in its upper part. The average specific yield for fresh water bearing units in the San Joaquin County Groundwater Investigation area as defined in (DWR 1967) is 7.3 percent.Groundwater Level TrendsCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 1/20/06
Hydrologic Region Groundwater BasinMeasurements over the past 40 years show a fairly continuous decline in groundwater levels in Eastern San Joaquin County (USACE 2001). Groundwater levels have declined at an average rate of 1.7 feet per year and have dropped as much as 100 feet in some areas. It is estimated that groundwater overdraft during the past 40 years has reduced storage in the basin by as much as 2 million acre feet.Due to the continued overdraft of groundwater within the subbasin, significant groundwater depressions are present below the City of Stockton, east of Stockton, and east of Lodi (SJCFC 1999). Several of these groundwater depressions extend to depths of about 100 feet below ground surface (or more than 40 feet below mean sea level).Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. The total available groundwater storage capacity from a depth of 20 feet to the base of the groundwater basin is about 42,400,000 af based on a total aquifer material volume of 579,900,000 af and an average specific yield of 7.3 percent (DWR 1967). This estimate was based on a study area that encompassed approximately 586,000 acres. Since the currently defined subbasin size is over 707,000 acres, the storage value mentioned above underestimates the total storage capacity for the subbasin as defined in Bulletin 118 – Update 2002.Groundwater in Storage. No published groundwater in storage estimates were identified.Groundwater Budget (Type A)A hydrologic balance for a study area approximately matching the subbasin was prepared by Brown & Caldwell (SJCFC 1985). The balance consists of an inventory of inflow and outflow items for the period 1963 – 1982. Inflow estimates include: average annual infiltration from applied water and precipitation (593,356 af); average annual seepage from surface water (141,127 af); and average annual net subsurface inflow (3,586 af). Outflow estimates include: average annual municipal and industrial pumpage (47,493 af); and average annual agricultural pumpage (761,828 af). This balance shows that there has been a total net outflow from the system of about 1.5 million acre feet over the 20 year study period which represents an average annual outflow (or overdraft) of about 70,000 acre feet.The (USBR 1996) estimated the 1990 annual groundwater extraction in San Joaquin County to be about 731,000 af/year, which exceeds the estimated safe yield of 618,000 af/year. This results in an estimated overdraft of 113,000 af/year. It is estimated that 70,000 af/year of overdraft occurs in northeastern San Joaquin County and about 35,000 af/year of overdraft occurs in the Stockton East Water District area.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. The majority of the groundwater in the basin is characterized by calcium-magnesium bicarbonate or calcium-sodium bicarbonate types (Sorenson 1981). Bicarbonate is the predominant anion in the eastern part of the basin. Large areas of chloride type water occur along the western margin of the subbasin along the San Joaquin River. Based on analyses of 174 water supply wells in the subbasin, TDS ranges from 30 toCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 1/20/06
Hydrologic Region Groundwater Basin1,632 mg/L and averages about 310 mg/L. TDS ranged from 50 to 3,520 mg/L with a mean of 463 and median of 269 according to the groundwater chemistry study in San Joaquin County and part of Contra Costa County by (Sorenson 1981). Specific conductance of groundwater ranged from 78 to 5,390 μmhos/cm, with a mean value of 685 and a median of 356. Some of the highest specific conductance values were found along the western part of the subbasin and San Joaquin River alignment.Impairments. As a result of declining water levels, poor quality water has been moving east along a 16-mile front on the east side of the Delta (DWR 1967). The degradation was particularly evident in the Stockton area where the saline front was moving eastward at a rate of 140 to 150 feet per year. Data from 1980 and 1996 indicate that the saline front has continued to migrate eastward up to about one mile beyond its 1963 extent (USACE 2001). Large areas of elevated nitrate in groundwater exist within the subbasin located southeast of Lodi and south of Stockton and east of Manteca extending towards the San Joaquin – Stanislaus County line.Water Quality in Public Supply WellsCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Constituent Group1Inorganics – Primary RadiologicalNitratesPesticidesVOCs and SVOCs Inorganics – SecondaryNumber of wells sampled2 182     179     189     191     185     182Number of wells with a concentration above an MCL3 887 21 6 71￼1 A description of each member in the constituent groups and a generalized discussion of the relevance of these groups are included in California’s Groundwater – Bulletin 118 by DWR (2003).2 Represents distinct number of wells sampled as required under DHS Title 22 program from 1994 through 2000.3 Each well reported with a concentration above an MCL was confirmed with a second detection above an MCL. This information is intended as an indicator of the types of activities that cause contamination in a given basin. It represents the water quality at the sample location. It does not indicate the water quality delivered to the consumer. More detailed drinking water quality information can be obtained from the local water purveyor and its annual Consumer Confidence Report.Well Production characteristicsWell yields (gal/min)￼￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationWell yields in the fresh water-bearing formations underlying the basin range (in general) from about 650 to 1,500 gpm.Total depths (ft)Range: 25-993 Average: 242 (Based on 1551 well completion reports)Range: 75-780 Average: 349 (Based on 224 well completion reports)￼Active Monitoring DataLast update 1/20/06
Hydrologic Region Groundwater BasinAgencyDWRSan Joaquin County Flood Control and Water Conservation District (SJCFC) and cooperators SJCFC and cooperatorsDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsBasin ManagementGroundwater management: (DWR 1999)Water agencies: Public and PrivateCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼ParameterGroundwater levels Groundwater levelsTDS, turbidity, chloride, and EC Title 22 water qualityNumber of wells /measurement frequency99 /semiannually, and 15 /monthly246 /semiannuallyApproximately 26 /annually540 /annually￼￼References CitedSan Joaquin County enacted a groundwater management ordinance in 1996; AB 3030 plans have been adopted by the following entities: County of Stanislaus ; North San Joaquin WCD (3/5/96); Oakdale ID (9/22/95); San Joaquin County FC&WCD (2/11/97); South San Joaquin ID (2/14/95); Stockton East WD (11/1/95); and Woodbridge ID.Lockeford CSD, North Delta WA,North San Joaquin WCD, OakdaleID, City of Lathrop WD, City of Lodi Service Area, City of MantecaWSA, Calaveras County WD,California Water Service Company, Central Delta WA, Central SanJoaquin WCD, City of EscalonWSA, Reclamation District No. 828,River Junction Reclamation DistrictNo. 2064, Rock Creek WD, SouthDelta WA, South San Joaquin ID, Stockton East WD, Valley SpringsPUD, Woodbridge ID, Woodbridge WUCD, and City of Stockton MUD. Northeastern San Joaquin County Groundwater Banking Authority adopted a groundwater management plan.Davis, G. H., J.H. Green, F.H. Olmsted, and Brown, D. W. (1959). "Ground-Water Conditions and Storage Capacity in the San Joaquin Valley, California. Water-Supply Paper 1469." U.S. Geological Survey.DWR. (1967). "San Joaquin County Groundwater Investigation - Bulletin 146." California Department of Water Resources.DWR. (1999). "Groundwater Management in California 1999 - A Report to the Legislature Pursuant to Senate Bill 1245 (1997)." California Department of Water Resources.SJCFC. (1985). "Eastern San Joaquin County Groundwater Study. Final Report." San Joaquin County Flood Control and Water Conservation District, prepared by Brown & Caldwell Consulting Engineers.Last update 1/20/06
Hydrologic Region Groundwater BasinSJCFC. (1999). "Spring 1999 Groundwater Report." San Joaquin County Flood Control and Water Conservation District.Sorenson, S. K. (1981). "Chemical Quality Of Ground Water In San Joaquin And Part Of Contra Costa Counties, California. Water-Resources Investigation 81-26." U.S. Geological Survey.USACE. (2001). "Farmington Groundwater Recharge/Seasonal Habitat Study. Final Report." U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, Sacramento District, prepared by Montgomery Watson Harza.USBR. (1996). "American River Water Resources Investigation Planning Report and Draft Environmental Impact Report/Environmental Impact Statement." U.S. Department of the Interior - Bureau of Reclamation, Mid Pacific Region.Wagner, D. L., Bortugno, E. J., and McJunkin, R. D. (1990). "Geologic Map of the San Francisco - San Jose Quadrangle." California Department of Conservation, Division of Mines and Geology.Additional ReferencesCDPW (1955). Water Quality Investigation Report No. 7: Quality of Ground Water in the Stockton Area, San Joaquin County., California State Department of Public Works, Division of Water Resources.CSWPA (1956). Investigation of the Sacramento-San Joaquin Delta, Report No. 1, Ground Water Geology., California State Water Project Authority.DWR (1969). Water Well Standards, San Joaquin County, Final Supplement. Bulletin 74-5., California Department of Water Resources.DWR (1975). California's Ground Water. Bulletin 118, California Department of Water Resources.DWR (1980). Ground Water Basins in California. Bulletin 118, California Department of Water Resources.DWR (1992). Historical Unconfined Ground Water Trends in San Joaquin Valley., California Department of Water Resources, Central District.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 1/20/06