San Joaquin River Hydrologic Region San Joaquin Valley Groundwater BasinSan Joaquin Valley Groundwater Basin Modesto Subbasin• Groundwater Subbasin Number: 5-22.02• County: Stanislaus• Surface Area: 247,000 acres (385 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe San Joaquin Valley is surrounded on the west by the Coast Ranges, on the south by the San Emigdio and Tehachapi Mountains, on the east by the Sierra Nevada and on the north by the Sacramento-San Joaquin Delta and Sacramento Valley. The northern portion of the San Joaquin Valley drains toward the Delta by the San Joaquin River and its tributaries, the Fresno, Merced, Tuolumne, and Stanislaus Rivers. The southern portion of the valley is internally drained by the Kings, Kaweah, Tule, and Kern Rivers that flow into the Tulare drainage basin including the beds of the former Tulare, Buena Vista, and Kern Lakes.The Modesto subbasin lies between the Stanislaus River to the north and Tuolumne River to the south and between the San Joaquin River on the west and crystalline basement rock of the Sierra Nevada foothills on the east. The northern, western, and southern boundaries are shared with the Eastern San Joaquin Valley, Delta-Mendota, and Turlock Groundwater Subbasins, respectively. The subbasin comprises land primarily in the Modesto Irrigation District (MID) and the southern two-thirds of the Oakdale Irrigation District (OID). The City of Modesto is in the southwestern portion of the subbasin. Average annual precipitation for this subbasin is 11 to 15 inches, increasing eastward.Hydrogeologic InformationThe San Joaquin Valley represents the southern portion of the Great Central Valley of California. The San Joaquin Valley is a structural trough up to 200 miles long and 70 miles wide. It is filled with up to 32,000 feet of marine and continental sediments deposited during periodic inundation by the Pacific Ocean and by erosion of the surrounding mountains, respectively. Continental deposits shed from the surrounding mountains form an alluvial wedge that thickens from the valley margins toward the axis of the structural trough. This depositional axis is below to slightly west of the series of rivers, lakes, sloughs, and marshes, which mark the current and historic axis of surface drainage in the San Joaquin Valley.Water Bearing FormationsThe primary hydrogeologic units in the Modesto Subbasin include both consolidated and unconsolidated sedimentary deposits. The consolidated deposits include the Ione Formation of Miocene age, the Valley Springs Formation of Eocene age, and the Mehrten Formation, which was deposited during the Miocene to Pliocene Epochs. The consolidated deposits lie in the eastern portion of the subbasin and generally yield small quantities of water to wells except for the Mehrten Formation, which is an important aquifer. In the Subbasin, the Mehrten Formation is composed of up to 300 feet of sandstone, breccia, conglomerate, tuff siltstone and claystone (Page 1973).California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
San Joaquin River Hydrologic Region San Joaquin Valley Groundwater BasinThe unconsolidated deposits were laid down during the Pliocene to present and, from oldest to youngest, include continental deposits lacustrine and marsh deposits, older alluvium, younger alluvium, and flood-subbasin deposits. The continental deposits and older alluvium are the main water- yielding units in the unconsolidated deposits. The lacustrine and marsh deposits (which include the Corcoran, or “E-” Clay), and the flood-subbasin deposits yield little water to wells, and the younger alluvium in most places probably yields only moderate quantities of water to wells (Page 1973).The continental deposits consist of poorly sorted gravel, sand, silt and clay varying in thickness from 0 to 450 feet occurring at the surface on the eastern side of the subbasin to over 400 feet deep in the western portion. These deposits are the equivalent of the North Merced Gravels and the lower Turlock Lake Formation (Davis and others 1959). The older alluvium consists of intercalated beds of gravel sand, silt and clay with some hardpan. This alluvium is up to 400 feet thick and is generally present near or at the surface of the western one-half of the subbasin. The older alluvium is largely equivalent to the Riverbank and Modesto Formations (Davis and others 1959).Ground water occurs under unconfined, semi-confined, and confined conditions. The unconfined water body occurs in the unconsolidated deposits above and east of the Corcoran Clay, which underlies the southwestern portion of the subbasin at depths ranging from 150 to 250 feet (DWR 1981). Where clay lenses restrict the downward flow of ground water, semi-confined conditions occur. The confined water body occurs in the unconsolidated deposits below the Corcoran Clay and extends downward to the base of fresh water.The estimated average specific yield of this subbasin is 8.8 percent (based on DWR San Joaquin District internal data and Davis and others 1959).Restrictive StructuresGroundwater flow is primarily to the southwest, following the regional dip of basement rock and sedimentary units. The lower to middle reaches of the Stanislaus and Tuolomne Rivers in the Subbasin appear to be gaining streams with groundwater flow into both, especially the Tuolomne River (DWR 2000). No faults have been identified that affect the movement of fresh groundwater (Page and Balding 1973).Recharge AreasGroundwater recharge is primarily from deep percolation of applied irrigation water and canal seepage from MID and OID facilities. Seepage from Modesto Reservoir is also significant (STRGBA 1995). Lesser recharge occurs as a result of subsurface flows originating in the mountains and foothills along the east side of the subbasin, losses from minor streams, and from percolation of direct precipitation.Groundwater Level TrendsChanges in groundwater levels are based on annual water level measurements by DWR and cooperators. Water level changes wereCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
San Joaquin River Hydrologic Region San Joaquin Valley Groundwater Basinevaluated by quarter township and computed through a custom DWR computer program using geostatistics (kriging). On average, the subbasin water level has declined nearly 15 feet from 1970 through 2000. The period from 1970 through 1978 showed steep declines totaling about 12 feet. The six-year period from 1978 to 1984 saw stabilization and rebound of about 7 feet. 1984 through 1995 again showed steep declines, bottoming out in 1995 at nearly 20 feet below the 1970 level. Water levels then rose about 5 feet from 1996 to 2000. Water level declines have been more severe in the eastern portion of the subbasin, but have risen faster in the eastern subbasin between 1996 and 2000 than in any other portion of the subbasin.Groundwater StorageEstimations of the total storage capacity of the subbasin and the amount of water in storage as of 1995 were calculated using an estimated specific yield of 8.8 percent and water levels collected by DWR and cooperators. According to these calculations, the total storage capacity of this subbasin is estimated to be 6,500,000 af to a depth of 300 feet. According to published literature, the amount of stored groundwater in this subbasin as of 1961 is 14,000,000 af to a depth of < 1000 feet (Williamson 1989).Groundwater Budget (Type B)Although a detailed budget was not available for this subbasin, an estimate of groundwater demand was calculated based on the 1990 normalized year and data on land and water use. A subsequent analysis was done by a DWR water budget spreadsheet to estimate overall applied water demands, agricultural groundwater pumpage, urban pumping demand and other extraction data.Natural recharge into the subbasin is estimated to be 86,000 af. Artificial recharge and subsurface inflow values are not determined. There is approximately 92,000 af of applied water recharge. Annual urban and agricultural extractions are estimated to be 81,000 and 145,000 af, respectively. There are no other extractions, and values for subsurface outflow are not determined.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. The groundwater in this basin is of a calcium bicarbonate type in the eastern subbasin to a calcium-magnesium bicarbonate or calcium- sodium bicarbonate type in the western portion. TDS values range from 60 to 8,300 mg/L, with a typical range of 200 to 500 mg/L. The Department of Health Services, which monitors Title 22 water quality standards, reports TDS values in 88 wells ranging from 60 to 860 mg/L, with an average value of 295 mg/L.Impairments. There are areas of hard groundwater and localized areas of high chloride, boron, DBCP, nitrate, iron, and manganese. Some sodium chloride waters of high TDS values are found along the east side of the subbasin. There are also some areas of shallow groundwater in the subbasin that require dewatering wells.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Last update 2/27/04
San Joaquin River Hydrologic Region San Joaquin Valley Groundwater BasinWater Quality in Public Supply WellsCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Constituent Group1Inorganics – Primary RadiologicalNitratesPesticidesVOCs and SVOCs Inorganics – SecondaryNumber of wells sampled2 110     109     114     117     117     110Number of wells with a concentration above an MCL3 325 3 14 8 8￼￼1 A description of each member in the constituent groups and a generalized discussion of the relevance of these groups are included in California’s Groundwater – Bulletin 118 by DWR (2003).2 Represents distinct number of wells sampled as required under DHS Title 22 program from 1994 through 2000.3 Each well reported with a concentration above an MCL was confirmed with a second detection above an MCL. This information is intended as an indicator of the types of activities that cause contamination in a given basin. It represents the water quality at the sample location. It does not indicate the water quality delivered to the consumer. More detailed drinking water quality information can be obtained from the local water purveyor and its annual Consumer Confidence Report.Well CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)Municipal/Irrigation Range: 350 – 4,500 Average: 1,000 - 2,000Total depths (ft)￼DomesticMunicipal/Irrigation Range: 50 - 500Active Monitoring Data￼￼AgencyDWR (incl. Cooperators)Oakdale Irrigation DistrictDepartment of Health Services (including Cooperators)ParameterGroundwater levelsDrinking water parametersTitle 22 water qualityNumber of wells /measurement frequency 230 Semi-annually15 Monthly to every 3 years 209 Varies￼Last update 2/27/04
San Joaquin River Hydrologic Region San Joaquin Valley Groundwater BasinCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management:The Stanislaus and Tuolumne Rivers' Groundwater Subbasin Association has developed an AB3030 ground water management plan for the individual Association members (City of Modesto, Del Este Water Company, County of Stanislaus, Oakdale I.D., City of Oakdale, City of Riverbank, and Modesto I.D.)Conjunctive use programs, stormwater recharge subbasins, water conservation programs operated by Oakdale and Modesto I.Ds., Stanislaus County and other public entities.Oakdale I.D., Modesto I.D.; Stanislaus and Tuolumne Rivers' Groundwater Subbasin Association; City of Oakdale; City of Riverbank￼Water agencies PublicPrivateReferences Cited￼￼California Department of Water Resources (DWR), San Joaquin District. Unpublished Land and Water Use Data.________. Well completion report files.________. 1981. Depth to Top of Corcoran Clay. 1:253,440 scale map.________. 1995. Internal computer spreadsheet for 1990 normal computation of net water demand used in preparation of DWR Bulletin 160-93.________. 2000. Spring 1999, Lines of Equal Elevation of Water in Wells, Unconfined Aquifer. 1:253,440 scale map sheet.Davis, GH, Green, JH, Olmstead, SH, and Brown, DW. 1959. Ground Water Conditions and Storage Capacity in the San Joaquin Valley, California; US Geological Survey Water Supply Paper No. 1469, 287p.Page, RW, and Balding, GO. 1973. Geology and Quality of Water in the Modesto-Merced Area, San Joaquin Valley, California, with a Brief Section of Hydrology. USGS Water- Resources Investigations 6-73, 85p.Stanislaus and Tuolumne Rivers' Groundwater Subbasin Association (STRGBA). 1995. Development of a Groundwater Management Plan Phase I. Technical Memorandum. Prepared by Black & Veatch, Provost & Pritchard, and Kenneth D. Schmidt & Associates Consulting Firms.Williamson, Alex K, Prudic, David E, and Swain, Lindsay A. 1989. Groundwater flow in the Central Valley, California. US Geological Survey Professional Paper 1401-D. 127 p.Additional ReferencesBalding, GO, and Page, RW. 1971. Data for Wells in the Modesto-Merced Area San Joaquin Valley, California. US Geological Survey Open-File Report.Last update 2/27/04
San Joaquin River Hydrologic Region San Joaquin Valley Groundwater BasinCalifornia Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1980. Bulletin 118-80, Ground Water Subbasins in California.________. 1994. Bulletin 160-93. California Water Plan Update, Vol. 1.Davis, SN and Hall, FR. 1959. Water Quality of Eastern Stanislaus and North Merced Counties, California; Stanford Univ. Pubs., Geol. Sci., v. 6, no. 1. 112 p.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04