North Coast Hydrologic Region Smith River Plain Groundwater BasinSmith River Plain Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 1-1• County: Del Norte• Surface Area: 40,450 acres (63 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Smith River Plain Groundwater Basin is located in Del Norte County in the extreme northwest corner of California. The plain is irregular in shape narrowing to the south against the steep scarp of the faulted mountain headland. The major structural feature in the basin is the inferred Del Norte fault which constitutes the basin boundary to the north and east (USBR 1960). The north end of the plain narrows at the mouth of the Smith River to a marine terrace less than one mile wide that continues into Oregon (DWR 1987). The basin is bounded to the north, east, and south by Mesozoic Franciscan Formation (Strand 1963).The Smith River crosses the northern portion of the plain near the town of Smith River and is the major watercourse responsible for most of the floodplain deposits in the area. Lake Earl and Talawa are shallow brackish lakes in the west central part of the plain and form collection basins for runoff from several minor streams (Back 1957).Annual precipitation in the basin ranges from 65- to 77-inches, increasing to the northeast.Hydrogeologic InformationThe Smith River Plain is an emerged low-relief marine terrace. The surface of the plain is comprised of sand dunes, floodplain deposits, unconsolidated river terrace deposits, and surface exposures of the marine Battery Formation. Underlying the terrace deposits are the marine Battery Formation and the St. George Formation. Beneath the St. George Formation is basement rock of the Jurassic-Cretaceous Franciscan Complex.Water-Bearing FormationsQuaternary alluvial fan, flood-plain, terrace, and Battery Formation deposits form the primary water-bearing formations in the basin. The St. George Formation and basement rock of the Franciscan formation yield very little water to wells.Holocene Alluvial Fan Deposits. Alluvial fan deposits form a steep, nearly continuous apron less than one mile wide along the base of the mountains. These deposits consist primarily of poorly-sorted, subrounded rocks in a silty clay matrix and are up to 50 feet thick. The occasional sand and gravel lenses represent buried stream channels. The bulk of the unit was probably derived from landslides and possibly mudflows rather than entirely from stream deposition (DWR 1987). Permeability of the fan deposits is generally low due to large amounts of interstitial clay; however, sand and gravel lenses near the western edges of the fans have a relatively high permeability. In general, yields to wells penetrating only alluvial fan deposits are relatively low but can be highly variable.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
North Coast Hydrologic Region Smith River Plain Groundwater BasinHolocene Floodplain Deposits. Floodplain deposits underlie the present floodplain of the Smith River and its tributaries. These deposits rest on either basement rock or the Battery Formation and overlie river terrace deposits along the edge of the floodplain. The overlying deposits consist of unconsolidated clay, sand, and gravel and range in thickness from about 40- to 95-feet. The deposits are commonly covered with a shallow, silty soil 2- to 3-feet in thickness. The sands and gravels are well-rounded and poorly sorted. Boulders and cobbles are common where the Smith River flows out of the mountains. As the floodplain spreads west over the plain, the alluvial deposits generally become finer (DWR 1987). The deposits contain large amounts of unconfined water and are the most productive aquifers in the Smith River Plain. Most of the irrigation wells in the area obtain water from this zone. Yields to wells range from about 200- to 800-gpm and permeabilities range from about 6,000- to 10,000-gpd per square foot (DWR 1987).Pleistocene Terrace Deposits. The Pleistocene age terrace deposits are associated with Smith River and Rowdy Creek and serve as the major aquifer in the northern part of the basin and also provide recharge to adjacent formations. These deposits contain poorly-sorted silt, sand, and gravel and include some clay - predominantly in the upper portion. Generally, these deposits become coarser with depth and large boulders are often encountered at the base. Thickness of the deposits generally range from about 30- to 55- feet, but may exceed 75 feet in the area south of the community of Smith River (DWR 1987). These deposits are underlain by basement rocks, but locally they may rest on the Battery or St. George Formations. The river terrace deposits are moderate to highly permeable, with permeabilities ranging from 1,000- to 2,000-gpd per square foot (DWR 1987). Generally, well yields are not high due to the limited saturated thickness. Several irrigation wells in the Fort Dick and Rowdy Creek areas yield 140- to 400- gpm. Some of the smaller terraces may not have enough storage-carryover capabilities to provide adequate water supplies throughout the summer and fall months because of limited areal extents.Pleistocene Battery Formation. The Pleistocene Battery Formation is a thin, flat-lying, marine terrace deposit that unconformably overlies the basement rocks of the Franciscan complex or the Pliocene St. George Formation. It consists of alternating sand and clay beds with interbedded continental deposits of stream gravel and sand. Well logs and seismic data indicate that it is 30- to 70-feet thick. It underlies most of the plain south and east of Lake Earl and forms the narrow marine terrace north of the mouth of Smith River. The Battery Formation is the principal aquifer in the southern two-thirds of the plain. The producing zones consist of lenticular beds of fine to medium grained, well sorted sand. Depth to this aquifer ranges from 5- to 30-feet and averages about 20 feet. Groundwater in this aquifer is either perched or unconfined. Permeability ranges from 150- to 900-gpd per square foot and is commonly about 350- to 450-gpd per square foot (Back 1957). The formation is moderately permeable, but has limited saturated thickness. Well yields are large enough for domestic and limited irrigation uses.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
North Coast Hydrologic Region Smith River Plain Groundwater BasinTertiary Pliocene St. George Formation. The Pliocene St. George Formation consists of massive, poorly indurated siltstone and shale that contain irregular and sporadic lenses of sand and pebbles. The formation thickness is estimated at about 400 feet (Back 1957). The permeability of the St. George Formation is very low but contains two prominent joint sets that yield limited water to some wells.Restrictive StructuresSand dunes within the basin form a narrow strip about one mile wide from west of Crescent City to the mouth of Smith River. These dunes form elongated ridges as much as 60 feet high and form a barrier to surface runoff from the central part of the plain resulting in the formation of lake Earl and Lake Talawa (DWR 1987).Recharge AreasRecharge is accomplished by direct infiltration of precipitation, subsurface inflow from surface water/precipitation infiltration of alluvial fans or dune areas, and infiltration of runoff in the lower reaches of the Smith River and other permeable stream channels (Back 1957).Groundwater Level TrendsReview of hydrographs for long-term comparison of spring-spring groundwater levels indicates a slight decline associated with the 1976-77 and 1987-94 droughts, followed by a recovery to pre-drought conditions of the early 1970’s and 1980’s. Generally, groundwater level data show a seasonal fluctuation of approximate 5- to 15-feet for normal and dry years. Overall, there does not appear to be any increasing or decreasing trends in groundwater levels.Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. Storage capacity in the basin is estimated to be 99,350 acre-feet based a surface area of 31,070 acres, a depth interval of 10- to 35-feet below ground surface, and an average specific yield of 12.8 percent (Back 1957).Groundwater Budget (Type B)Estimates of groundwater extraction are based on a survey conducted by the California Department of Water Resources in 1996. The survey included landuse and sources of water. Estimates of groundwater extraction for agricultural and municipal/industrial uses are 12,000 and 990 acre-feet respectively. Deep percolation from applied water is estimated to be 3,100 acre-feet.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. Groundwater in the basin consists of magnesium bicarbonate and magnesium-sodium bicarbonate type waters. Increasing proportions of sodium and chloride are found in waters from the southern half of the basin (Back 1957). Total dissolved solids (TDS) range from 50- to 500-mg/L, averaging 100 mg/L (DWR unpublished data).California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
North Coast Hydrologic Region Smith River Plain Groundwater BasinImpairments. High levels of iron are found in some areas. Locally high chloride, calcium, and TDS are also found.Water Quality in Public Supply WellsCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Constituent Group1Inorganics – Primary RadiologicalNitratesPesticidesVOCs and SVOCs Inorganics – SecondaryNumber of wells sampled2 2312 26 8 15 23Number of wells with a concentration above an MCL3 10 0 0 1 1￼￼1 A description of each member in the constituent groups anddiscussion of the relevance of these groups are included in California’s Groundwater – Bulletin 118 by DWR (2003).2 Represents distinct number of wells sampled as required under DHS Title 22 program from 1994 through 2000.3 Each well reported with a concentration above an MCL was confirmed with a second detection above an MCL. This information is intended as an indicator of the types of activities that cause contamination in a given basin. It represents the water quality at the sample location. It does not indicate the water quality delivered to the consumer. More detailed drinking water quality information can be obtained from the local water purveyor and its annual Consumer Confidence Report.Well Production characteristics Well yields (gal/min)a generalized￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationMaximum well yield is estimated to be 500. (DWR 1975)Average: 44 (1,017 Well Completion Reports)Average: 39 (19 Well Completion Reports)Number of wells /measurement frequency 7 wells semi-annually10 wells biennial 33Active Monitoring DataAverage well yield is estimated to be 50Total depths (ft)Range: 15 - 400 Range: 16 - 110￼￼AgencyDWR DWRDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water quality Miscellaneous water quality￼Last update 2/27/04
North Coast Hydrologic Region Smith River Plain Groundwater BasinCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateSelected ReferencesNo known groundwater management plans, groundwater ordinances, or basin adjudications.Smith River CSD, Church Tree CSD., Bertsch- Oceanview CSD, Klamath CSD, Roosevelt Water SystemCrescent City WC￼￼￼Back, W. 1957. Geology and Ground Water Features of Smith River Plain. USGS Water Supply Paper 1254.California Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1987. Smith River Plain Ground Water Study. Northern District.California Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1987. Smith River Plain Ground Water Study. Sacramento: California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. Report No. 7.California Department of Water Resources. 1988. The Geohydrology of Four Pesticide Problem Areas Near Smith River, California. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. Memorandum Report.Iwatsubo RT, and others. 1982. Water Quality Assessment of the Smith River Drainage Basin, California and Oregon. USGS. Water Resources Investigations 81-22.United States Bureau of Reclamation (USBR). January, 1960. Natural Resources of Northwestern California. Report Appendix – Plans of Water Development.Regional Water Quality Control Board. 1989. Ground Water Contamination by Pesticides on the Smith River Plains, Del Norte County, North Coast Region. Regional Water Quality Control Board.Strand RG. 1963. Geologic Map of California [Weed Sheet]. California Division of Mines and Geology.BibliographyBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1958. Ground Water Conditions in Central and NorthernCalifornia 1957-58. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 77-58.California Department of Water Resources. 1964. Quality of Ground Water in California 1961-62, Part 1: Northern and Central California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 66-62.California Department of Water Resources. 1966. Water Well Standards, Del Norte County, California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 74-3.California Department of Water Resources. 1970. North Coastal Area Action Program. A Study of the Smith River basin and Plain. Bulletin 105-3.California Department of Water Resources. 1974. Smith River Gravel Study. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.Last update 2/27/04
North Coast Hydrologic Region Smith River Plain Groundwater BasinCalifornia Department of Water Resources. 1998. California Water Plan Update. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 160-98 Volumes 1 and 2.California Deptartment of Public Works. 1954. Summary Report on Water Quality, Cresent City and Vicinity, Del Norte County. California Deptartment of Public Works, Division of Water Resources.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Dupre WR, Morrison RB, Clifton HE, Lajoie KR, Ponti DJ. 1991. Quaternary Geology of the Pacific Margin. USGS.Pessagno EA, Blome CD. 1990. Implications of New Jurassic Stratigraphic, Geochronometric, and Paleolatitudinal Data from the Western Klamath Terrane (Smith River and Rogue Valley Subterranes). Geology.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.Rantz SE. 1964. Surface-water Hydrology of Coastal Basins of Northern California. USGS. Report No.1758.Wagner DL. 1989. Geology of Del Norte and Siskiyou Counties and Adjacent Portions of Humboldt, Shasta and Trinity Counties. California Geology.Wagner DL, Saucedo GJ. 1987. Geologic Map of the Weed Quadrangle, California, Regional Geologic Map Series 4A. California Division of Mines and Geology.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04