North Coast Hydrologic Region Pepperwood Town Area Groundwater BasinPepperwood Town Area Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 1-30• County: Humboldt• Surface Area: 6,290 acres (10 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Pepperwood Town Area Groundwater Basin occupies a small alluviated valley along the Eel River downstream of the community of Englewood. The basin is bounded on most sides by Tertiary marine sedimentary rocks of the Wildcat series (Strand 1962). The Wildcat series is a group of five formations ranging in age from Miocene to Pleistocene consisting of sandstone, marine siltstone, and claystone (Evenson 1959). The basin is bounded to a limited extent to the west by Upper Cretaceous marine sedimentary rocks (Srand 1962). The basins primary aquifer is comprised of Quaternary non-marine terrace and alluvial deposits. Annual precipitation ranges from 45- to 53-inches.Hydrogeologic InformationHydrogeologic information was not available for the following:Water-Bearing Formations Groundwater Level Trends Groundwater StorageGroundwater Budget (Type B)The estimate of groundwater extraction for the Pepperwood Town Area Basin is based on a 1996 survey conducted by the California Department of Water Resources. The survey included landuse and sources of water. Groundwater extraction for agricultural use is estimated to be 850 acre-feet. Groundwater extraction for municipal and industrial uses is estimated to be 97 acre-feet. Deep percolation of applied water is estimated to be 230 acre- feet.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Groundwater QualityHydrogeologic information was not available.Well Production characteristics Well yields (gal/min)￼IrrigationDomestic IrrigationNKD – No known dataNKDTotal depths (ft)Range: 26 - 170 Range: 33 - 55Average: 68 (21 Well Completion Reports) Average: 44 (2 Well Completion Reports)￼Last update 2/27/04
North Coast Hydrologic Region Pepperwood Town Area Groundwater BasinActive Monitoring DataCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼AgencyDepartment of Health ServicesParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water qualityNumber of wells /measurement frequency NKD1￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateSelected ReferencesNo known groundwater management plans, groundwater ordinances, or basin adjudications.None None￼￼Evenson, R.E. 1959. Geology and Groundwater Features of Eureka Area, Humboldt County, California. USGS Water Supply Paper 1470.Fraticelli LA, Albers JP, Irwin WP, Blake MC. 1987. Geologic Map of the Redding 1 x 2 Degree Quadrangle, Shasta, Tehama, Humboldt, and Trintity Counties, California. USGS. OF-87-257.Irwin WP. 1960. Geologic Reconnaissance of the Northern Coast Ranges and Klamath Mountains, California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 179.Strand RG. 1962. Geologic Map of California, [Redding Sheet]. Scale 1:250,000. California Division of Mines and Geology.BibliographyBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.Last update 2/27/04