North Coast Hydrologic Region Weott Town Area Groundwater BasinWeott Town Area Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 1-31• County: Humboldt• Surface Area: 3,650 acres (6 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Weott Town Area Groundwater Basin is an irregularly shaped basin consisting of the river valleys of the Eel River, downstream of the community of McCann, and the South Fork Eel River, downstream of Myers Flat. The basin continues north from their confluence. The basin is primarily bounded by Upper Cretaceous marine sedimentary rocks (Strand 1962) with the exception of the valley west of McCann where portions of the valley are bounded by Tertiary marine sedimentary rocks of the Wildcat series (Strand 1962). The Wildcat series is a group of five formations ranging in age from Miocene to Pleistocene consisting of sandstone, marine siltstone, and claystone (Evenson 1959). The basin deposits consist of Quaternary terrace deposits. Annual precipitation ranges from 55- to 61-inches.Hydrogeologic InformationHydrogeologic information was not available for the following:Water-Bearing Formations Groundwater Level Trends Groundwater StorageGroundwater Budget (Type B)The estimate of groundwater extraction for the Weott Town Area Basin is based on a 1996 survey conducted by the California Department of Water Resources. The survey included landuse and sources of water. Groundwater extraction for municipal and industrial uses is estimated to be 110 acre-feet. Deep percolation of applied water is estimated to be 110 acre-feet.Groundwater QualityWater Quality in Public Supply WellsCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Constituent Group1Inorganics – Primary RadiologicalNitratesPesticidesVOCs and SVOCs Inorganics – SecondaryNumber of wells sampled2 21 3 0 0 2Number of wells with a concentration above an MCL3 00 0 0 0 0￼￼1 A description of each member in the constituent groups and a generalized discussion of the relevance of these groups are included in California’s Groundwater – Bulletin 118 by DWR (2003).2 Represents distinct number of wells sampled as required under DHS Title 22 program from 1994 through 2000.Last update 2/27/04
North Coast Hydrologic Region Weott Town Area Groundwater Basin3 Each well reported with a concentration above an MCL was confirmed with a second detection above an MCL. This information is intended as an indicator of the types of activities that cause contamination in a given basin. It represents the water quality at the sample location. It does not indicate the water quality delivered to the consumer. More detailed drinking water quality information can be obtained from the local water purveyor and its annual Consumer Confidence Report.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Well Production characteristics Well yields (gal/min)Municipal/Irrigation NKD￼Domestic Municipal/IrrigationNKD – No known dataActive Monitoring Data53 (1 Well Completion Report)Number of wells /measurement frequency NKD2Total depths (ft)￼￼AgencyDepartment of Health ServicesParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water quality￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateSelected ReferencesNo known groundwater management plans, groundwater ordinances, or basin adjudications.Weott CSD None￼￼Evenson, R.E. 1959. Geology and Groundwater Features of Eureka Area, Humboldt County, California. USGS Water Supply Paper 1470.Fraticelli LA, Albers JP, Irwin WP, Blake MC. 1987. Geologic Map of the Redding 1 x 2 Degree Quadrangle, Shasta, Tehama, Humboldt, and Trintity Counties, California. USGS. OF-87-257.Strand RG. 1962. Geologic Map of California, [Redding Sheet]. Scale 1:250,000. California Division of Mines and Geology.Last update 2/27/04
North Coast Hydrologic Region Weott Town Area Groundwater BasinBibliographyBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Irwin WP. 1960. Geologic Reconnaissance of the Northern Coast Ranges and Klamath Mountains, California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 179.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04