North Coast Hydrologic Region Dinsmores Town Area Groundwater BasinDinsmores Town Area Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 1-34• County: Humboldt, Trinity• Surface Area: 2,300 acres (4 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Dinsmores Town Area Groundwater Basin occupies a southeast trending alluvial valley within a short reach of the Van Duzen River in the vicinity and downstream of the community of Dinsmores. The basin is completely bounded by the Franciscan Formation. Basin deposits consist of Quaternary alluvium (Strand 1962). Annual precipitation ranges from 57- to 61-inches.Hydrogeologic InformationHydrogeologic information was not available for the following:Water-Bearing Formations Groundwater Level Trends Groundwater StorageGroundwater Budget (Type B)Estimates of groundwater extraction are based on a 1996 survey conducted by the California Department of Water Resources. The survey included landuse and sources of water. Groundwater extraction for agricultural use is 46 acre-feet. Groundwater extraction for municipal and industrial uses is estimated to be 78 acre-feet. Deep percolation of applied water is estimated to be 24 acre-feet.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Groundwater QualityHydrogeologic information was not available.Well Production characteristics Well yields (gal/min)￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationNKD – No known dataNKDTotal depths (ft)Range: 27 – 160￼Active Monitoring DataAverage: 89 (13 Well Completion Reports)Number of wells /measurement frequency NKD3￼AgencyDepartment of Health ServicesParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water quality￼Last update 2/27/04
North Coast Hydrologic Region Dinsmores Town Area Groundwater BasinCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateSelected ReferencesNo known groundwater management plans, groundwater ordinances, or basin adjudications.None None￼￼￼Fraticelli LA, Albers JP, Irwin WP, Blake MC. 1987. Geologic Map of the Redding 1 x 2 Degree Quadrangle, Shasta, Tehama, Humboldt, and Trintity Counties, California. USGS. OF-87-257.Irwin WP. 1960. Geologic Reconnaissance of the Northern Coast Ranges and Klamath Mountains, California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 179.Strand, RG. 1962. Geologic Map of California, [Redding Sheet]. Scale 1:250,000. California Division of Mines and Geology.BibliographyBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.Last update 2/27/04