North Coast Hydrologic RegionTen Mile River Valley Groundwater BasinTen Mile RiverValley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 1-40• County: Mendocino• Surface Area: 1,490 acres (approx. 2 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyTen Mile River Valley is an elongate, double-branched coastal drainage basin situated within the Coast Ranges of northwest central Mendocino County and located approximately 8 miles north of Fort Bragg. The north and south fork of Ten Mile River are approximately 5 and 6 miles in total length, respectively, and vary in width from about 0.2 to 0.4 miles. The Ten Mile River Valley Groundwater Basin is defined by the areal extent of Quaternary Alluvium, which is bounded on all sides by bedrock of the Franciscan Formation.The North Fork of Ten Mile River Valley drains to the south and southwest before joining the South Fork approximately 1.5 miles from the Pacific Ocean. The South Fork drains to the northwest into the Pacific Ocean north of the town of Inglenook and Mac Kerricher State Park. Precipitation in this basin ranges from approximately 43 inches near the rivermouth to 49 inches on the eastern sides of the basin.Hydrogeologic InformationWater-Bearing FormationsSignificant water-bearing formations that occur in Ten Mile River Valley include only Quaternary Alluvium. Bedrock of the Franciscan Complex surrounds and underlies the area but due to its consolidated nature, it is essentially non-water bearing except for areas with significant fracture porosity. Information on water-bearing formations and groundwater occurrence was taken from DWR (1958).Alluvium and River Channel Deposits. These deposits are Holocene in age and consist largely of unconsolidated silts, gravels, clays, and sands. These deposits are exposed in the active river channel and floodplain of Ten Mile River. Limited data suggests the alluvium in the smaller valleys in Mendocino County averages 10 to 15 feet thick. The maximum thickness of these deposits is unknown. No published well yield data was identified for wells in this area; however, wells drilled in the small alluvial valleys in Mendocino County have proven unproductive because of low permeability. Groundwater in the alluvial deposits is typically unconfined but may be semi-confined locally. No published specific yield data for alluvium in this area are available.Groundwater Level TrendsNo groundwater level data available.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
North Coast Hydrologic RegionTen Mile River Valley Groundwater BasinGroundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. No data available. Groundwater in Storage. No data available.Groundwater Budget (Type C)No data available.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. No groundwater quality data available.Impairments. No data available; however, since this basin is in contact with the Pacific Ocean, seawater intrusion could reasonably be expected to be a problem.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Well CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationNo data is available.Total depths (ft)Range: 80 - 200 No data is availableAverage: 114 (Based on 15 well completion reports)￼Active Monitoring Data￼AgencyDWR (incl. Cooperators) DWR (incl. Cooperators) Department of Health ServicesParameterGroundwater levelsMineral, nutrient, & minor element. Coliform, nitrates, mineral, organic chemicals, and radiological.Number of wells /measurement frequency NoneNone None￼Basin Management￼Groundwater management: No groundwater management plans were identified.Water agenciesPublic Mendocino County Water Agency. PrivateSelected BibliographyCalifornia Department of Water Resources (DWR) 1958. Recommended Water Well Construction and Sealing Standards, Mendocino County. Bulletin No. 62 – November.￼Last update 2/27/04
North Coast Hydrologic Region California’s Groundwater Ten Mile River Valley Groundwater Basin Bulletin 118ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.￼Last update 2/27/04