North Coast Hydrologic RegionNavarro River Valley Groundwater BasinNavarro River Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 1-46• County: Mendocino• Surface Area: 770 acres (approx. 1 square mile)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyNavarro River Valley is an elongate, west- to northwest-trending coastal drainage basin situated within the Coast Ranges of west central Mendocino County and located approximately 2 miles south of the Town of Albion. Navarro River Valley Groundwater Basin is approximately 5 miles in length and varies in width from about 0.1 to 0.4 miles. The Navarro River Valley Groundwater Basin is defined by the areal extent of Quaternary Alluvium, which is bounded on all sides by bedrock of the Franciscan Formation. This groundwater basin transects the Fort Bragg Terrace Area Groundwater Basin south of Albion.Navarro River Valley Groundwater Basin is drained to the west and northwest by the Navarro River and several of its tributaries; Mustard, Flume, and Marsh Gulches before entering the Pacific Ocean between Navarro Point/Headland and Saddle Point. Precipitation in this basin ranges from about 39 to 43 inches annually.Hydrogeologic InformationWater-Bearing FormationsSignificant water-bearing formations that occur in Navarro River Valley include only Quaternary Alluvium. Bedrock of the Franciscan Complex surrounds and underlies the area but due to its consolidated nature, it is essentially non-water bearing except for areas with significant fracture porosity. Information on water-bearing formations and groundwater conditions was taken from DWR (1958).Alluvium and River Channel Deposits. These deposits are Holocene in age and consist largely of unconsolidated silts, gravels, clays, and sands. These deposits are exposed in the active river channel and floodplain of the Navarro River. Limited data suggests the alluvium in the smaller valleys in Mendocino County averages 10 to 15 feet thick, but may be 100 feet or more in places within the coastal drainages (DWR 1982, 1985). The maximum thickness of these deposits is unknown. No published well yield data was identified for wells in this area; however, wells drilled in the small alluvial valleys in Mendocino County have proven unproductive because of low permeability. Groundwater in the alluvial deposits is typically unconfined but may be semi-confined locally. No published specific yield data for alluvium in this area are available.Groundwater Level TrendsNo groundwater level data available.Groundwater StorageCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
North Coast Hydrologic RegionNavarro River Valley Groundwater BasinGroundwater Storage Capacity. No data available. Groundwater in Storage. No data available.Groundwater Budget (Type C)No data available.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. No data is available.Impairments. No data available; however, since this basin is in connection with the Pacific Ocean, seawater intrusion may be reasonably expected as a potential problem.Well CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationNo data is available.Total depths (ft)Range: 100 – 120 Average: 110 (Based on 2 well completionreports)One well - 120 feet total depth (l well completion report)￼Active Monitoring Data￼AgencyDWR (incl. Cooperators) DWR (incl. Cooperators) Department of Health ServicesParameter Number of wells /measurement frequencyGroundwater levels NoneMineral, nutrient, & None minor element.Coliform, nitrates, None mineral, organicchemicals, and radiological.￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateNo groundwater management plans were identified.Mendocino County Water Agency.￼￼Last update 2/27/04
North Coast Hydrologic RegionNavarro River Valley Groundwater BasinSelected BibliographyCalifornia Department of Water Resources (DWR) 1958. Recommended Water Well Construction and Sealing Standards, Mendocino County. Bulletin No. 62 – November.California Department of Water Resources (DWR) 1982. Mendocino County Coastal Ground Water Study. Northern District. June.California Department of Water Resources (DWR) 1985. Town of Mendocino Ground Water Study. Northern District. June.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04