North Coast Hydrologic RegionScott River Valley Groundwater BasinScott River Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 1-5• County: Siskiyou• Surface Area: 63,900 (100 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Scott River Valley Groundwater Basin is a narrow alluvial floodplain about 28 miles long and 1⁄2- to 4-miles wide. The basin is bounded on the north and northwest by the Scott Bar Mountains, on the west and southwest by the Salmon Mountains, on the south and southeast by the Scott Mountains, and on the east by a northern extension of the Trinity Mountains. Generally, the contact between the valley alluvium and rocks dating from Pre-Silurian to Cretaceous defines the basin boundary. Annual precipitation within the basin is estimated to be 21- to 25-inches.Hydrogeologic InformationWater-Bearing FormationsQuaternary stream channel, floodplain, and alluvial fan deposits are the primary water-bearing deposits in the basin.Holocene Stream Channel Deposits. The stream channel and floodplain alluvial deposits consist of unconsolidated sand and gravel with clay deposited by Scott River and its major tributaries. The most permeable alluvium underlies the east side of Scott Valley between Etna and Fort Jones in an area averaging 11⁄2 miles in width on the floodplain of the Scott River. Large irrigation wells in this area range from 1,200- to 2,500-gpm. Specific capacities range from 67- to 100-gpm per foot of drawdown (Mack 1958). The permeability of the channel deposits ranges up to 1,000 gpd per square foot (SWRCB 1975). Thickness of the deposits ranges up to 260 feet and may exceed that depth near Scott River (SWRCB 1975). Alluvium within east Scott River tributaries has lower permeability and likely provides sufficient quantity of groundwater for domestic wells.Pleistocene to Holocene Alluvial Fan Deposits. The alluvial fan deposits consist of sandy clay with boulders deposited by lateral tributaries along the western valley margin. These surficial deposits grade towards the valley into fine sand and clay and interfinger with Scott River floodplain deposits. Fan deposits may also underlie the stream channel alluvium of the eastern valley tributaries. Generally, the alluvium deposited as fans is less permeable than the alluvium beneath the Scott River floodplain. The most permeable sediments along the western mountain front are found in the large gravelly fans deposited by West Patterson, Kidder, Etna, and Shackleford creeks and in stream channels.Older alluvial deposits are also found along the valley margins. These consist of remnants of alluvial fan and terrace deposits, primarily of sand and silty clay with boulders. The older alluvium is not considered to be an important groundwater source.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
North Coast Hydrologic RegionScott River Valley Groundwater BasinRecharge AreasThe major source of recharge into stream channel and floodplain deposits between Etna and Fort Jones is underflows and surface runoff originating upstream of the vicinity of Etna. This is supplemented by underflow from the western tributaries (SWRCB 1975).Groundwater Level TrendsAnalysis incomplete.Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. Groundwater storage capacity to a depth of 100 feet is estimated to be 400,000 acre-feet for a surface area of 39,900 acres with specific yield ranging from 5 to 15 percent (Mack 1958).Groundwater Budget (Type B)Estimates of groundwater extraction for the Scott River Valley Basin are based on a survey conducted by the California Department of Water Resources during 1991. Surveys included land use and sources of water. Estimates of groundwater extraction for agricultural and municipal/industrial uses are 23,000, and 1,300 acre-feet respectively. Deep percolation of applied water is estimated to be 13,000 acre-feet.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. The major water type in the basin is calcium-magnesium bicarbonate water. Total dissolved solids range from 47- to 1,510-mg/L, averaging 258 mg/L (DWR unpublished data).Impairments. Locally high concentrations of iron, manganese, sodium, chloride, total dissolved solids, calcium, and ASAR occur in the basin. Potassium, sulfate, nitrate, fluoride, and boron occur in negligible amounts (Mack 1958). Hard waters occur locally on the eastern side of the valley. Northward from Callahan, these areas include McConnahue and Hamlin Gulches and Moffett Creek (Mack 1958).Water Quality in Public Supply WellsCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Constituent Group1Inorganics – Primary RadiologicalNitratesPesticidesVOCs and SVOCs Inorganics – SecondaryNumber of wells sampled2 40 4 1 1 4Number of wells with a concentration above an MCL3 10 0 0 0 1￼￼1 A description of each member in the constituent groups anddiscussion of the relevance of these groups are included in California’s Groundwater – Bulletin 118 by DWR (2003).2 Represents distinct number of wells sampled as required under DHS Title 22 program from 1994 through 2000.Last update 2/27/04a generalized
North Coast Hydrologic RegionScott River Valley Groundwater Basin3 Each well reported with a concentration above an MCL was confirmed with a second detection above an MCL. This information is intended as an indicator of the types of activities that cause contamination in a given basin. It represents the water quality at the sample location. It does not indicate the water quality delivered to the consumer. More detailed drinking water quality information can be obtained from the local water purveyor and its annual Consumer Confidence Report.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Well CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)￼IrrigationDomestic IrrigationRange: 30 – 3000Total depths (ft)Range: 17 – 460 Range: 13 – 400￼Active Monitoring DataAverage: 794 (27 Well Completion Reports)Average: 104 (666 Well Completion Reports)Average: 106 (167 Well Completion Reports)Number of wells /measurement frequency 6 wells semi-annually10 wells biennial 5￼AgencyDWR DWRDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous Water Quality Miscellaneous Water Quality￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateSelected ReferencesScott River and the region of interconnected groundwater is adjudicated.Siskiyou County adopted a groundwater management ordinance in 1998.Scott Valley ID￼￼California State Water Resources Control Board. 1974. Report on Water Supply and Use of Water, Scott River Stream System, Scott River Adjudication, Siskiyou County. California Division of Water Rights.California State Water Resources Control Board (SWRCB). 1975. Report on Hydrogeologic Conditions, Scott River Valley, Scott River Adjudication, Siskiyou County. California Division of Water Rights.Last update 2/27/04
North Coast Hydrologic RegionScott River Valley Groundwater BasinCalifornia State Water Resources Control Board. 1980. Scott River Adjudication, Decree No. 30662 Superior Court for Siskiyou County.Mack S. 1958. Geology and Ground Water of Scott Valley, Siskiyou County, California. USGS. Water Supply Paper 1462.BibliographyBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1958. Ground Water Conditions in Central and Northern California 1957-58. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 77-58.California Department of Water Resources. 1960. Northeastern Counties Investigation. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 58.California Department of Water Resources. 1964. Quality of Ground Water in California 1961-62, Part 1: Northern and Central California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 66-62.California Department of Water Resources. 1964. Klamath River Basin Investigation. Bulletin 83.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.Davis GA. 1966. Metamorphic and Granitic History of the Klamath Mountains. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190. p.39-50Davis GA, Lipman PW. 1962. Revised Structural Sequences of Pre-Cretaceous Metamorphic Rocks in the Southern Klamath Mountains, California. Geological Society of America 73(12):1547-1552.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Irwin WP. 1960. Geologic Reconnaissance of the Northern Coast Ranges and Klamath Mountains, California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 179.Irwin WP. 1966. Geology of the Klamath Mountain Province. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190. p.19-38.Irwin WP. 1981. Tectonic Accretion of the Klamath Mountains. In: Ernst WG, editor. The Geotectonic Development of California: Prentice Hall, Inc. p 29-49.Mankinen EA, Irwin WP, Graomme CS. 1984. Implications of Paleomagnetism for the Tectonic History of the Eastern Klamath and Related Terrains in California and Oregon. Pacific Section Society of Economic Paleontologists and Mineralogists No. 42 (Geology of the Upper Cretaceous Hornbrook Formation, Oregon and Californa): 221-229.Mortimer N, Coleman RG. 1984. A Neogene Structural Done in the Klamath Mountains, California and Oregon. Pacific Petroleum Geologist 42(Geology of the Upper Cretaceous Hornbrook Formation, Oregon and California): 179-186.Nilsen TH. 1984. Stratigraphy, Sedimentology, and Tectonic Framework of the Upper Cretaceous Hornbrook Formation, Oregon and California. Pacific Section Society of Economic Paleontologists and Mineralogists 42(Geology of the Upper Cretaceous Hornbrook Formation, Oregon and California): 51-58.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.Smith JP. 1894. The Metamorphic Series, Shasta County, California. Journal of Geology 2:588-612.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
North Coast Hydrologic RegionScott River Valley Groundwater BasinStrand RG. 1969. Geologic Atlas of California [Weed Sheet]. California Division of Mines and Geology.Wagner DL, Saucedo GJ. 1987. Geologic Map of the Weed Quadrangle, California, Regional Geologic Map Series 4A. California Division of Mines and Geology.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04