Colorado River Hydrologic Region Ames Valley Groundwater BasinAmes Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 7-16• County: San Bernardino• Surface Area: 110,000 acres (169.7 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThis groundwater basin underlies Ames Valley, Homestead Valley, and Pipes Wash in the southcentral San Bernardino County. The basin is bounded by nonwater-bearing rocks of the San Benrardino Mountains on the west, of Iron Ridge on the north, and of Hidalgo Mountain on the northeast (Rogers 1967). The Emerson, Copper Mountain, and West Calico faults form parts of the eastern and northern boundaries. The southern boundary and parts of the northern and eastern boundaries lie along surface drainage divides. The valley is drained northeastward by Pipes Wash to Emerson (dry) Lake. Average annual precipitation ranges from 4 to 12 inches.Hydrogeologic InformationWater Bearing FormationsThe water-bearing materials in this basin consist of unconsolidated to partly consolidated Miocene to Quaternary age continental deposits (Mendez and Christensen 1997). Wells in Ames Valley Groundwater Basin reach a maximum depth of 838 feet without encountering bedrock. Regionally, these deposits are estimated to range to 10,000 feet in thickness (Moyle 1984).The main water-bearing deposits are interbedded gravels, conglomerates, and silts deposited in alluvial fans (Schaefer 1978). Other less productive deposits include alluvial channel sands and gravels; silt, clay, and sandy-clay deposits in Emerson Lake playa; and dune sands (Schaefer 1978; Bookman- Edmonston Engineering 1994). These deposits have an average specific yield of about 14 percent (Lewis 1972), and well yields range from 30 to 2,000 gpm. Groundwater is typically unconfined in the alluvial deposits (Schaefer 1978), but may be confined near dry lakes where fine-grained deposits are found.Restrictive StructuresSeveral faults cut northwestward across this basin causing the water table to step down toward the east (Moyle 1974; French 1978; Mendez and Christensen 1997), which indicates they are partial barriers to groundwater flow. Groundwater levels drop eastward across the Johnson Valley fault 100 to 175 feet and across the Emerson fault 25 to 50 feet (Lewis 1972; Moyle 1974). Groundwater levels may drop eastward about 550 feet across the Homestead Valley fault (Moyle 1974).Recharge AreasNatural recharge of the basin is mainly from percolation of stream flow from the San Bernardino Mountains and precipitation to the valley floor (Mendez and Christensen 1997; Bookman-Edmonston Engineering 1994). Percolation of septic tank effluent from the town of Landers and surrounding communities also contributes to recharge of groundwater. Some subsurface inflow may come from Means Valley Groundwater Basin, and subsurfaceCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Colorado River Hydrologic Region Ames Valley Groundwater Basinoutflow probably crosses the Emerson fault into Deadman Valley Groundwater Basin (French 1978; Mendez and Christensen 1997).Groundwater Level TrendsGroundwater in this basin flows eastward from the San Bernardino Mountains to the Emerson fault and northeast toward Emerson (dry) Lake (Mendez and Christensen 1997). In the central part of the basin near Landers, one well declined about 15 feet during 1981 through 1999. In the eastern and northern parts of the basin, water levels were stable during 1952 through 2000, varying about 2 feet.Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. Total storage capacity is estimated to be 1,200,000 af (DWR 1975).Groundwater in Storage. Groundwater in storage in 1969 is estimated to be 540,000 af (Lewis 1972).Groundwater Budget (Type C)About 500 af/yr of underflow may be moving through the sediments in Pipes Wash, the main recharge source (Lewis 1972).Groundwater QualityCharacterization. Groundwater in the basin is sodium bicarbonate in character. The TDS content of water from one well near Landers is 233 mg/L (MWA 1999). The TSD content of water from 8 public supply wells ranges from 246 to 390 mg/L and averages 312 mg/L.Impairments. Groundwater in the basin has locally high TDS, fluoride, and chloride contents (DWR 1975). TDS content reaches about 1,000 mg/L southwest of Emerson Lake (MWA 1999).Water Quality in Public Supply WellsCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Constituent Group1Inorganics – Primary RadiologicalNitratesPesticidesVOCs and SVOCs Inorganics – SecondaryNumber of wells sampled2 1010 10 10 10 10Number of wells with a concentration above an MCL3 03 0 0 0 0￼￼1 A description of each member in the constituent groups anddiscussion of the relevance of these groups are included in California’s Groundwater – Bulletin 118 by DWR (2003).2 Represents distinct number of wells sampled as required under DHS Title 22 program from 1994 through 2000.3 Each well reported with a concentration above an MCL was confirmed with a second detection above an MCL. This information is intended as an indicator of the types of activities that cause contamination in a given basin. It represents the water quality at the sample location. It does not indicate the water quality delivered to theLast update 2/27/04a generalized
Colorado River Hydrologic Region Ames Valley Groundwater Basinconsumer. More detailed drinking water quality information can be obtained from the local water purveyor and its annual Consumer Confidence Report.Well Production characteristics Well yields (gal/min)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationActive Monitoring DataAgencyUSGS USGSDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water quality Title 22 water qualityNumber of wells /measurement frequency 193 11Range: 30 – 2,000 (Well Completion Reports)Total depths (ft)￼￼￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateReferences CitedThis basin is managed under a Regional Water Management Plan adopted in 1994 by the Mojave Water Agency (MWA 1999).Mojave Water Agency￼￼Bookman-Edmonston Engineering Inc. (BEE). 1994. Regional water management plan: Mojave Water Agency, Apple Valley California,.135 p.California Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1975. California’s Ground Water. Bulletin 118. 135 p.French, J.J. 1978. Ground-water storage in the Johnson Valley area, San Bernardino County, California: U.S. Geological Survey Water-Resources Investigations Report 77-130. 35 p.Lewis, R.E. 1972. Ground-Water Resources of the Yucca Valley-Joshua Tree area, San Bernardino County, California. U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report. 51 p.Mendez, G.O. and A.H. Christensen. 1997. Regional water table (1996) and water-level changes in the Mojave River, the Morongo, and the Fort Irwin ground-water basins, San Bernardino County, California: U.S. Geological Survey Water-Resources Investigations Report 97-4160. 34 p.Mojave Water Agency (MWA). 1999. Fourth Annual Engineer’s Report on Water Supply, for Water Year 1997-1998. Apple Valley, California. 77p.Moyle, W.R., Jr. 1974. Geohydrologic map of southern California: U.S. Geological Survey Water-Resources Investigations Report 48-73.________. 1984. Bouguer gravity anomaly map of the Twentynine Palms Marine Corps Base and vicinity, California: U.S. Geological Survey Water-Resources Investigations Report 84-4005.Last update 2/27/04
Colorado River Hydrologic Region Ames Valley Groundwater BasinRogers, T. H. 1967. Geologic Map of California, San Bernardino Sheet. Olaf P. Jenkins Edition. California Division of Mines and Geology. 1 sheet. Scale 1:250,000.Schaefer, D.H. 1978. Ground-water resources of the Marine Corps Base, Twentynine Palms, San Bernardino County, California: U.S. Geological Survey Water-Resources Investigations Report 77-37. 29 p.Additional ReferencesAkers, J.P. 1986. Geohydrology and potential for artificial recharge in the western part of the U.S. Marine Corps Base, Twentynine Palms, California, 1982-83. U.S. Geological Survey Water-Resources Investigations Report 84-4119. 18 p.Bader, J.S. 1963. Effect of faulting in alluvium on the occurrence, movement, and quality of ground water in the Twentynine Palms area, California (abstract). Geological Society of America Special Paper 73. 22 p.California Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1960. Data on Water wells and Springs in the Yucca Valley-Twentynine Palms area, San Bernardino and Riverside Counties, California. Bulletin 91-2. 163 p.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04