Tulare Lake Hydrologic RegionWalker Basin Creek Valley Groundwater BasinWalker Basin Creek Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-26• County: Kern• Surface Area: 7,670 acres (12 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Walker Basin Creek Valley is a fault-influenced, shallow alluvial basin within the southern Sierra Nevada. The basin is bound by Breckenridge Mountain, Red Mountain and Harper Peak to the west, northeast, and southeast, respectively. The basin is triangular in shape with a drainage outlet (Walker Basin Creek) at its southern apex. The Breckenridge Fault forms the linear western boundary of the basin (Smith 1964). Average annual precipitation ranges from 14 to 16 inches.Hydrogeologic InformationWater Bearing FormationsThe basin is predominantly surrounded by granitic rocks typical of the southern Sierra Nevada. Metamorphic bedrock (including marble) outcrops along the northeastern basin boundary.Both granitic and metamorphic rocks floor the basin at depth. While mostly granitic bedrock is described in drill logs, some marble bedrock was noted in wells near the northeastern basin boundary and also from the central portion of the basin.Based on review of available well completion reports, the alluvial basin fill is thin, ranging in thickness from a few feet to over 150 feet, with an average thickness of approximately 70 feet. Description of surficial materials on well completion reports includes abundant decomposed granitic rock, and sand, clay and minor gravel.Restrictive StructuresBelow the decomposed granitic rock, drill logs note that more competent bedrock often exhibits abundant fracturing, probably as a result of proximity to the Breckenridge Fault, or to the Kern Canyon Fault, which projects beneath the valley fill (Smith 1964). Because of the shallow nature of the alluvial fill, much to most of the groundwater in the basin is derived from the bedrock. Well completion reports indicate that some of the best producing wells in the basin are at the basin center and axis where the alluvial fill is thickest.Recharge AreasGroundwater recharge is from percolation of direct precipitation and from ephemeral and spring-fed perennial streams entering the basin.Groundwater Budget (Type C)There are not enough data to estimate a budget for this basin.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Tulare Lake Hydrologic RegionWalker Basin Creek Valley Groundwater BasinGroundwater QualityThe characterization of the basin has not been determined.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Well CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)￼Municipal/Irrigation Domestic:Domestic Municipal/IrrigationRange:50 - 650 Range: 0.5 – 300Total depths (ft)Range: 105 - 677 Range: 120 - 400￼Active Monitoring DataAverage:(2 Well completion reports)Average: 41(56 Well completion reports)Average: 278(48 Well completion reports)Average: 238(5 Well completion reports)Number of wells /measurement frequency 1 Varies￼AgencyDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsParameterTitle 22 water qualityBasin ManagementGroundwater management: None Water agenciesPublic None Private NoneReferences Cited￼￼California Department of Water Resources, San Joaquin District. Well completion report files.Ross, Donald C. 1986. Basement-Rock Correlations Across the White Wolf-Breckenridge- Southern Kern Canyon Fault Zone, Southern Sierra Nevada, California. U.S..Geological Survey Bulletin 1651.Smith, Arthur R. (compiler). 1964. Bakersfield Sheet of Geologic Map of California. California Division of Mines and Geology (CDMG). Scale 1:250,000.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.Last update 2/27/04