Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Goose Lake Valley Groundwater BasinGoose Lake Valley Groundwater Basin, Lower Goose Lake Valley Subbasin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-1.01• County: Modoc• Surface Area: 36,000 acres (56 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Lower Goose Lake Valley Groundwater Subbasin is part of the Goose Lake Valley Groundwater Basin which extends north into Lake County, Oregon. The valley is approximately 47 miles long and 12 miles wide. The basin is a downfaulted block with numerous bounding faults on the west and east side of the valley.The subbasin is bounded on the north by Goose Lake, on the east by Pliocene and Tertiary basalt and Tertiary intrusive rocks of the Warner Mountains, and on the west by Pliocene basalt of the Modoc Plateau. The surface area of Goose Lake is variable given that the lake is an intermittent lake and has been completely dry several times since the early 1900’s (DWR 1963). Several tributary streams flow into the subbasin from the Warner Mountains. At the southern end of the subbasin, tributary streams flow south to the North Fork Pit River. Annual precipitation ranges from 15- to 17-inches.Hydrogeologic InformationWater-Bearing FormationsThe primary water-bearing formations are Holocene sedimentary deposits (which include lake deposits, intermediate alluvium, and alluvial fan deposits), Pleistocene near-shore deposits, Pliocene to Pleistocene lava flows, and to a lesser extent, the Plio-Pleistocene Alturas Formation. The following summary of water-bearing formations is from DWR (1963).Holocene Sedimentary Deposits. The lake deposits consist of unconsolidated interstratified clay and silty clay. Water produced from these sediments may be of poor quality depending on the degree of alkalinity. Thickness of the deposits ranges up to 1,000 feet.The intermediate alluvium consists of unconsolidated, poorly sorted silt and sand with lenses of gravel up to a thickness of 100 feet. These zones are moderately permeable.The alluvial fan deposits consist of unconsolidated to poorly consolidated, partially stratified sand, gravel, and silt with lenses of clay. These deposits are generally the most permeable of the valley sedimentary deposits. The eastside alluvial fans range up to 300 feet in thickness and are considered the most important groundwater source. The upper fan areas are moderately to highly permeable and, where saturated, can yield large amounts of water to wells. The mid- to lower fans are generally less permeable but contain confined zones yielding moderate amounts of water to wells. The west side fans, ranging in thickness to 100 feet, are less permeable resulting in low to moderate well yields.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Goose Lake Valley Groundwater BasinPleistocene Near-Shore Deposits. Near-shore deposits occur at the south end of the subbasin and overlie the basin in the southwest trending towards the northeast subbasin boundary. The deposits are moderately to highly permeable and may yield large quantities of water to wells.Pleistocene Volcanic Rocks. The Pleistocene volcanic rocks consist of highly jointed flat lying basalt flows ranging from 50 to 200 feet in thickness with interbedded scoriaceous zones and pyroclastic rocks. In the surrounding upland, these rocks serve as a recharge zone; in the valley they interfinger with valley sediments and act as a forebay to water-bearing deposits. In general these rocks are highly permeable and can yield large amounts of water to wells.Plio-Pleistocene Volcanic Rocks. The Plio-Pleistocene volcanic rocks consist of highly jointed basalt flows with some zones of scoria and interbedded pyroclastic rocks. The deposits range up to 500 feet in thickness. These rocks are generally highly permeable and are areas of recharge where exposed at the ground surface. Flows from the west side of the basin contain numerous permeable zones which likely provide large quantities of water to wells. On the east side of the basin, multiple flows of fractured lava are interbedded within the valley sedimentary deposits. Wells penetrating these rocks yield moderate to high quantities of water.Plio-Pleistocene Alturas Formation. The Alturas Formation consists of slightly consolidated, well-bedded, tuffaceous sandstone and occurs at depth in the basin separating younger and older lava flows. The deposits are moderately permeable and may provide moderate amounts of confined water to deep wells. Thickness of the formation ranges up to 500 feet.Recharge AreasUpland recharge areas consist of permeable basalt flows of Pliocene to Pleistocene age. Precipitation and surface runoff infiltrates the basalt flows and percolates towards the valley recharging valley sediments. Most of the recharge to deeper aquifers along the east side of the California portion of Goose Lake Valley is derived from infiltration of surface water, generally along the foothill portions of stream channels. A relatively large portion of precipitation occurring along the west side of the valley infiltrates upland recharge areas (DWR 1963).Groundwater Level TrendsAnalysis incomplete.Groundwater StorageGroundwater storage to a depth of 500 feet is estimated to be 1,000,000 acre- feet (DWR 1963). The percentage of the 1,000,000 acre-feet located within Fandango Valley Subbasin is unknown. DWR (1963) notes that the amount of water that is useable is unknown.Groundwater Budget (Type B)Estimates of groundwater extraction for the Goose Lake Basin (including Lower Goose Lake Valley Subbasin and the Fandango Subbasin) are basedCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Goose Lake Valley Groundwater Basinon a survey conducted by the California Department of Water Resources during 1997. The survey included land use and sources of water. Estimates of groundwater extraction for agricultural and municipal /industrial uses are 10,000, and 25 acre-feet respectively. Deep percolation from applied water is estimated to be 1,600 acre-feet.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. Calcium bicarbonate type waters occur throughout the basin. The concentration of total dissolved solids averages 183 mg/L and ranges between 66- to 528-mg/L (DWR unpublished data).California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Well CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)￼IrrigationDomestic IrrigationRange: 350– 2000Total depths (ft)Range: 80 – 440 Range: 212 – 865￼Active Monitoring DataAverage: 1117 (2 Well Completion Reports)Average: 209 (32 Well Completion Reports) Average: 520 ( 26 Well Completion Reports)Number of wells /measurement frequency 9 wells semi-annually9 wells biennially 5￼AgencyDWR DWRDepartment of Health ServicesParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous Water Quality Miscellaneous Water Quality￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateSelected ReferencesModoc County adopted a groundwater management ordinance in 2000.￼￼California Department of Water Resources (DWR). February 1963. Northeastern Counties Ground Water Investigation. Bulletin 98, Volumes I and II.California Department of Water Resources. 1965. Office Report Geology, Northeastern Counties Ground Water investigation. Bulletin 98, Appendix C.BibliographyBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Goose Lake Valley Groundwater BasinCalifornia Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Lorenson TD, Mann GM. 1992. Thermogenic Hydrocarbon Gases From Thermal Springs in Eastern Oregon and Northeastern California. Geological Society of America.Phillips KN, Van Denburgh AS. 1971. Hydrology and Geochemistry of Abert, Summer, and Goose Lakes, and Other Closed-Basin Lakes in South-Central Oregon. USGS. 502-B.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.Reed JE, Bedinger MS, Langer WH, Ireland RL, Mulvihill DA. 1984. Maps Showing Ground- Water Units, Withdrawl, and Levels Springs and Depth to Ground-water, Basin and Range Province, Northern California. USGS. WRI 83-4115-A. 11 p.Thompson TH, Chappell R. 1983. Maps Showing Distribution of Dissolved Solids and Dominant Chemical Type in Ground Water, Basin and Range Province, Northern California. USGS. WRI 83-4115-B.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04