Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Big Valley Groundwater BasinBig Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-15• County: Lake• Surface Area: 24,210 acres (38 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Big Valley Basin is located in the west-central portion of Lake County. The basin has been referred to as the Kelseyville Basin in previous versions of Bulletin 118. The basin name has been changed from Kelseyville Basin to the Big Valley Basin in this bulletin update to reflect past investigative work and to avoid any confusion with references to the Kelseyville Subbasin – an aquifer system within Big Valley. Plio-Pleistocene extrusive rocks of Mt. Konocti and Camelback Ridge border the basin to the east and southeast. The Jurassic-Cretaceous Franciscan Formation borders the basin to the west and south and constitutes the basement rock (SMFE 1967). The north side of the basin is open to Clear Lake. The basin shares a boundary with the Scott Valley Basin to the northwest and may be hydrologically contiguous. Precipitation in the basin ranges from 22- to 35-inches annually, decreasing to the northeast.Previous work conducted in the valley identified eight subbasins based on geologic structure, geologic material, and aquifer conditions (perched or confined conditions) (SMFE 1967). For the purpose of this basin summary, the valley has been divided into five subbasins based on geologic conditions, groundwater boundaries, and topography. These areas are referred to as the Western Upland, the Adobe Creek-Manning Creek Subbasin, the Kelseyville Subbasin, the Central Upland and Upper Big Valley Subbasin, and the Cole Creek Upland.The Western Upland is a one-half to one-mile wide topographic bench located along the western margin of the basin. The Adobe Creek - Manning Creek Subbasin is located east of the Western Upland, extends north to the Big Valley Fault, and is hydrologically connected to the Kelseyville Subbasin. The Kelseyville Subbasin is located north of the Big Valley Fault and extends north to Clear Lake. The Central Upland and Upper Big Valley Subbasin includes the eastern half of the basin south of the Big Valley Fault and is geologically similar to the Western Upland but is separated topographically by the Adobe Creek – Manning Creek Subbasin and separated structurally by the Adobe Creek Fault system. The Cole Creek Upland is located east of the Central Upland and Upper Big Valley system and is bounded to the north by the Mt. Konocti volcanics and to the south by Camel Back Ridge.Hydrogeologic InformationThe Big Valley Basin is comprised of extensive Quaternary to late Tertiary alluvial deposits, including fan deposits, lake bed and flood plain deposits, and terrace uplands.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Big Valley Groundwater BasinWater-Bearing FormationsThe primary water-bearing formations in the basin are Quaternary alluvium, lake, and terrace deposits and Upper Pliocene to Lower Pleistocene volcanic ash deposits.Quaternary Alluvium. Surface distribution of younger alluvium is observed throughout the Adobe Creek – Manning Creek and Kelseyville aquifer systems. The younger alluvium generally extends to depths of 40- to 90-feet and consists of alternating strata of gravel, sand, silt, and clay. Alluvial fan deposits extend from the eastern boundary to the northeast- southwest trending Adobe Creek Fault Zone (DWR 1957).Quaternary Terrace Deposits. Quaternary terrace deposits are observed south of the east-west trending Wight Way Fault system and along the western margin of the valley within the Western Upland. The deposits consist of red-brown, poorly stratified, sand, clay, and moderately well rounded gravels (DWR 1957). Permeability of the formation is generally low. Thickness of the deposits range from 50- to 100-feet (SMFE 1967).Quaternary to Tertiary Lake Deposits. Plio-Pleistocene lake deposits underlie all terrace deposits and younger alluvium in most places. The deposit consists of blue clay with alternating strata of shale and limestone. Permeability of the formation is generally low; however, groundwater flow through sedimentary strata and volcanic deposits can be significant (DWR 1957). Thickness of the formation ranges up to 500 feet (SMFE 1967).Upper Pliocene to Lower Pleistocene Volcanic Ash Deposit. An unconsolidated coarse ash deposit ranging in depth from 70- to 240-feet has been encountered in a number of wells (DWR 1957). The volcanic ash is a thin bed of lithic tuff confined within older semiconsolidated sediments and occupies the Western Upland, Adobe Creek-Manning Creek, and most of the Central Upland and Upper Big Valley aquifer system situated south of the Big Valley Fault. The ash layer is offset by the northeast/southwest trending Adobe fault system. Groundwater contained within the deposit is confined with pressure heads ranging between 100- to 150-feet. Thickness of the deposit averages 2 feet (SMFE 1967).Recharge AreasRecharge in the northern portion of the Big Valley Basin is primarily infiltration from Kelsey Creek and by underflow from the Adobe Creek- Manning Creek Subbasin. Underflow occurs mainly from more permeable zones at depths of 25- to 45-feet and 70- to 90-feet. A limited amount of underflow probably enters the basin from the Central Upland system and from Mt. Konocti. Some recharge by infiltration of rain, applied water, and creek water occurs in areas other than the Kelsey Creek flood plain; however, direct surface recharge is inhibited by clayey soil and the near surface clay layer (SMFE 1967).Recharge within the Adobe Creek-Manning Creek Subbasin is from percolation from the channels of Highland and Adobe Creeks and from underflow from the Western Upland and Central Upland areas.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Big Valley Groundwater BasinGroundwater Level TrendsEvaluation of the groundwater level data shows an average seasonal fluctuation ranging from 5- to 15-feet for normal and dry years with some wells located in the center of the subbasin varying from 15- to 30-feet. A review of the hydrographs for long-term comparison of spring-spring groundwater levels indicates a decline in groundwater levels of 5- to 10-feet associated with the 1976-77 and 1987-94 droughts, followed by a recovery in levels to pre-drought conditions of early 1970’s and 1980’s. Overall there does not appear to be any increasing or decreasing trend in the groundwater levels.Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. DWR (1960) estimates storage capacity to be 105,000 acre-feet for a saturated depth interval of 10 to 100-feet. Useable storage is estimated to be 60,000 acre-feet.Groundwater Budget (Type B)Estimates of groundwater extraction for the Big Valley Basin are based on a survey conducted by the California Department of Water Resources in 1995. The survey included land use and sources of water. Estimates of groundwater extraction for agricultural and municipal/industrial uses are 24,000 and 410 acre-feet respectively. Deep percolation from applied water is estimated to be 5,600 acre-feet.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. Magnesium bicarbonate is the predominant groundwater type in the basin. Total dissolved solids range from 270- to 790-mg/L, averaging 535 mg/L (DWR unpublished data).Impairments. Boron is present in groundwater at concentrations that may be injurious to crops (SMFE 1967).Water Quality in Public Supply WellsCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Constituent Group1Inorganics – Primary RadiologicalNitratesPesticidesVOCs and SVOCs Inorganics – SecondaryNumber of wells sampled2 86 8 6 5 8Number of wells with a concentration above an MCL3 00 0 0 0 6￼￼1 A description of each member in the constituent groups anddiscussion of the relevance of these groups are included in California’s Groundwater – Bulletin 118 by DWR (2003).2 Represents distinct number of wells sampled as required under DHS Title 22 program from 1994 through 2000.3 Each well reported with a concentration above an MCL was confirmed with a second detection above an MCL. This information is intended as an indicator of the types of activities that cause contamination in a given basin. It represents the water quality at the sample location. It does not indicate the water quality delivered to theLast update 2/27/04a generalized
Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Big Valley Groundwater Basinconsumer. More detailed drinking water quality information can be obtained from the local water purveyor and its annual Consumer Confidence Report.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Well CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)￼Municipal/Irrigation DomesticMunicipal/IrrigationRange: 30 – 1470Total depths (ft)Range: 20 – 660Range: 48 – 524￼Active Monitoring DataAverage: 475 (32 Well Completion Reports)Average: 103 (414 Well Completion Reports)Average: 162 (285 Well Completion Reports)Number of wells /measurement frequency 16 wells semi-annually49 wells monthly 11 wells biennially7￼AgencyDWRLake CountyDWRDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsParameterGroundwater levelsGroundwater Levels Miscellaneous water qualityTitle 22 water quality￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateSelected ReferencesLake County adopted a groundwater management ordinance in 1999.An AB3030 groundwater management plan was adopted in 1999.County of Lake￼￼California Department of Water Resources (DWR). July 1957. Lake County Investigation. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 14.California Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1960. Northeastern Counties Investigation. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 58.Hearn BC, Donnelly JM, Goff FE. 1975. Geology and Geochronology of the Clear Lake Volcanics, California. USGS. 75-296.Hearn BC, Jr., McLaughlin RJ, Donnelly-Nolan JM. 1988. Tectonic Framework of the Clear Lake Basin, California. Geological Society of America.Ott Water Engineers, Inc. 1987. Lake County Resource Management Plan Update. Lake County Flood Control and Water Conservation District.McLaughlin RJ, Ohlin HN, Blome CD. 1983. Tectonostratigraphic Framework of the Franciscan Assemblage and Lower Part of the Great Valley Sequence in the Geysers- Clear Lake Region, California. American Geophysical Union, Eos, Transactions.Last update 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Big Valley Groundwater BasinRymer MJ. 1978. Stratigraphy of the Cache Formation (Pliocene-Pleistocene) in Clear Lake basin, Lake County, California. USGS.Rymer MJ. 1981. Stratigraphic Revision of the Cache Formation (Pliocene and Pliestocene), Lake County, California. USGS.Rymer MJ. 1983. Late Cenozoic Stratigraphic Setting of the Clear Lake Area, Lake County, California. Geological Society of America.Rymer MJ, Roth B, Bradbury JP, Forester RM. 1988. Depositional Environments of the Cache, Lower Lake, and Kelseyville Formations, Lake County, California. Geological Society of America.Sims JD. 1988. Late Quaternary Climate, Tectonism, and Sedimentation in Clear Lake, Northern California Coast Ranges. Geological Society of America.Soil Mechanics and Foundation Engineers Inc. (SMFE). March 1967. Big Valley Ground- Water Recharge Investigation for Lake County Flood Control and Water Conservation District.BibliographyBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1964. Quality of Ground Water in California 1961-62, Part 1: Northern and Central California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 66-62.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.California Department of Water Resources. 1998. California Water Plan Update. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 160-98, Volumes 1 and 2.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Jennings CW, Strand RG. 1969. Geologic Atlas of California [Ukiah Sheet]. California Division of Mines and Geology.McNitt JR. 1968. Geology of the Kelseyville Quadrangle, Sonoma, Lake and Mendocino Counties. California Divisions of Mines and Geology. Map Sheet 9.McNitt JR. 1968. Geology of the Lakeport Quadrangle, Lake County, California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Map Sheet 10.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.United States Bureau of Reclamation Mid Pacific Region. 1976. Four Counties Study, Appraisal Ground-water Geology and Resources Appendix for Yolo, Lake, and Napa Counties. United States Bureau of Reclamation Mid Pacific Region.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04