Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Burns Valley Groundwater BasinBurns Valley Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-17• County: Lake• Surface Area: 2,900 acres (4 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyBurns Valley Basin is located along the southeastern edge of Clear Lake and consists of low-lying alluvial plains and upland terrace deposits. The basin is bounded by basalt flows to the northwest and the Plio-Pleistocene Cache Formation on all other sides with the exception of Olivine basalt to the southeast. The west side of the basin opens to Clear Lake. The Cache Formation underlies the majority of the basin. Assuming that there is hydraulic continuity between the alluvium and the Cache Formation, groundwater is in hydraulic continuity in all directions beyond the alluvial plain with the exception being to the northwest. The Jurassic-Cretaceous Franciscan Formation and volcanics constitute the basement rock (USBR 1976). Almost all of the groundwater of Burns Valley is derived from rain that falls within a 12.5 square mile drainage area (Upson 1955). Annual precipitation in the basin is approximately 27 inches.Hydrogeologic InformationWater-Bearing FormationsQuaternary alluvium and upland terrace deposits and the Plio-Pleistocene Cache Formation are the primary water-bearing deposits in the valley.Quaternary Alluvium. Lowlands in the valley are composed of stream channel gravel and adjacent floodplain deposits of several unnamed creeks. The Quaternary alluvium of the lowland deposits is composed of silt, sand, and gravel. Its maximum thickness at the lower end of the valley is approximately 50 feet (USBR 1976). Groundwater is essentially unconfined and yields water for domestic use (DWR 1976).Quaternary Terrace Deposits. On either side of the alluvial plain are remnants of a least two levels of terrace deposits (Upson 1955). The deposits are approximately 15 feet above the valley floor and slope up the valley and merge with the Cache terrain. The deposits consist almost entirely of clastic debris from the Cache formation (DOM 1953).Plio-Pleistocene Cache Formation. Plio-Pleistocene Cache formation deposits underlie all alluvial and terrace deposits. The formation is largely made up of lake deposits with the potential for included stream deposits (DWR 1957). The formation consists of fine sands, silts, and thin interbeds of marl and limestone to a thickness of 200 feet. Near the top of the formation, water-laid tuffs and tuffaceous sands become dominant with intercalated clay, marl, limestone, and diatomite (DOM 1953). The formation has low permeability and yields water to wells at rates up to a few hundred gallons per minute (Upson 1955).California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Burns Valley Groundwater BasinGroundwater Level TrendsAnalysis incomplete.Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. Storage capacity is estimated to be 4,000 acre-feet based on an area of 1,000 acres, a saturated thickness of 50 feet, and a specific yield of 8 percent (Upson 1955). DWR (1960) estimates the useable storage capacity to be 1,400 acre-feet.Groundwater Budget (Type B)Estimates of groundwater extraction for the Burns Valley Basin are based on a survey conducted by the California Department of Water Resources in1995. The survey included land use and sources of water. Estimates of groundwater extraction for agricultural use is 900 acre-feet. Deep percolation from applied water is estimated to be 210 acre-feet.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. Groundwater in the basin consists of magnesium-calcium type waters. Total dissolved solids concentrations range from 280- to 455- mg/L, averaging 335 mg/L (DWR unpublished data).Impairments. Groundwater in the basin has high sodium and iron concentrations. Locally high manganese, magnesium, calcium, and phosphorus also occurs. High boron concentrations may be an issue for agricultural applications.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Well CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/Irrigation30 (1 Well Completion Report)Total depths (ft)Range: 30 – 335 Range: 68 – 175￼Active Monitoring DataAverage: 108 (65 Well Completion Reports)Average: 134 (3 Well Completion Reports)Number of wells /measurement frequency1 well measured semi-annually5 wells biennially 0￼AgencyLake County DWRDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water qualityTitle 22 water quality￼Last update 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Burns Valley Groundwater BasinBasin ManagementGroundwater management: County of Lake Water agenciesPublic NonePrivate Highland Mutual Water CompanySelected ReferencesCalifornia Department of Water Resources (DWR). July 1957. Lake County Investigation. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 14.California Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1960. Northeastern Counties Investigation. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 58.California Department of Water Resources (DWR). September 1976. Southwestern Sacramento Valley Ground Water Investigation. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. Draft Memorandum Report.California Division of Mines (DOM). 1953. Geology of Lower Lake Quadrangle, California. Bulletin 166.Hearn BC, Donnelly JM, Goff FE. 1975. Geology and Geochronology of the Clear Lake Volcanics, California. USGS. 75-296.Hearn BC, Jr., McLaughlin RJ, Donnelly-Nolan JM. 1988. Tectonic Framework of the Clear Lake Basin, California. Geological Society of America.McLaughlin RJ, Ohlin HN, Blome CD. 1983. Tectonostratigraphic Framework of the Franciscan Assemblage and Lower Part of the Great Valley Sequence in the Geysers- Clear Lake Region, California. American Geophysical Union, Eos, Transactions.Ott Water Engineers Inc. 1987. Lake County Resource Management Plan Update. Lake County Flood Control and Water Conservation District.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.Rymer MJ. 1978. Stratigraphy of the Cache Formation (Pliocene-Pleistocene) in Clear Lake basin, Lake County, California. USGS.Rymer MJ. 1981. Stratigraphic Revision of the Cache Formation (Pliocene and Pliestocene), Lake County, California. USGS.Rymer MJ. 1983. Late Cenozoic Stratigraphic Setting of the Clear Lake Area, Lake County, California. Geological Society of America.Rymer MJ, Roth B, Bradbury JP, Forester RM. 1988. Depositional Environments of the Cache, Lower Lake, and Kelseyville Formations, Lake County, California. Geological Society of America.Sims JD. 1988. Late Quaternary Climate, Tectonism, and Sedimentation in Clear Lake, Northern California Coast Ranges. Geological Society of America.Upson JE. and others. 1955. Ground Water of Lower Lake-Middletown Area, Lake County, California, USGS. Water Supply Paper 1297.United States Department of Interior, Bureau of Reclamation, Mid Pacific Region (USBR). Four counties Study, appraisal Ground-Water Geology and Resources Appendix For Yolo, Lake, And Napa Counties. United States Department of Interior, Bureau of Reclamation, Mid Pacific Region. August 1976.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼￼￼Last update 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Burns Valley Groundwater BasinBibliographyBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1976. Southwestern Sacramento Valley Ground Water Investigation. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. Memorandum Report.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.California Department of Water Resources. 1998. California Water Plan Update. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 160-98,Volumes 1 and 2.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Jennings CW, Strand RG. 1969. Geologic Atlas of California [Ukiah Sheet]. California Division of Mines and Geology.McNitt JR. 1968. Geology of the Kelseyville Quadrangle, Sonoma, Lake and Mendocino Counties. California Divisions of Mines and Geology. Map Sheet 9.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04