Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinSacramento Valley Groundwater Basin, East Butte Subbasin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-21.59• County: Butte, Sutter• Surface Area: 265,390 acres (415 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe East Butte Subbasin is the portion of the Sacramento Valley Groundwater Basin bounded on the west and northwest by Butte Creek, on the northeast by the Cascade Ranges, on the southeast by the Feather River and the south by the Sutter Buttes. The northeast boundary along the Cascade Ranges is primarily a geographic boundary with some groundwater recharge occurring beyond that boundary. The subbasin is contiguous with the West Butte Subbasin at depth. Annual precipitation is approximately 18 inches in the valley increasing to 27 inches towards the eastern foothills.Hydrogeologic InformationWater-Bearing FormationsThe East Butte aquifer system is comprised of deposits of late Tertiary to Quaternary age. The Quaternary deposits include Holocene stream channel deposits and basin deposits, Pleistocene deposits of the Modesto and Riverbank formations, and Sutter Buttes alluvium. The Tertiary deposits include the Tuscan and Laguna formations.Holocene Stream Channel Deposits. These deposits consist of unconsolidated gravel, sand, silt and clay derived from the erosion, reworking, and deposition of adjacent Quaternary stream terrace alluvial deposits. The thickness varies from 1- to 80-feet (Helley and Harwood 1985). These deposits represent the upper part of the unconfined zone of the aquifer and are moderately-to-highly permeable; however, the thickness and areal extent of the deposits limit the water-bearing capability.Holocene Basin Deposits. These deposits are the result of sediment-laden floodwaters that rose above the natural levees of streams and rivers to spread across low-lying areas. They consist primarily of silts and clays and may be locally interbedded with stream channel deposits. These deposits result from deposition from erosion from portions of the Cascade Ranges to the Sutter Buttes. Thickness of the deposits range to 150 feet (DWR 2000). These deposits have low permeability and generally yield low quantities of water to wells. The quality of groundwater produced from the basin deposits is often poor (USBR 1960).Pleistocene Modesto Formation. The Modesto Formation in this subbasin consists of poorly indurated gravel and cobbles with sand, silt, and clay derived from reworking and deposition of the Tuscan Formation, Laguna Formation, and the Riverbank Formation. Surface exposure of the formation is west of the Feather River extending from south of the Thermalito Afterbay to the southern subbasin boundary. The formation may extend across the entire subbasin, underlying basin deposits, with thicknesses ranging from 50- to 150-feet (DWR 2000).California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinPleistocene Riverbank Formation. These older terrace deposits consist of poorly-to-highly permeable pebble and small cobble gravels interlensed with reddish clay sands and silt. Surface exposure of the Riverbank Formation is primarily south and west of the Thermalito Afterbay. The formation may extend across the entire subbasin, underlying basin and Modesto deposits, with thicknesses ranging from 50- to 200-feet (Helley and Harwood 1985).Pleistocene Sutter Butte Alluvium. In the southern portion of the subbasin, alluvium of the Sutter Buttes is observed in the subsurface and may range in thickness up to 600 feet (DWR 2000). The fan deposits forming the apron around the buttes consist largely of gravel, sand, silt and clay and may extend up to 15 miles north of the Sutter Buttes and westerly beyond the Sacramento River. Utility pump test records show the average well yield for that formation to be approximately 2300 gallons per minute with an average specific capacity of 64.Pliocene Tuscan Formation. The Tuscan Formation is composed of a series of volcanic mudflows, tuff breccia, tuffaceous sandstone and volcanic ash layers. Thickness of the formation is estimated to be 800 feet (DWR 2000). The formation is described as four separate but lithologically similar units, A through D (with Unit A being the oldest), which in some areas are separated by layers of thin tuff or ash units (Helley and Harwood 1985). Units A, B, and C are found within the subsurface in the northern part of the subbasin and Units A and B are found in the southern part of the subbasin. Surface exposures of Units B and C are located in the foothills at the far eastern extents of the subbasin.Unit A is the oldest water bearing unit of the formation and is characterized by the presence of metamorphic clasts within interbedded lahars, volcanic conglomerate, volcanic sandstone and siltstone.Unit B is composed of fairly equal distribution of lahars, tuffaceous sandstone, and conglomerate. Unit C consists of massive mudflow or lahar deposits with some interbedded volcanic conglomerate and sandstone. In the subsurface, these low permeability lahars form thick, confining layers for groundwater contained in the more permeable sediments if Unit B.Pliocene Laguna Formation. The Laguna Formation consists of interbedded alluvial sand, gravel, and silt deposits which are moderately consolidated and poorly-to-well cemented. The Laguna is compacted and generally has a low-to-moderate permeability, except in scattered gravels in the upper portion. The formation yields moderate quantities of water to wells along the eastern margin of the valley. Wells of higher capacity generally tap underlying Tuscan deposits.Surface exposures of the Laguna appear along the eastern margin of the subbasin in the vicinity of the Thermalito Afterbay and extend westerly in the subsurface. The lateral extent of the formation is unknown. The thickness of the formation is difficult to determine because the base of the unit is rarely exposed. Estimates of maximum thickness range from 180 feet (Helley and Harwood 1985) to 1,000 feet (Olmsted and Davis 1961). Geologic cross sections developed by California Department of WaterCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinResources estimate the thickness to be approximately 500 feet (DWR 2000). Wells completed in the formation yield only moderate quantities of water.Groundwater Level TrendsAs part of a groundwater inventory analysis prepared for Butte County, the portion of the East Butte Subbasin located within Butte County was evaluated for seasonal and long-term changes in groundwater levels for confined and composite portions of the aquifer systems (DWR 2001).For wells constructed in confined and composite portions of the aquifer, the increased use of groundwater in the northern portion of the subbasin has resulted in wide seasonal fluctuations in groundwater levels. In the northern portion of the subbasin, composite well fluctuations (composite wells are monitoring wells that represent groundwater levels that combine confined and unconfined portions of the aquifer system) average about 15 feet during normal years and 30- to 40- feet during drought years. Annual groundwater fluctuations in the confined and semi-confined aquifer system ranges from 15- to 30- feet during normal years.In the portion of the subbasin located within the southern part of Butte County, groundwater level fluctuations for composite wells average about 4 feet during normal years and up to 10 feet during drought years. The groundwater fluctuations for wells constructed in the confined and semi- confined aquifer system average 4 feet during normal years and up to 5 feet during drought years.Recharge AreasLocalized fluctuations in groundwater levels are observed just south of the Thermalito Afterbay due to the recharging of groundwater from this surface water system (DWR 2001).Groundwater StorageThe storage capacity of the subbasin was estimated based on estimates of specific yield for the Sacramento Valley as developed in DWR (1978). Estimates of specific yield, determined on a regional basis, were used to obtain a weighted specific yield conforming to the subbasin boundary. The estimated specific yield for the East Butte Subbasin is 5.9 percent. The estimated storage capacity to a depth of 200 feet is approximately 3,128,959 acre-feet.Groundwater Budget (Type B)Estimates of groundwater extraction are based on surveys conducted by the California Department of Water Resources during 1993 and 1997. Surveys included landuse and sources of water. Estimates of groundwater extraction for agricultural; municipal and industrial; and environmental wetland uses are 104,000, 75,500 and 1,300 acre-feet respectively. Deep percolation of applied water is estimated to be 126,000 acre-feet.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. Calcium-magnesium bicarbonate and magnesium-calcium bicarbonate waters are the predominant groundwater water types in theCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater Basinsubbasin. Magnesium bicarbonate waters occur locally near Biggs-Gridley, south and east to the Feather River. Total dissolved solids range from 122- to 570-mg/L, averaging 235 mg/L (DWR unpublished data).Impairments. Localized high concentrations of manganese, iron, magnesium, total dissolved solids, conductivity, ASAR, and calcium occur within the subbasin.Water Quality in Public Supply WellsCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Constituent Group1Inorganics – Primary RadiologicalNitratesPesticidesVOCs and SVOCs Inorganics – SecondaryNumber of wells sampled2 3025 32 16 19 30Number of wells with a concentration above an MCL3 10 2 0 0 3￼￼1 A description of each member in the constituent groups anddiscussion of the relevance of these groups are included in California’s Groundwater – Bulletin 118 by DWR (2003).2 Represents distinct number of wells sampled as required under DHS Title 22 program from 1994 through 2000.3 Each well reported with a concentration above an MCL was confirmed with a second detection above an MCL. This information is intended as an indicator of the types of activities that cause contamination in a given basin. It represents the water quality at the sample location. It does not indicate the water quality delivered to the consumer. More detailed drinking water quality information can be obtained from the local water purveyor and its annual Consumer Confidence Report.Well Production characteristics Well yields (gal/min)Irrigation Range: 0 – 4500 Average: 1839 (37 Well CompletionReports)Utility pump test records for the East Butte Subbasin show well yields rangingfrom a low of 65 gpm to a high of 5,459 gpm with an average yield of 1,602 gpm (DWR 2001).a generalized￼Domestic IrrigationTotal depths (ft)Range: 25 – 639 Range: 35 – 983￼Active Monitoring DataAverage: 101 (1477 Well Completion Reports)Average: 285 (699 Well Completion Reports)Number of wells /measurement frequency 43 wells semi-annually4 wells biennially 44￼AgencyDWR DWRDepartment of Health ServicesParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water quality Miscellaneous water quality￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinBasin ManagementGroundwater management: Butte County adopted a groundwater management ordinance in 1996.Water agenciesPublic Butte Basin Water Users Association, Biggs- West Gridley WD, Butte WD, Durham ID, Cityof Biggs, City of Gridley, Oroville-Wyandotte ID, Richvale ID, Thermalito ID, and Western Canal WD.Private North Burbank Public Utility District.Selected ReferencesCalifornia Department of Water Resources. 1978. Evaluation of Groundwater Resources: Sacramento Valley. Department of Water Resources in cooperation with the United States Geological Survey. Appendix A. Bulletin 118-6.California Department of Water Resources. 2001. Butte County Groundwater Inventory Analysis. Draft Report. Northern District.California Department of Water Resources. 2000. Geology and Hydrogeology of the Freshwater Bearing Aquifer Systems of the Northern Sacramento Valley, California. In Progress.Helley EJ, Harwood DS. 1985. Geologic Map of the Late Cenozoic Deposits of the Sacramento Valley and Northern Sierran Foothills, California. Map MF-1790.Olmsted FH, Davis GH. 1961. Geologic Features and Ground Water Storage Capacity of the Sacramento Valley, California. USGS. Water Supply Paper 1497.United States Bureau of Reclamation (USBR), 1960. Tehama-Colusa Service Area Geology and Groundwater Resources Appendix.BibliographyBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.Berkstressor CF. 1973. Base of Fresh Water in the Sacramento Valley and Sacramento-San Joaquin Delta, California. U.S. Geological Survey in Cooperation with California Department of Water Resources.Bertoldi GT, Johnson RH, Evenson KD. 1991. Groundwater in the Central Valley, California - - A Summary Report. Regional Aquifer System Analysis--Central Valley, California. USGS. Professional Paper 1401-A.Beyer LA. 1993. Sacramento Basin Province. USGS.Bryan K. 1923. Geology and Ground-water Resources of Sacramento Valley, California. USGS. 495.Busacca AJ, Singer MJ, Verosub KL. 1989. Late Cenozoic Stratigraphy of the Feather and Yuba Rivers Area, California, with a Section on Soil Development in Mixed Alluvium at Honcut Creek. USGS.California Department of Pesticide Regulation. 1993. Sampling for Pesticide Residues in California Well Water, 1993 Well Inventory Database. California Environmental Protection Agency.California Department of Water Resources. 1958. Ground Water Conditions in Central and Northern California 1957-58. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 77-58.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼￼￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinCalifornia Department of Water Resources. 1960. Northeastern Counties Investigation. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 58.California Department of Water Resources. 1964. Groundwater Conditions in Central and Northern California, 1961-62. California Department of Water Resources.California Department of Water Resources. 1964. Quality of Ground Water in California 1961-62, Part 1: Northern and Central California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 66-62.California Department of Water Resources. 1966. Precipitation in the Central Valley. Coordinated Statewide Planning Program. California Department of Water Resources, Sacramento District. Office Report.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. Progress Report Sacramento And Redding Basins Groundwater Study. California Department of Water Resources, Northern and Central Districts, in cooperation with the U.S. Geological Survey. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1976. Progress Report in Ground Water Development Studies, North Sacramento Valley. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. Memorandum Report.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.California Department of Water Resources. 1987. Progress Report Sacramento and Redding Basins Ground Water Study. California Department of Water Resources, Northern and Central Districts, in cooperation with the U.S. Geological Survey.California Department of Water Resources. 1993. Sacramento Valley Basin Groundwater Levels -- Butte County. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. District Report.California Department of Water Resources. 1994. Butte and Sutter Basins Water Data Atlas. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. District Report.California Department of Water Resources. 1995. Sacramento Valley Groundwater Quality Investigation. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District.California Department of Water Resources. 1998. California Water Plan Update. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 160-98, Volumes 1 and 2.California Deptartment of Public Works. 1950. Views and Recommendations of State of California on Proposed Report of Chief of Engineers, U.S. Army, on Butte Creek and Cherokee Canal, California. Sacramento: California. Deptartment of Public Works.California Division of Water Resources. 1940. Butte Creek Adjudication. Butte Creek and Tributaries Above Western Dam, Butte County, California. Sacramento.California Division of Water Resources. 1942. Butte Creek Adjudication. Sacramento: 74 p.California Reclamation Board. 1986. Butte Basin Overflow Area Plan of Flood Control: Draft; Project Proposal and Environmental Impact Report. Sacramento: Department of Water Resources Reclamation Board.Cherven VB, Edmondson WF. 1992. Structural Geology of the Sacramento Basin: Annual Meeting, Pacific Section AAPG, Sacramento, California, April 27, 1992 - May 2,1992.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America: Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Fogelman RP. 1976. Descriptions and Chemical Analysis for Selected Wells in the Central Sacramento Valley, California. USGS. OF-76-472.Fogelman RP. 1978. Chemical Quality of Ground Water in the Central Sacramento Valley, California. USGS. Water Resources Investigations 77-133.Fogelman RP. 1982. Dissolved-solids Concentrations of Groundwater in the Sacramento Valley, California. USGS. HA-645.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinFogelman RP. 1983. Ground Water Quality in the Sacramento Valley, California, Water Types and Potential Nitrate and Boron Problem Areas. USGS. HA-651.Fogelman RP, Rockwell GL. 1977. Descriptions and Chemical Analysis for Selected Wells in the Eastern Sacramento Valley, California. USGS. OF-77-486.Fogleman RP. 1979. Chemical Quality of Ground Water in the Eastern Sacramento Valley, California. USGS.Harwood DS, Helley EJ. 1982. Preliminary Structure Contour Map of the Sacramento Valley, California, Showing Major Late Cenozoic Structural Features and Depth to Basement. USGS.Harwood DS, Helley EJ. 1987. Late Cenozoic Tectonism of the Sacramento Valley. USGS.Harwood DS, Helley EJ, Doukas MP. 1981. Geologic Map of the Chico Monocline and Northeastern Part of the Sacramento Valley, California. USGS.Harwood DS, Murchey BL. 1990. Biostratigraphic, Tectonic, and Paleogeographic Ties Between Upper Paleozoic Volcanic and Basinal Rocks in the Northern Sierra Terrane, California. Geological Society of America Special Paper.Hawkins FF, Anderson L. 1985. Late Quaternary Tectonics of Part of the Northern Sierra Nevada, California. Geological Society of America.Hill KA, Webber JD. 1999. Butte Creek Spring-run Chinook Salmon, Oncorhynchus Tshawytscha, Juvenile Outmigration and Life History, 1995-1998. Sacramento: State of California Resources Agency Department. of Fish and Game. 46 p.Hull LC. 1984. Geochemistry of Groundwater in the Sacramento Valley, California. Central Valley of California RASA Project. USGS. Professional Paper 1401-B.Lydon PA. 1969. Geology and Lahars of the Tuscan Formation, Northern California. The Geological Society of America.Mankinen EA. 1978. Paleomagnetic Evidence for a Late Cretaceous Deformation of the Great Valley Sequence, Sacramento Valley, California. USGS.Mitten HT. 1972. Estimated Ground-water Pumpage in the Northern Part of the Sacramento Valley, California,1966-69. USGS.Mitten HT. 1973. Estimated Ground-water Pumpage in the Northern Part of the Sacramento Valley, California, 1970-71. USGS.Page RW. 1974. Base and Thickness of the Post-Eocene Continental Deposits in the Sacramento Valley, California. U.S. Geological Survey in cooperation with California Department of Water Resources. Water Resources Investigations 45-73.Page RW. 1986. Geology of the Fresh Groundwater Basin of the Central Valley, California, with Texture Maps and Sections. Regional Aquifer System Analysis. USGS. Professional Paper 1401-C.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.Poland JF, Evenson RE. 1966. Hydrogeology and Land Subsidence, Great Central Valley, California, Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. 239-247 p.Russell RD. 1931. The Tehama Formation of Northern California [Ph.D]: University of California.Saucedo GJ, Wagner DL. 1992. Geologic Map of the Chico Quadrangle, California. California Division of Mines and Geology.United States Army Corps of Engineers Sacramento District. 1957. Little Chico - Butte Creeks General Design. Sacramento, Calif.: United States Army Corps of Engineers Sacramento District.U.S.Geological Survey. 1981. Water Resources Data for California; Volume 4, Northern Central Valley Basins and the Great Basin from Honey Lake Basin to Oregon State Line. USGS.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinWilliamson AK, Prudic DE, Swain LA. 1985. Groundwater Flow in the Central Valley, California. USGS. OF-85-345.Williamson AK, Prudic DE, Swain LA. 1989. Groundwater Flow in the Central Valley, California. Regional Aquifer-System Analysis--Central Valley, California. USGS. Professional Paper 1401-D.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04