Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinSacramento Valley Groundwater Basin, West Butte Subbasin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-21.58• County: Butte, Glenn, Colusa• Surface Area: 181,560 acres (284 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe portion of the Sacramento Valley Groundwater Basin bounded on the west and south by the Sacramento River, on the north by Big Chico Creek, on the northeast by the Chico Monocline, and on the east by Butte Creek comprises the West Butte Subbasin. Big Chico and Butte Creeks serve as subbasin boundaries in the near surface. The subbasin is hydrologically contiguous with the Vina and East Butte Subbasins at depth. The Chico Monocline forms a geographic boundary; however, a component of recharge to the subbasin appears east of the fault structure. Groundwater flow is southwesterly toward the Sacramento River north of the city of Princeton. South of Princeton, groundwater flows away from the Sacramento River to recharge the groundwater system. Annual precipitation within subbasin is approximately 18 inches in the valley increasing to 27 inches towards the foothills.Hydrogeologic InformationWater-Bearing FormationsThe West Butte aquifer system is comprised of deposits of Late Tertiary to Quaternary age. The Quaternary deposits include the Holocene stream channel deposits and basin deposits, and the Pleistocene Modesto Formation, Riverbank Formation, and Sutter Buttes alluvium. The Tertiary deposits consist of the Pliocene Tehama Formation and the Tuscan Formation.Holocene Stream Channel Deposits. These deposits consist of unconsolidated gravel, sand, silt and clay derived from the erosion, reworking, and deposition of adjacent Quaternary stream terrace alluvial deposits. The thickness varies from 1- to 80-feet (Helley and Harwood 1985). The unit represents the upper part of the unconfined zone of the aquifer and is moderately-to-highly permeable; however, the thickness and areal extent of the deposits limit the water-bearing capability.Holocene Basin Deposits. Basin deposits are the result of sediment-laden floodwaters that rose above the natural levees of streams and rivers to spread across low-lying areas. They consist primarily of silts and clays and may be locally interbedded with stream channel deposits along the Sacramento River. The deposits extend from south of Big Chico Creek to north of Angel Slough. Thickness of the unit can range from 10- to 100-feet (DWR 2001). The deposits have low permeability and generally yield low quantities of water to wells. The quality of groundwater produced from the unit is often poor (USBR 1960).Pleistocene Modesto Formation. The Modesto Formation (deposited between 14,000 to 42,000 years ago) consists of poorly indurated gravel and cobbles with sand, silt, and clay derived from reworking and deposition ofCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater Basinthe Tuscan and Riverbank formations. Surface exposures extend south from Big Chico Creek to north of the city of Durham and also extend south of Angel Slough to the Sacramento River. The unit varies in thickness from 50- to 150-feet (DWR 2000). In locations where gravel and sand predominate, groundwater yields are moderate.Pleistocene Riverbank Formation. The Riverbank Formation (deposited between 130,000 and 450,000 years ago) consists of poorly-to-highly permeable pebble and small cobble gravels interlensed with reddish clay sands and silt. The areal extent of the formation is limited more to the southern portion of the subbasin and underlies surface exposures of the Modesto Formation. The thickness of the formation is approximately 1- to 200-feet depending on location (DWR 2000). The formation is moderately to highly permeable and yields moderate quantities of water to domestic and shallow irrigation wells.Pleistocene Sutter Buttes Alluvium. In the southern extents of the subbasin, Sutter Buttes alluvium is observed in the subsurface and may range in thickness up to 600 feet (DWR 2000). These alluvial fan deposits consist largely of gravel, sand, silt and clay and may extend up to 15 miles north of the Sutter Buttes and westerly beyond the Sacramento River. Utility pump test records for wells located east of the subbasin, but believed to be in the same formation, show the average well yield for the formation to be approximately 2300 gallons per minute with an average specific capacity of 64 gpm/ft.Pliocene Tehama Formation. The Tehama Formation consists of sediments originating from the coastal mountains and interfingers with sediments of the Tuscan Formation in the vicinity of the Sacramento River at the far western extent of the subbasin (DWR 2000).Pliocene Tuscan Formation. The Tuscan Formation is composed of a series of volcanic mudflows, tuff breccia, tuffaceous sandstone and volcanic ash layers. Thickness of the formation is estimated to be 800 feet (DWR 2000). The formation is described as four separate but lithologically similar units, A through D (with Unit A being the oldest), which in some areas are separated by layers of thin tuff or ash units (Helley and Harwood 1985). Units A, B, and C are found within the subsurface in the northern part of the subbasin and Units A and B are found in the southern part of the subbasin. Surface exposures of Units A, B, and C are located in the foothills at the far- eastern extents of the subbasin. The surface exposure of Unit B east of the subbasin boundary is a recharge area.Unit A is the oldest water bearing unit of the formation and is characterized by the presence of metamorphic clasts within interbedded lahars, volcanic conglomerate, volcanic sandstone and siltstone. Unit B is composed of a fairly equal distribution of lahars, tuffaceous sandstone, and conglomerate. Unit B is volcaniclastic and is the most transmissive portion of the volcanic aquifer system and is the primary aquifer at depth. The surface exposure of Unit B, east of the subbasin boundary, is a recharge area. Although the Tuscan Formation is unconfined where it is exposed near the valley margin, at depth, the formation is confined. Unit C consists of massive mudflow orCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater Basinlahar deposits with some interbedded volcanic conglomerate and sandstone. In the subsurface, these low permeability lahars form thick, confining layers for groundwater contained in the more permeable underlying sediments of Unit B.Groundwater Level TrendsReview of the hydrographs for long-term comparison of spring-to-spring groundwater levels indicates a decline in groundwater levels associated with the 1976-77 and 1987-94 droughts, followed by a recovery in groundwater levels to pre-drought conditions of the early-1970s and 1980s. Comparison of spring-to-spring groundwater levels from the 1950’s and 1960’s, versus today’s levels, indicate about a 10-foot decline in groundwater levels in portions of the West Butte Subbasin (DWR 2001).Areas unaffected by municipal water use reflect the natural groundwater table distribution and direction of movement. Year-round extraction of groundwater for municipal use in the Chico area causes several small groundwater depressions that tend to alter the natural southwesterly movement of groundwater in the area (DWR 2001). In the Chico area, groundwater levels in the unconfined portion of the aquifer system is about 5- to 7-feet during normal precipitation and up to approximately 16 feet during periods of drought. Annual fluctuation in the confined or semi- confined portion of the aquifer system is approximately 15- to 25-feet during normal years and up to approximately 30 feet during periods of drought. Long-term comparison of spring to spring groundwater levels indicates a 10 to 15-foot decline in levels since the 1950’s.Groundwater StorageThe storage capacity of the subbasin was estimated based on estimates of specific yield for the Sacramento Valley as developed in DWR (1978). Estimates of specific yield, determined on a regional basis, were used to obtain a weighted specific yield conforming to the subbasin boundary. The estimated specific yield for the West Butte Subbasin is 7.7 percent. The estimated storage capacity to a depth of 200 feet is approximately 2,794,330 acre-feet.Groundwater Budget (Type B )Estimates of groundwater extraction for the West Butte Subbasin are based on surveys conducted by the California Department of Water Resources during 1993 and 1997. Surveys included landuse and sources of water. Estimates of groundwater extraction for agricultural; municipal/industrial; and environmental wetland uses are 161,000, 10,000 and 4,600 acre-feet respectively. Deep percolation of applied water is estimated to be 64,000 acre-feet (DWR 2001).Groundwater QualityCharacterization. Calcium-magnesium bicarbonate and magnesium-calcium bicarbonate are the predominant groundwater types found in the subbasin. Sodium bicarbonate type waters occur at the southern tip of the subbasin west of Sutter Buttes. Concentrations of total dissolved solids (TDS) range from 130- to 676-mg/L, averaging 293 mg/L (DWR unpublished data).California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinImpairments. Some high nitrates are found in the Chico area. Localized high calcium, conductivity, boron, TDS, and adjusted sodium absorption ratio occur within the subbasin.Water Quality in Public Supply WellsCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Constituent Group1Inorganics – Primary RadiologicalNitratesPesticidesVOCs and SVOCs Inorganics – SecondaryNumber of wells sampled2 2925 30 26 26 29Number of wells with a concentration above an MCL3 00 0 0 1 2￼￼1 A description of each member in the constituent groups anddiscussion of the relevance of these groups are included in California’s Groundwater – Bulletin 118 by DWR (2003).2 Represents distinct number of wells sampled as required under DHS Title 22 program from 1994 through 2000.3 Each well reported with a concentration above an MCL was confirmed with a second detection above an MCL. This information is intended as an indicator of the types of activities that cause contamination in a given basin. It represents the water quality at the sample location. It does not indicate the water quality delivered to the consumer. More detailed drinking water quality information can be obtained from the local water purveyor and its annual Consumer Confidence Report.Well Production characteristics Well yields (gal/min)a generalized￼IrrigationDomestic IrrigationAverage: 1833 (46 Well Completion Reports)Average: 136 (1469 Well Completion Reports)Average: 321 (1038 Well Completion Reports)Number of wells /measurement frequency 32 wells semi-annually8 wells biennially 36Active Monitoring DataRange: 7 – 4000Total depths (ft)Range: 15 – 680 Range: 40 - 920￼￼AgencyDWR DWRDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water quality Miscellaneous water quality￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinBasin ManagementGroundwater management: Butte County adopted a groundwater management ordinance in 1996.Glenn County adopted a groundwater management ordinance in 2000. Colusa County adopted a groundwater management ordinance in 1998.Water agenciesPublic Butte Basin Water Users Association, Buzztail Communtiy Service District, Durham ID, City ofChico, RD 1004,Western Canal WD, M&T Chico Ranch Inc., Sartain MWCPrivate Dayton Mutual Water Company, Del Oro Water Company, Durham Mutual Water Company andCalifornia Water ServiceSelected ReferencesCalifornia Department of Water Resources. 1978. Evaluation of Groundwater Resources: Sacramento Valley. Department of Water Resources in cooperation with the United States Geological Survey. Appendix A. Bulletin 118-6.California Department of Water Resources. 2001. Butte County Groundwater Inventory Analysis. Draft Report. Northern District.California Department of Water Resources. 2000. Geology and Hydrogeology of the Freshwater Bearing Aquifer Systems of the Northern Sacramento Valley, California. In Progress.Helley EJ, Harwood DS. 1985. Geologic Map of the Late Cenozoic Deposits of the Sacramento Valley and Northern Sierran Foothills, California. Map MF-1790.United States Bureau of Reclamation (USBR), 1960. Tehama-Colusa Service Area Geology and Groundwater Resources Appendix.Northern DistrictBibliographyBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.Berkstressor CF. 1973. Base of Fresh Water in the Sacramento Valley and Sacramento-San Joaquin Delta, California. U.S. Geological Survey in Cooperation with California Department of Water Resources.Bertoldi GT, Johnson RH, Evenson KD. 1991. Groundwater in the Central Valley, California - - A Summary Report. Regional Aquifer System Analysis--Central Valley, California. USGS. Professional Paper 1401-A.Beyer LA. 1993. Sacramento Basin Province. USGS.Bryan K. 1923. Geology and Ground-water Resources of Sacramento Valley, California. USGS. 495.California Department of Pesticide Regulation. 1993. Sampling for Pesticide Residues in California Well Water, 1993 Well Inventory Database. California Environmental Protection Agency.California Department of Water Resources. Groundwater Levels in the Sacramento Valley Groundwater Basin, Glenn County.California Department of Water Resources. 1958. Ground Water Conditions in Central and Northern California 1957-58. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 77-58.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼￼￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinCalifornia Department of Water Resources. 1960. Northeastern Counties Investigation. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 58.California Department of Water Resources. 1964. Groundwater Conditions in Central and Northern California, 1961-62. California Department of Water Resources.California Department of Water Resources. 1964. Quality of Ground Water in California 1961-62, Part 1: Northern and Central California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 66-62.California Department of Water Resources. 1966. Precipitation in the Central Valley. Coordinated Statewide Planning Program. California Department of Water Resources, Sacramento District. Office Report.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. Progress Report Sacramento And Redding Basins Groundwater Study. California Department of Water Resources, Northern and Central Districts, in cooperation with the U.S. Geological Survey. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1976. Progress Report in Ground Water Development Studies, North Sacramento Valley. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. Memorandum Report.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.California Department of Water Resources. 1984. Study of Nitrates in the Ground Water of the Chico Area, Butte County. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. Memorandum Report.California Department of Water Resources. 1987. Progress Report Sacramento and Redding Basins Ground Water Study. California Department of Water Resources, Northern and Central Districts, in cooperation with the U.S. Geological Survey.California Department of Water Resources. 1993. Sacramento Valley Basin Groundwater Levels -- Butte County. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. District Report.California Department of Water Resources. 1994. Butte and Sutter Basins Water Data Atlas. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. District Report.California Department of Water Resources. 1995. Sacramento Valley Groundwater Quality Investigation. California Department of Water Resouces, Northern District.California Department of Water Resources. 1998. California Water Plan Update. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 160-98, Volumes 1 and 2.California Division of Water Resources. 1940. Butte Creek Adjudication. Butte Creek and Tributaries Above Western Dam, Butte County, California. Sacramento.California Division of Water Resources. 1942. Butte Creek Adjudication. Sacramento: 74 p.California Reclamation Board. 1986. Butte Basin Overflow Area Plan of Flood Control : Draft ; Project Proposal and Environmental Impact Report. Sacramento: Department of Water Resources Reclamation Board.Cherven VB, Edmondson WF. 1992. Structural Geology of the Sacramento Basin: Annual Meeting, Pacific Section AAPG, Sacramento, California, April 27, 1992 - May 2,1992.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Fogelman RP. 1976. Descriptions and Chemical Analysis for Selected Wells in the Central Sacramento Valley, California. USGS. OF-76-472.Fogelman RP. 1978. Chemical Quality of Ground Water in the Central Sacramento Valley, California. USGS. Water Resources Investigations 77-133.Fogelman RP. 1982. Dissolved-solids Concentrations of Groundwater in the Sacramento Valley, California. USGS. HA-645.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinFogelman RP. 1983. Ground Water Quality in the Sacramento Valley, California, Water Types and Potential Nitrate and Boron Problem Areas. USGS. HA-651.Fogelman RP, Rockwell GL. 1977. Descriptions and Chemical Analysis for Selected Wells in the Eastern Sacramento Valley, California. USGS. OF-77-486.Fogleman RP. 1979. Chemical Quality of Ground Water in the Eastern Sacramento Valley, California. USGS.French J. 1983. Data for Ground-water Test Hole Near Butte City, Central Valley Aquifer Project, California. USGS. USGS 83-697.Harwood DS, Helley EJ. 1982. Preliminary Structure Contour Map of the Sacramento Valley, California, Showing Major Late Cenozoic Structural Features and Depth to Basement. USGS.Harwood DS, Helley EJ. 1987. Late Cenozoic Tectonism of the Sacramento Valley. USGS.Harwood DS, Helley EJ, Doukas MP. 1981. Geologic Map of the Chico Monocline and Northeastern Part of the Sacramento Valley, California. USGS.Harwood DS, Murchey BL. 1990. Biostratigraphic, Tectonic, and Paleogeographic Ties Between Upper Paleozoic Volcanic and Basinal Rocks in the Northern Sierra Terrane, California. Geological Society of America Special Paper.Hawkins FF, Anderson l. 1985. Late Quaternary Tectonics of Part of the Northern Sierra Nevada, California. Geological Society of America.Hill KA, Webber JD. 1999. Butte Creek Spring-run Chinook Salmon, Oncorhynchus Tshawytscha, Juvenile Outmigration and Life History, 1995-1998. Sacramento: State of California Resources Agency Dept. of Fish and Game. 46 p.Hull LC. 1984. Geochemistry of Groundwater in the Sacramento Valley, California. Central Valley of California RASA Project. USGS. Professional Paper 1401-B.Jennings CW, Strand RG. 1969. Geologic Atlas of California [Ukiah Sheet]. California Division of Mines and Geology.Lydon PA. 1969. Geology and Lahars of the Tuscan Formation, Northern California. The Geological Society of America.Mankinen EA. 1978. Paleomagnetic Evidence for a Late Cretaceous Deformation of the Great Valley Sequence, Sacramento Valley, California. USGS.Mitten HT. 1972. Estimated Ground-water Pumpage in the Northern Part of the Sacramento Valley, California,1966-69. USGS.Mitten HT. 1973. Estimated Ground-water Pumpage in the Northern Part of the Sacramento Valley, California, 1970-71. USGS.Olmsted FH, Davis GH. 1961. Geologic Features and Ground Water Storage Capacity of the Sacramento Valley, California. USGS. Water Supply Paper 1497.Page RW. 1974. Base and Thickness of the Post-Eocene Continental Deposits in the Sacramento Valley, California. U.S. Geological Survey in cooperation with California Department of Water Resources. Water Resources Investigations 45-73.Page RW. 1986. Geology of the Fresh Groundwater Basin of the Central Valley, California, with Texture Maps and Sections. Regional Aquifer System Analysis. USGS. Professional Paper 1401-C.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.Poland JF, Evenson RE. 1966. Hydrogeology and Land Subsidence, Great Central Valley, California, Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. 239-247 p.Russell RD. 1931. The Tehama Formation of Northern California [Ph.D]: University of California.Saucedo GJ, Wagner DL. 1992. Geologic Map of the Chico Quadrangle, California. California Division of Mines and Geology.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinUnited States Army Corps of Engineers Sacramento District. 1957. Little Chico - Butte Creeks General Design. Sacramento, Calif.: United States Army Corps of Engineers Sacramento District.U.S.Geological Survey. 1981. Water Resources Data for California; Volume 4, Northern Central Valley Basins and the Great Basin from Honey Lake Basin to Oregon State Line. USGS.Williamson AK, Prudic DE, Swain LA. 1985. Groundwater Flow in the Central Valley, California. USGS. OF-85-345.Williamson AK, Prudic DE, Swain LA. 1989. Groundwater Flow in the Central Valley, California. Regional Aquifer-System Analysis--Central Valley, California. USGS. Professional Paper 1401-D.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04