Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Jess Valley Groundwater BasinJess Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-3• County: Modoc• Surface Area: 6,700 acres (10 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Jess Valley Groundwater Basin is located in southeastern Modoc County and consists of Quaternary alluvium and lake deposits. The west side of the basin is bounded by Miocene basalt and, to a much lesser extent, Tertiary pyroclastic rocks. The basin is bounded on all other sides by Tertiary pyroclastic rocks. Basin drainage is to the west. Annual precipitation is approximately 17 inches.Hydrogeologic InformationHydrogeologic information was not available for the following:Water-Bearing Formations Groundwater Level Trends Groundwater StorageGroundwater Budget (Type B)The estimate of groundwater extraction for the Jess Valley Basin is based on a 1997 survey conducted by the California Department of Water Resources. The survey included landuse and sources of water. Groundwater extraction for municipal and industrial uses is estimated to be 2 acre-feet. Deep percolatin of applied water is estimated to be 830 acre-feet.Groundwater QualityWell CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationNKD – No known dataActive Monitoring Data Agency Parameter3000 (1 Well Completion Report)Total depths (ft)NKD500 (1 Well Completion Report)￼￼NKD – No known dataLast update 2/27/04Groundwater levelsMiscellaneous water qualityNumber of wells /measurement frequency NKDNKD
Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Jess Valley Groundwater BasinCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateSelected ReferencesModoc County adopted a groundwater management Ordinance in 2000.None None￼￼￼California Department of Water Resources. 1963. Northeastern Counties Groundwater Investigation, Volume 1, Text. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 98. 224 p.California Department of Water Resources. 1963. Northeastern Counties Investigation, Volume 2, Plates. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 98.California Department of Water Resources. 1965. Northeastern Counties Ground Water Investigation, Appendix C, Geology. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. Bulletin 98.Gay TE, Jr., Aune QA. 1968. Geologic Map of California [Alturas Sheet]. California Division of Mines and Geology. Atlas.BibliographyBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.Thompson TH, Chappell R. 1983. Maps Showing Distribution of Dissolved Solids and Dominant Chemical Type in Ground Water, Basin and Range Province, Northern California. USGS. WRI 83-4115-B.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.Last update 2/27/04