Sacramento River Hydrologic Region McCloud Area Groundwater BasinMcCloud Area Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-35• County: Siskiyou• Surface Area: 21,320 acres (33 square miles)Basin Boundary and HydrologyThe McCloud Area Groundwater Basin is located at the base of Mount Shasta on the southeast slope. Elevation of the basin ranges from 3,060 feet mean sea level in the south to 6,000 feet mean sea level in the north. The basin is bounded to the west by Pleistocene volcanic rocks and glacial deposits of Mount Shasta. The basin is bounded to the north by Pliocene basalt, to the east by Pliocene basalt and Pleistocene volcanic rocks, and to the south by Paleozoic marine sedimentary and metasedimentary rocks (Strand 1962). Numerous creeks that drain Mount Shasta transect the basin and McCloud River drains the basin to the south. Annual precipitation ranges from 49- to 55-inches, increasing to the north.Hydrogeologic InformationHydrogeologic information was not available for the following:Water-Bearing Formations Groundwater Level Trends Groundwater StorageGroundwater Budget (Type B)The estimate of groundwater extraction for the McCloud Area Basin is based on a 1991 survey conducted by the California Department of Water Resources. The survey included land use and sources of water.Groundwater extraction for agricultural use is estimated to be 3 acre-feet. Groundwater extraction for municipal and industrial uses is estimated to be 420 acre-feet. Deep percolation of applied water is estimated to be 280 acre- feet.Groundwater QualityWater Quality in Public Supply WellsCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Constituent Group1Inorganics – Primary RadiologicalNitratesPesticidesVOCs and SVOCs Inorganics – SecondaryNumber of wells sampled2 00 1 0 0 0Number of wells with a concentration above an MCL3 00 0 0 0 0￼￼1 A description of each member in the constituent groups anddiscussion of the relevance of these groups are included in California’s Groundwater – Bulletin 118 by DWR (2003).Last update 2/27/04a generalized
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region McCloud Area Groundwater Basin2 Represents distinct number of wells sampled as required under DHS Title 22 program from 1994 through 2000.3 Each well reported with a concentration above an MCL was confirmed with a second detection above an MCL. This information is intended as an indicator of the types of activities that cause contamination in a given basin. It represents the water quality at the sample location. It does not indicate the water quality delivered to the consumer. More detailed drinking water quality information can be obtained from the local water purveyor and its annual Consumer Confidence Report.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Well CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)￼IrrigationDomestic Irrigation380 (1 Well Completion Report)Average: 132 (32 Well Completion Reports) Average: 170 (2 Well Completion Reports)Number of wells /measurement frequency NKDNKD 1Active Monitoring Data Agency ParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneouswater quality Department of MiscellaneousHealth Services water qualityNKD – No Known DataBasin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateSelected ReferencesTotal depths (ft)Range: 43 – 280 Range: 112 – 227￼￼￼￼Siskiyou County adopted a groundwater management ordinance in 1998.McCloud CSD None￼Strand RG. 1962. Geologic Map of California [Weed Sheet] Scale 1:250,000. California Division of Mines and Geology.U. S. Geological Survey. 1956. Plan and Profile, McCloud River, California : Shasta Lake to Mile 38.5; Squaw Valley Creek to Mile 20--Dam Sites. USGS.Wagner DL, Saucedo GJ. 1987. Geologic Map of the Weed Quadrangle, California, Regional Geologic Map Series 4A. California Division of Mines and Geology.BibliographyBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region McCloud Area Groundwater BasinCalifornia Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04