Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Round Valley Groundwater BasinRound Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-36• County: Modoc• Surface Area: 7,270 acres (11 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Round Valley Groundwater Basin is northeast of Big Valley and surrounded entirely by mountains. The basin is bounded to the northwest by Tertiary basalt of Ryan and Barbar ridges, to the north and northeast by Tertiary pyroclastic rocks of Horsehead Mountain, and to the south and southwest by Tertiary pyroclastic rocks.Ash Creek enters the valley from the southeast and continues to flow to the southwest entering Big Valley through a narrows in Barber Ridge. Annual precipitation ranges from 15- to 19-inches.Hydrogeologic InformationWater-Bearing FormationsThe primary water-bearing formations in Round Valley are Holocene sedimentary deposits, Pliocene lava flows, and the Plio-Plesitocene Bieber Formation. The following summary of water-bearing formations is from DWR (1963).Holocene Sedimentary Deposits. The Holocene sedimentary deposits include basin deposits, intermediate alluvium, and alluvial fan deposits. Basin deposits, located predominately in low-lying areas in the southeast central part of the valley, consist of unconsolidated interbedded silt, clay and organic muck having low permeability. These deposits are not considered to be a significant water-bearing formation.Intermediate alluvium, found along the perimeter and the northwest central part of the valley, consists of unconsolidated silt and sand with some clay and gravel. These deposits are generally moderately permeable with gravel zones being highly permeable.Alluvial fan deposits consist of unconsolidated poorly stratified silt, sand, and gravel with some clay lenses. Because the fans occur in only a few small areas, they are not considered a significant source of water. Locally they may yield moderate amounts of water to wells.Plio-Pleistocene Bieber Formation. The Bieber Formation consists of lake deposited diatomite, clay, silt, sand, and gravel. These interbedded sediments are unconsolidated to semi-consolidated and are moderately permeable. The principal water-bearing zones consist of white pumiceous sand and black volcanic sand which yield large amounts of water to wells where there’s sufficient thickness and continuity.Pliocene Volcanic Rocks. Pliocene lavas consisting of jointed and fractured basalt occur to the north and south of Round Valley on the surrounding ridges. The lavas are moderately permeable and serve primarily as rechargeCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Round Valley Groundwater Basinareas in the uplands. They may contain unconfined and confined zones near the margins of the valley.Recharge AreasGroundwater within the sediments of Round Valley is recharged primarily from the upland recharge areas of Pliocene basalt northwest of Round Valley. The Turner Creek Formation of Ryan Ridge is a barrier between groundwater moving downslope through Barber Canyon and groundwater of Round Valley.Groundwater Level TrendsAnalysis incomplete.Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. Storage capacity for the basin is estimated to be 120,000 acre-feet to a depth of 200 feet (DWR 1963). DWR (1963) notes that the quantity of water that is useable in storage is unknown.Groundwater Budget (Type B)Estimates of groundwater extraction are based on a survey conducted by the California Department of Water Resources during 1997. The surveys included land use and sources of water. Estimates of groundwater extraction for agricultural and municipal/industrial uses are 400 and 4 acre-feet respectively. Deep percolation is estimated to be 460 acre-feet.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. Sodium bicarbonate type waters are present in the basin. The concentration of total dissolved solids ranges between 141- to 633-mg/L, averaging 260 mg/L (DWR unpublished data).Impairments. Locally high conductivity, calcium, adjusted sodium absorption ratio, phosphorus, and total dissolved solids levels occur in the basin.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Well CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)￼IrrigationDomestic IrrigationRange: 50 – 2000Total depths (ft)Range: 36 –500 Range: 48 – 720￼Active Monitoring Data Agency ParameterDWR Groundwater levelsMiscellaneousWater Quality NKD – No Known DataAverage: 800 (3 Well Completion Reports)Average: 200 (17 Well Completion Reports) Average: 439 (10 Well Completion Reports)Number of wells /measurement frequency 2 wells semi-annuallyNKD￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Round Valley Groundwater BasinCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateSelected ReferencesModoc County adopted a groundwater management ordinance in 2000.Adin Community Service District￼￼￼California Department of Water Resources. 1963. Northeastern Counties Groundwater Investigation, Volume 1, Text. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 98. 224 p.California Department of Water Resources. 1963. Northeastern Counties Investigation, Volume 2, Plates. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 98.BibliographyBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1959. Big Valley Water Quality Investigation. California Department of Water Resources, Division of Resource Planning.California Department of Water Resources. 1960. Northeastern Counties Investigation. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 58.California Department of Water Resources. 1964. Quality of Ground Water in California 1961-62, Part 1: Northern and Central California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 66-62.California Department of Water Resources. 1965. Northeastern Counties Ground Water Investigation, Appendix C, Geology. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. Bulletin 98.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Gay TE, Jr., Aune QA. 1968. Geologic Map of California, [Alturas Sheet]. California Division of Mines and Geology. Atlas.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.Last update 2/27/04