Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Long Valley Groundwater BasinLong Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-44• County: Lassen, Modoc• Surface Area: 1,090 acres (2 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Long Valley Groundwater Basin is located in eastern Modoc and Lassen counties. The basin is an alluvial filled valley bounded on the west side by a north/south trending fault. The basin is bounded on the northern half of the west side of the valley by Tertiary pyroclastic rocks and on all other sides by Miocene basalt (Gay 1968). Annual precipitation ranges from 25- to 27- inches.Hydrogeologic InformationHydrogeologic information was not available for the following:Water-Bearing Formations Groundwater Level Trends Groundwater Storage Groundwater Budget Groundwater QualityWell CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)Municipal/Irrigation NKDTotal depths (ft)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Domestic NKD Municipal/Irrigation NKDNKD – No Known DataActive Monitoring Data Agency ParameterNumber of wells /measurement frequency NKDNKD￼￼NKD – No Known DataBasin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateModoc County adopted a groundwater management ordinance in 2000.Groundwater levelsMiscellaneous water quality￼￼Last update 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Long Valley Groundwater BasinSelected ReferencesCalifornia Department of Water Resources. 1963. Northeastern Counties Groundwater Investigation, Volume 1, Text. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 98. 224 p.California Department of Water Resources. 1963. Northeastern Counties Investigation, Volume 2, Plates. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 98.California Department of Water Resources. 1965. Northeastern Counties Ground Water Investigation, Appendix C, Geology. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. Bulletin 98.Gay TE, Jr., Aune QA. 1968. Geologic Map of California [Alturas Sheet]. California Division of Mines and Geology. Atlas.Thompson TH, Chappell R. 1983. Maps Showing Distribution of Dissolved Solids and Dominant Chemical Type in Ground Water, Basin and Range Province, Northern California. USGS. WRI 83-4115-B.BibliographyBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04