Hydrologic Region Sacramento RiverNorth Fork Battle Creek Valley Groundwater BasinNorth Fork Battle Creek Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-50• County: Shasta• Surface Area: 12,760 acres (20 square miles)Basin Boundary and HydrologyThe North Fork Battle Creek Valley Basin is located in eastern Shasta County near the crest of the Cascade Range. The basin is bounded to the north by Pliocene volcanic rock and on all other sides by Pleistocene volcanic basalt (Gay 1960). The basin consists of several east-west trending courses of alluvium located along North Fork Battle Creek and Bailey Creek. Annual precipitation ranges from 43- to 49-inches, increasing to the west.Hydrogeologic InformationWater-Bearing FormationsWater-bearing formations in the basin include the Quaternary alluvium and underlying volcanic rocks.Holocene Alluvium. Driller reports for wells located in the area of Viola (along the eastern basin boundary) show uniform stratification of alluvium and volcanic rocks. The reports indicate that alluvium is approximately 32 feet thick overlying a succession of volcanic rocks (DWR 1984). The volcanic rocks are composed of two 10- to 40-foot thick flows which are separated by a 40- to 80-foot section of sand, gravel, ash, and cinders. DWR (1984) indicates that the interbedded sand-gravel-ash-cinder strata is the primary groundwater source in the area.Groundwater Level TrendsDWR (1984) reports that groundwater in the area of Viola has a seasonal fluctuation of 1-foot with the lowest elevations occurring during periods of maximum evapotranspiration.Hydrogeologic information was not available for the following:Groundwater Storage Groundwater Budget (Type B)The estimate of groundwater extraction is based on a 1995 survey conducted by the California Department of Water Resources. The survey included land use and sources of water. Groundwater extraction for municipal and industrial use is estimated to be 190 acre-feet. Deep percolation of applied water is estimated to be 220 acre-feet.Groundwater QualityCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region Sacramento RiverNorth Fork Battle Creek Valley Groundwater BasinWater Quality in Public Supply WellsCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Constituent Group1Inorganics – Primary RadiologicalNitratesPesticidesVOCs and SVOCs Inorganics – SecondaryNumber of wells sampled2 01 0 0 0 0Number of wells with a concentration above an MCL3 00 0 0 0 0￼￼1 A description of each member in the constituent groups anddiscussion of the relevance of these groups are included in California’s Groundwater – Bulletin 118 by DWR (2003).2 Represents distinct number of wells sampled as required under DHS Title 22 program from 1994 through 2000.3 Each well reported with a concentration above an MCL was confirmed with a second detection above an MCL. This information is intended as an indicator of the types of activities that cause contamination in a given basin. It represents the water quality at the sample location. It does not indicate the water quality delivered to the consumer. More detailed drinking water quality information can be obtained from the local water purveyor and its annual Consumer Confidence Report.Well CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)a generalized￼Municipal/IrrigationDomesticMunicipal/IrrigationDWR (1984) reports an average yield of 20 gpmTotal depths (ft)Range: 45 – 600; Average: 198 (186 completion reports)264 (1 completion report)￼Active Monitoring Data￼Agency Parameter Number of wells /measurement frequencyGroundwater NKDlevelsDepartment of Miscellaneous 3Health Services water qualityNKD – No Known DataBasin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateShasta County adopted a groundwater management ordinance in 1998.None None￼￼Last update 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region Sacramento RiverNorth Fork Battle Creek Valley Groundwater BasinSelected ReferencesCalifornia Department of Water Resources. 1963. Northeastern Counties Groundwater Investigation, Volume 1 and Volume 2. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 98.California Department of Water Resources. 1960. Northeastern Counties Investigation. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 58.California Department of Water Resources. 1964. Shasta County Investigation. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 22.California Department of Water Resources. 1965. Northeastern Counties Ground Water Investigation, Appendix C, Geology. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. Bulletin 98.California Department of Conservation, Division of Mines and Geology. 1966. Geology of Northern California Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1968. Water Well Standards-Shasta County, California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 74-8.California Department of Water Resources. 1982. Northeastern Counties Ground Water Update. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. Office Report.California Department of Water Resources. 1984. Eastern Shasta County Ground Water Study, California Department of Water Resources, Northern District.Gay TE, Jr., Aune QA. 1960. Geologic Map of California, [Westwood Sheet]. California Division of Mines and Geology. Atlas.BibliographyCalifornia Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04