Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Butte Creek Valley Groundwater BasinButte Creek Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-51• County: Lassen• Surface Area: 3,230 acres (5 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Butte Creek Valley Groundwater Basin is an alluvium filled valley located to the west of Crater Lake Mountain and to the northwest of Project Peak in southwest Lassen County. The basin is bounded on all sides by Pleistocene basalt (Lydon 1960). Annual precipitation ranges between 17- to 19-inches.Hydrogeologic InformationHydrogeologic information was not available for the following:Water-Bearing Formations Groundwater Level Trends Groundwater Storage Groundwater Budget Groundwater QualityWell CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)Municipal/Irrigation NKDTotal depths (ft)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Domestic NKD Municipal/Irrigation NKDNKD – No Known DataActive Monitoring Data Agency ParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneouswater quality NKD – No Known DataBasin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateNumber of wells /measurement frequency NKDNKD￼￼￼No known groundwater management plans, groundwater ordinances, or basin adjudications.None None￼Last update 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Butte Creek Valley Groundwater BasinSelected ReferencesLydon PA, Gay TE, Jennings CW. 1960. Geologic Atlas of California [Westwood Sheet]. California Division of Mines and Geology.BibliographyBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04