Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Redding Groundwater BasinRedding Groundwater Basin, Bowman Subbasin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-6.01• County: Tehama• Surface Area: 85,330 acres (133 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Bowman Subbasin comprises the portion of the Redding Groundwater Basin bounded on the west by the Coast Ranges; on the north by Salt, Dry, and Cottonwood Creeks; on the east by the Sacramento River and on the south by the Red Bluff Arch. The Red Bluff Arch is defined as the hydrologic divide between the drainages of Cottonwood Creek and Hooker Creek to the north and the drainages of Blue Tent Creek, Dibble Creek, and Reeds Creek to the south.The South Fork of Cottonwood Creek drains the western half of the subbasin and Hooker Creek drains the central portion. The eastern extents of the subbasin has many small drainages tributary to the Sacramento River. Annual precipitation ranges from 23- to 27-inches.Hydrogeologic InformationWater-Bearing FormationsThe Bowman Subbasin aquifer system consists of continental deposits of late Tertiary to Quaternary age. The Quaternary deposits include Holocene alluvium and Pleistocene Modesto and Riverbank formations. The Tertiary deposits include Pliocene Tehama and Tuscan formations. The following descriptions are from Helley and Harwood (1985) unless otherwise noted.Holocene Alluvium. The alluvium consists of unconsolidated gravel, sand, silt and clay from stream channel and floodplain deposits. These deposits are found along stream and river channels. The thickness ranges up to 30 feet. This unit represents the perched water table and the upper part of the unconfined zone of the aquifer. Although the alluvium is moderately permeable, it is not a significant contributor to groundwater usage.Pleistocene Modesto and Riverbank Formations. The Modesto and Riverbank formations consist of poorly consolidated gravel with some sand and silt deposited during the Pleistocene time. They are usually found as terrace deposits near the surface along the Sacramento River and its tributaries. Modesto Formation deposits are observed along parts of Cottonwood Creek and Hooker Creek and along the Sacramento River. Riverbank Formation deposits are observed along all major creeks. The thickness ranges up to 50 feet. These deposits are moderately to highly permeable and yield limited domestic water supplies.Pliocene Tehama Formation. The Tehama Formation consists of locally cemented silts, sand, gravel, and clay of fluviatile origin derived from the Klamath Mountains and Coast Ranges and is the principal water-bearing formation in the subbasin. The formation is exposed over approximately 80 percent of the subbasin surface area. The thickness varies from 4,000 feet toCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Redding Groundwater Basinthe north to approximately 3,800 feet to the south along Interstate Highway 5. The thickness of the deposit thins to the west from Cottonwood and reaches a thickness of 2,500 feet at the Sacramento River (DWR 1964). The permeability of the formation is moderate to high with yields of 100- to 1,000-gpm.Pliocene Tuscan Formation. The Tuscan Formation is found interfingered with the Tehama Formation south of Cottonwood Creek. The overlapping thickness may reach up to 2,500 feet towards the Red Bluff Arch. The Tuscan Formation is the principal water-bearing formation at the eastern extents of the subbasin. The formation consists of volcanic gravel and tuff- breccia, fine- to coarse-grained volcanic sandstone, conglomerate, tuff, tuffaceous silt and clay predominantly derived from andesitic and basaltic source rocks. The formation is described as four separate but lithologically similar units, Units A through D (with Unit A being the oldest), which in some areas are separated by layers of thin tuff or ash units.Unit A is the oldest water-bearing unit of the formation and is characterized by the presence of metamorphic clasts within interbedded lahars, volcanic conglomerate, volcanic sandstone and siltstone. Unit B is composed of a fairly equal distribution of lahars, tuffaceous sandstone, and conglomerate. Coarse cobble to boulder conglomerate predominates the deposit in the eastern and northern parts of mapped unit. Unit C consists of several massive mudflow or lahar deposits with some interbedded volcanic conglomerate and sandstone. Unit D consists of fragmental deposits characterized by large monolithologic masses of andesite, pumice, and fragments of black obsidian in a mudstone matrix. The unit has limited areal extents and may not occur within the Redding Basin.Permeability is moderate to high with yields of 100- to 1,000-gpm except for beds of tuff-breccia which are essentially impermeable.Restrictive StructuresThe Red Bluff Arch is an anticlinal structure that forms the hydrogeologic boundary between the Redding and Sacramento Valley groundwater basins.Recharge AreasRecharge to the principal aquifer is mostly by infiltration of streamflows at the margins of the subbasin. Infiltration of applied water and streamflows, and direct infiltration of precipitation are the main sources of recharge into the alluvium (Pierce 1983).Groundwater Level TrendsReview of the hydrographs for long-term comparison of spring-spring groundwater levels indicates a slight decline in groundwater levels associated with the 1976-77 and 1987-94 droughts, followed by a recovery to pre- drought conditions of the early 1970’s and 1980’s. Some wells increased in levels beyond the pre-drought conditions of the 1970’s during the wet season of the early 1980’s. Generally, the seasonal fluctuation is approximately 5- feet for normal and dry years. Overall, there does not appear to be any increasing or decreasing trends in groundwater levels.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Redding Groundwater BasinGroundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. The storage capacity for the entire Redding Basin is estimated to be 5.5 million acre-feet for 200 feet of saturated thickness over an area of approximately 510 square miles (Pierce 1983). Specific yield data for the Bowman Subbasin aquifer system is not available to estimate storage capacity at the subbasin level.Groundwater Budget (Type B)Estimates of groundwater extraction are based on surveys conducted by the California Department of Water Resources during 1994 and 1995. Surveys included land use and sources of water. Estimates of groundwater extraction for agricultural and municipal/industrial uses are 350 and 9 acre-feet respectively. Deep percolation of applied water is estimated to be 1,500 acre-feet.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. Groundwater in the subbasin is characterized as magnesium-calcium bicarbonate and calcium-magnesium bicarbonate type waters. Total dissolved solids concentrations range from 70- to 247-mg/L (DWR unpublished data).Impairments. Groundwater impairments include localized high boron concentrations.Water Quality in Public Supply WellsCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Constituent Group1Inorganics – Primary RadiologicalNitratesPesticidesVOCs and SVOCs Inorganics – SecondaryNumber of wells sampled2 65 6 5 5 6Number of wells with a concentration above an MCL3 00 0 0 0 1￼￼1 A description of each member in the constituent groups anddiscussion of the relevance of these groups are included in California’s Groundwater – Bulletin 118 by DWR (2003).2 Represents distinct number of wells sampled as required under DHS Title 22 program from 1994 through 2000.3 Each well reported with a concentration above an MCL was confirmed with a second detection above an MCL. This information is intended as an indicator of the types of activities that cause contamination in a given basin. It represents the water quality at the sample location. It does not indicate the water quality delivered to the consumer. More detailed drinking water quality information can be obtained from the local water purveyor and its annual Consumer Confidence Report.Last update 2/27/04a generalized
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Redding Groundwater BasinWell CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼IrrigationDomestic IrrigationRange: 65 – 2000Total depths (ft)Range: 60 – 700 Range: 112 – 600Average: 589 (4 Well Completion Reports)Average: 257 (804 Well Completion Reports)Average: 312 ( 27 Well Completion Reports)￼Active Monitoring Data￼AgencyDWRDepartment of Health ServicesParameter Number of wells /measurement frequencyGroundwater levels 8 wells semi-annuallyMiscellaneous 13 Water Quality￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateReferences CitedTehama County adopted a groundwater management ordinance in 1994. Tehama County adopted a countywide AB3030 plan in 1996.Tehama County Flood Control and Water Conservation DistrictAnderson-Cottonwood ID, and Rio Alto WD.￼￼California Department of Water Resources. 1964. Shasta County Investigation. Appendixes E through P. Bulletin 22.Helley EJ, Harwood DS. 1985. Geologic Map of the Late Cenozoic Deposits of the Sacramento Valley and Northern Sierran Foothills, California. USGS Map MF-1790.Pierce MJ. 1983. Ground Water in the Redding Basin Shasta and Tehama Counties California. USGS Water-Resources Investigations Report 83-4052.Additional ReferencesBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1964. Quality of Ground Water in California 1961-62, Part 1: Northern and Central California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 66-62.Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Redding Groundwater BasinCalifornia Department of Water Resources. 1966. Precipitation in the Central Valley. Coordinated Statewide Planning Program. California Department of Water Resources, Sacramento District. Office Report.California Department of Water Resources. 1968. Water Well Standards-Shasta County, California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 74-8.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. Progress Report Sacramento And Redding Basins Groundwater Study. California Department of Water Resources, Northern and Central Districts, in cooperation with the U.S. Geological Survey. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1978. Evaluation of Groundwater Resources: Sacramento Valley. Department of Water Resources in cooperation with the United States Geological Survey. Appendix A. Bulletin 118-6.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.California Department of Water Resources. 1987. Progress Report Sacramento and Redding Basins Ground Water Study. California Department of Water Resources, Northern and Central Districts, in cooperation with the U.S. Geological Survey.California Department of Water Resources. 1993. Ground Water Levels in the Sacramento Valley Ground Water Basin; Tehama County. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District.California Department of Water Resources. 1995. Sacramento Valley Groundwater Quality Investigation. California Department of Water Resouces, Northern District.California Department of Water Resources. 1996. Groundwater Levels in the Redding Groundwater Basin. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District.California Department of Water Resources. 1998. California Water Plan Update. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 160-98 Volumes 1 and 2.CH2M Hill. 1975. Redding Regional Water Supply Alternatives for Shasta County Water Agency, City of Redding, Enterprise Public Utility District, Cascade Community Services District, and Bella Vista Water District. Engineering Report.CH2M Hill. 2001. Redding Basin Water Resources Management Plan, Phase 2B Report, Prepared for Redding Area Water Council.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Diller JA. 1906. Description of the Redding Quadrangle (California). USGS. Report No.138. 14 p.Evenson KD, Kinsey WB. 1985. Maps Showing Ground-Water Conditions in the Cottonwood Creek Area, Shasta and Tehama Counties, California,1983-84. USGS. WRI 85-4184.Fogelman RP, Evenson KD. 1984. Water Resources Monitoring in the Cottonwood Creek Area, Shasta and Tehama Counties, California, 1982-1983. USGS. Water Resources Investigations 84-4187.Fraticelli LA, Albers JP, Irwin WP, Blake MC. 1987. Geologic Map of the Redding 1 x 2 Degree Quadrangle, Shasta, Tehama, Humboldt, and Trintity Counties, California. USGS. OF-87-257.Graham SA, Lowe DR, editors. 1993. Advances in Sedimentary Geology of the Great Valley Group, Sacramento Valley, California.Helley EJ, Jaworowski C. 1985. The Red Bluff Pediment; A Datum Plane for Locating Quaternary Structures in the Sacramento Valley, California. USGS.Hinds NEA. 1933. Geologic Formations of the Redding and Weaverville Districts, Northern California. California Journal of Mines and Geology 29(1):76-122.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Redding Groundwater BasinIngersoll RV, Rich EI, Dickerson WR. 1977. Field Guide: Great Valley Sequence, Sacramento Valley.Johnson MJ, Houston ER, Neil JM. 1989. Test Holes for Monitoring Surface Water/Groundwater Relations in the Cottonwood Creek Area, Shasta and Tehama Counties, California. USGS. WRI 88-4090.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.Steele WC. 1980. Quaternary Stream Terraces in the Northwestern Sacramento Valley, Glenn, Tehama, and Shasta Counties, California. USGS.Strand RG. 1963. Geologic Atlas of California [Redding Sheet]. California Division of Mines and Geology.Tehama County Flood Control and Water Conservation District. 1996. Coordinated AB 3030 Groundwater Management Plan. Tehama County Flood Control and Water Conservation District.Tehama County Flood Control and Water Conservation District. 1999. Coordinated AB 3030 Groundwater Management Plan, First Annual Report. Tehama County Flood Control and Water Conservation District.United States Army Corps of Engineers Sacramento District. 1978. Flood Hazard Information: Sacramento River and Cottonwood and Battle Creeks, Cottonwood-Bend Area, California. Sacramento, Calif.: United States Army Corps of Engineers Sacramento District.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04