Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Stonyford Town Area Groundwater BasinStonyford Town Area Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-63• County: Glenn, Colusa• Surface Area: 6,440 acres (10 square miles)Basin Boundary and HydrologyThe Stonyford Town Area Groundwater Basin consists of Quaternary stream terrace deposits and may be bounded on several sides by faulting of the Stony Creek Fault System. The basin is bounded to the west by Mesozoic Franciscan volcanic and metavolcanic rocks, to the north by metasedimentary rocks of the Franciscan Formation and Mesozoic ultrabasic intrusive rocks, and to the south and east by Mesozoic ultrabasic intrusive rocks and the Knoxville Formation (Jennings 1960). Annual precipitation ranges between 21- to 23-inches.Hydrogeologic InformationHydrologic information was not available for the following:Water-Bearing Formations Groundwater Level Trends Groundwater StorageGroundwater Budget (Type B)The estimate of groundwater extraction for the Stonyford Town Area Basin is based on a1993 survey conducted by the California Department of Water Resources. The survey included land use and sources of water. Groundwater extraction for municipal and industrial uses is estimated to be 35 acre-feet. Deep percolation of applied water is estimated to be 400 acre- feet.Groundwater QualityWater Quality in Public Supply WellsCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Constituent Group1Inorganics – Primary RadiologicalNitratesPesticidesVOCs and SVOCs Inorganics – SecondaryNumber of wells sampled2 22 2 2 2 2Number of wells with a concentration above an MCL3 00 0 0 0 0￼￼1 A description of each member in the constituent groups anddiscussion of the relevance of these groups are included in California’s Groundwater – Bulletin 118 by DWR (2003).2 Represents distinct number of wells sampled as required under DHS Title 22 program from 1994 through 2000.3 Each well reported with a concentration above an MCL was confirmed with a second detection above an MCL. This information is intended as an indicator of theLast update 2/27/04a generalized
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Stonyford Town Area Groundwater Basintypes of activities that cause contamination in a given basin. It represents the water quality at the sample location. It does not indicate the water quality delivered to the consumer. More detailed drinking water quality information can be obtained from the local water purveyor and its annual Consumer Confidence Report.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Well CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)￼IrrigationDomestic IrrigationNKD – No Known DataNKDTotal depths (ft)Range: 30 – 220Average: 108 (40 Well Completion Reports) 76 (1 Well Completion Report)Number of wells /measurement frequency NKDNKDGlenn Countymanagement ordinance in 2000. Colusa County adopted a groundwater management ordinance in 1998.￼Active Monitoring Data Agency ParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneouswater quality NKD – No Known DataBasin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateSelected Referencesadopted a groundwater￼￼￼Jennings CW, Strand RG. 1960. Geologic Map of California [Ukiah Sheet]. California Division of Mines and Geology.BibliographyBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Stonyford Town Area Groundwater BasinIngersoll RV, Rich EI, Dickerson WR. 1977. Field Guide: Great Valley Sequence, Sacramento Valley.McLaughlin RJ, Ohlin HN, Blome CD. 1983. Tectonostratigraphic Framework of the Franciscan Assemblage and Lower Part of the Great Valley Sequence in the Geysers- Clear Lake Region, California. American Geophysical Union, Eos, Transactions.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04