Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Funks Creek Groundwater BasinFunks Creek Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-90• County: Glenn, Colusa• Surface Area: 3,000 acres (5 square miles)Basin Boundary and HydrologyThe Funks Creek Groundwater Basin is located north of Antelope Valley and overlies the boundary of Glenn and Colusa Counties. The basin is north of a series of northeast trending faults and is bounded on all sides by Upper Cretaceous Marine deposits. The basin consists of Quaternary alluvial deposits and is drained to the east by Grapevine Creek and Funks Creek (Jennings 1960). Annual precipitation is approximately 18 inches.Hydrogeologic InformationHydrologic information was not available for the following:Water-Bearing Formations Groundwater Level Trends Groundwater Storage Groundwater Budget Groundwater QualityWell CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)Municipal/Irrigation NKDTotal depths (ft)Domestic NKD Municipal/Irrigation NKDNKD – No known dataActive Monitoring DataAgency Parameter Number of wells /measurement frequencyGroundwater levels NKDMiscellaneous NKDwater quality NKD – No Known DataCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼￼￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateGlenn County adopted a groundwater management ordinance in 2000. Colusa County adopted a groundwater management ordinance in 1998.None None￼￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Funks Creek Groundwater BasinSelected ReferencesJennings CW, Strand RG. 1960. Geologic Map of California [Ukiah Sheet]. California Division of Mines and Geology.BibliographyBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Ingersoll RV, Rich EI, Dickerson WR. 1977. Field Guide: Great Valley Sequence, Sacramento Valley.McLaughlin RJ, Ohlin HN, Blome CD. 1983. Tectonostratigraphic Framework of the Franciscan Assemblage and Lower Part of the Great Valley Sequence in the Geysers- Clear Lake Region, California. American Geophysical Union, Eos, Transactions.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04