San Francisco Bay Hydrologic RegionArroyo del Hambre Valley Groundwater BasinArroyo del Hambre Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 2-31• County: Contra Costa• Surface Area: 730 acres (1.3 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Arroyo del Hambre Valley Groundwater Basin is located in northern Contra Costa County along the south shore of Suisun Bay. The basin is about 35 miles northeast of San Francisco. It is bounded by Suisun Bay on the north, the Berkeley foothills on the west, the Ygnacio Valley groundwater basin on the east and the City of Martinez on the south.The topography of the area consists of gentle sloping lowlands ranging in elevation from sea level to 100 feet. The floor of the valley slopes gently to the northwest. Average annual precipitation in the basin is about 18 inches.Hydrogeologic InformationWater Bearing FormationsDue to the lack of published data the descriptions of the Arroyo del Hambre Valley groundwater basin hydrogeology is limited. The basin is underlain by Alluvium. The water bearing units in the basin are Recent alluvium and Older alluvium valley fill deposits. There are limited data regarding the occurrence and movement of groundwater in the basin. (DWR 1975).Quaternary Alluvium. The water bearing unconsolidated Quaternary alluvium deposits have unknown physical characteristics and thickness (DWR 1975).Alluvium. Modern alluvial sediments are located along the Suisun Bay shoreline of the basin. These sediments are characterized by soft, water- saturated muds, peat and loose sands (CCCPD 1975).Groundwater Level TrendsNo published data was found for the Arroyo del Hambre Valley groundwater basin.Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. No published groundwater storage capacity data for the basin was found.Groundwater in Storage. No published groundwater in storage data for the basin was found.Groundwater Budget (Type C)Due to lack of groundwater budget data, inflows, including natural, applied, and artificial recharge and outflows including urban and agricultural extraction have not been included.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
San Francisco Bay Hydrologic RegionArroyo del Hambre Valley Groundwater BasinGroundwater QualityCharacterization. No published groundwater quality data for the basin was found. Although, DWR examined sea-water intrusion in Bulletin 63-5.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Well Production characteristics Well yields (gal/min)￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationActive Monitoring Data￼￼AgencyDWRDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water quality Title 22 water qualityAverage: 70 (based on 1 well)Number of wells /measurement frequency NKDKND NKDContra Costa WD, East Bay MUDTotal depths (ft)￼NKD- No known dataBasin ManagementGroundwater management: Water agenciesPublic PrivateReferences Cited￼￼California Department of Water Resources (DWR), Bulletin No. 63-5, Sea-Water Intrusion in California, October 1975.Contra Costa County Planning Department (CCCPD), Seismic Safety Element, being a part of the Contra Costa County General Plan, December 1975.Additional ReferencesOakeshott, G.O. 1973, Geologic map of Contra Costa County: California Division of Mines, Journal Vol. 54, No. 4, Plate 5Jennings, O.P. 1973, Geologic map of California: California Division of Mines and Geology, Geologic Map Series, San Francisco Sheet, scale 1:250,000.Jennings, O.P. 1973, Geologic map of California: California Division of Mines and Geology, Geologic Map Series, Santa Rosa Sheet, scale 1:250,000.California Department of Water Resources, Bulletin No. 77-58, Ground Water Conditions in Central and Northern California 1957-58, October 1959.California Department of Water Resources, Bulletin No. 130-72, Volume II Northeastern California, December 1973.Last update 2/27/04
San Francisco Bay Hydrologic RegionArroyo del Hambre Valley Groundwater BasinCalifornia Department of Water Resources, Bulletin No. 118-80, Ground Water Basins in California, January 1980.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04