San Francisco Bay Hydrologic Region Visitacion Groundwater BasinVisitacion Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 2-32• County: San Francisco, San Mateo• Surface Area: 5830 acres (9 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Visitacion Valley Groundwater Basin is a roughly triangular shaped basin in the San Francisco Bay Hydrologic Region within the City of San Francisco. The San Bruno Mountains bound it on the southwest. It is separated from the Islais Valley Groundwater Basin to the northwest and the South San Francisco Groundwater Basin to the northeast by bedrock topographic highs. The San Francisco bay forms the basin boundary along its eastern extent (Phillips et al, 1993.) Mean annual precipitation within the basin is in the range of 20 inches to 24 inches (USDA, 1999).Hydrogeologic InformationWater Bearing FormationsGeologically the basin can be broadly classified as unconsolidated sediment and bedrock (Phillips et al, 1993). The primary water-bearing formations are unconsolidated sediments, including dune sand, the Colma Formation, bay mud and clay, and artificial fill (Phillips et al, 1993). The Colma Formation consists of fine-grained sand, silty sand and discontinuous beds of clay to five feet thick (Phillips et al, 1993). The artificial fill is largely composed of dune sand with lesser amounts of silt and clay, and some manmade debris (Schlocker, 1974). It reaches a maximum total thickness of about 60 feet (Phillips et al, 1993). The unconsolidated material in aggregate has a maximum thickness of 200 feet indicating a relatively low storage capacity for groundwater and minimal protection from potential surface contamination (USGS, 1993). Bedrock of the Franciscan Complex underlies the water-bearing formations (Schlocker, 1974.)Groundwater RechargeSources of recharge include infiltration of rainfall, landscape irrigation, and leakage from water and sewer pipes. Average groundwater recharge in the South San Francisco Groundwater Basin for the water years 1987-1988 was estimated to be 269 acre-feet/year (Phillips et al, 1993).Groundwater Level TrendsGenerally groundwater levels have remained relatively stable within the Visitacion Valley groundwater basin (Phillips et al, 1993).Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity.No estimate of groundwater storage capacity was found.Groundwater in Storage.No estimate of groundwater in storage was found.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
San Francisco Bay Hydrologic Region Visitacion Groundwater BasinGroundwater BudgetA hydrologic routing model was developed by the USGS to estimate groundwater recharge on the San Francisco peninsula. The model was based on land use zones in the region. A detailed discussion of the groundwater budget can be found in the report by Phillips et.al, 1993.Groundwater QualityCharacterization.Most of the groundwater is a mixed cation bicarbonate type. Generally the dissolved constituents in the local groundwater are within guidelines recommended by the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (1986).Impairments.Water from wells in the basin can be considered to be hard. Elevated nitrate concentration is the most common water quality problem with wells in the San Francisco peninsula and high chloride concentrations were observed in several wells (Phillips et al, 1993).California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Well CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationRange: –Total depths (ft)Range: - Range: -￼Active Monitoring DataAverage:Average: Average:Number of wells /measurement frequency￼AgencyDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water quality Title 22 water quality￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management: Water agenciesPublic Private￼￼Last update 2/27/04
San Francisco Bay Hydrologic Region Visitacion Groundwater BasinReferences CitedPhillips, Steven P., Scott N. Hamlin, Eugene B. Yates. Geohydrology, Water Quality, and Estimation of Ground-Water Recharge in San Francisco, California 1987-92. US Geological Survey Water- Resources Investigations Report 93-4019, 1993.Schlocker, Julius. Geology of the San Francisco North Quadrangle, California. US Geological Survey Professional Paper 782, 1974USDA. United States Average Annual Precipitation, 1961-1990: Map Layer, 1999ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04