Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Mohawk Valley Groundwater BasinMohawk Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-11• Counties: Plumas, Sierra• Surface Area: 19,000 acres (30 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Mohawk Valley Groundwater Basin lies within an elongated valley occupying a portion of a long, narrow graben. The graben is bounded on the southwest side by the Mohawk Valley fault. The east side of the valley is bounded by a group of northwest trending faults that branch from the Mohawk Valley fault near Gattley. The floor of the valley consists of a narrow strip of nearly flat alluvial material overlying lake sediments. Lake sediments also underlie the upland areas of the valley. Depth to bedrock is estimated to range between 1,500- to 3,000-feet. The basin is bounded to the northeast by Pliocene volcanic rocks of Penman Peak, to the east by Miocene volcanic rocks of Beckwourth Peak, and to the west and southwest by Paleozoic metavolcanic rocks and Mesozoic granitic rocks of the Sierra Nevada mountains. Sulphur Creek drains the southern half of the valley and enters Middle Fork Feather River near the midpoint of the valley and flows northwesterly (DWR 1963). Precipitation ranges from 27- to 39-inches in the valley and ranges to 51 inches in the upland areas.Hydrogeologic InformationWater-Bearing FormationsThe primary water-bearing formations in the basin are Holocene sedimentary deposits and Pleistocene lake and near-shore deposits. The following summary of water-bearing formations is from DWR (1963).Holocene Sedimentary Deposits. Holocene sedimentary deposits include alluvial fans and intermediate alluvium. Alluvial fans consist of unconsolidated gravel, sand, and silt with minor clay lenses. Thickness of the deposits ranges to 200 feet. The fan deposits coalesce or interfinger with lake and alluvial deposits. Specific yield ranges from 8- to 17-percent. Intermediate alluvium consists of unconsolidated silt and sand with lenses of clay and gravel. Specific yield is estimated to range between 5- to 25- percent. This unit is limited in extent. The deposits are up to 50 feet in thickness and yield moderate amounts of groundwater.Pleistocene Lake and Near-Shore Deposits. Lake and near-shore deposits underlie the majority of the valley and range in thickness to over 2000 feet. These deposits consist of slightly consolidated, bedded sand, silt, and diatomaceous clay. The sand beds usually yield large quantities of confined groundwater. The near-shore deposits are composed of moderately permeable sand and gravel and, where saturated, yield moderate amounts of groundwater. Specific yield ranges from 1- to 25-percent.Groundwater Level TrendsAnalysis incomplete.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Mohawk Valley Groundwater BasinGroundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. Storage capacity for the basin is estimated to be 90,000 acre-feet based on a specific yield of 5 percent for a depth interval of zero to 200 feet (DWR 1963).Groundwater Budget (Type B)The estimate of groundwater extraction is based on a 1997 survey conducted by the California Department of Water Resources. The survey included landuse and sources of water. Groundwater extraction for municipal and industrial uses is estimated to be 130 acre-feet. Deep percolation of applied water is estimated to be 330 acre-feet.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. Calcium-magnesium bicarbonate and sodium bicarbonate are the predominant groundwater types in the basin. Total dissolved solids concentrations range from 210- to 285-mg/L, averaging 248 mg/L (DWR unpublished data).Impairments. Groundwater in the basin has locally high iron, manganese, ammonia, phosphorus, ASAR and boron levels.Water Quality in Public Supply WellsCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Constituent Group1Inorganics – Primary RadiologicalNitratesPesticidesVOCs and SVOCs Inorganics – SecondaryNumber of wells sampled2 113 15 4 4 11Number of wells with a concentration above an MCL3 00 0 0 0 5￼￼1 A description of each member in the constituent groups anddiscussion of the relevance of these groups are included in California’s Groundwater – Bulletin 118 by DWR (2003).2 Represents distinct number of wells sampled as required under DHS Title 22 program from 1994 through 2000.3 Each well reported with a concentration above an MCL was confirmed with a second detection above an MCL. This information is intended as an indicator of the types of activities that cause contamination in a given basin. It represents the water quality at the sample location. It does not indicate the water quality delivered to the consumer. More detailed drinking water quality information can be obtained from the local water purveyor and its annual Consumer Confidence Report.Last update 2/27/04a generalized
Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Mohawk Valley Groundwater BasinWell CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/Irrigation500 (1 Well Completion Report)Total depths (ft)Range: 38 – 466 Average: 133 (168 Well Completion Reports)Range: 234 – 264 Average: 249 (2 Well Completion Reports)￼Active Monitoring Data￼AgencyDWR DWRDepartment of Health ServicesParameter Number of wells /measurement frequencyGroundwater levels 1 well semi-annuallyMiscellaneous 2 wells biennially water qualityMiscellaneous 15 water quality￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateSelected ReferencesNo known groundwater management plans, groundwater ordinances, or basin adjudicationsPlumas Eureka CSD, CLIO PUD￼￼California Department of Water Resources. 1963. Northeastern Counties Groundwater Investigation, Volume 1, Text. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 98. 224 p.California Department of Water Resources. 1963. Northeastern Counties Groundwater Investigation, Volume 1, Text. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 98. 224 p.California Department of Water Resources. 1963. Northeastern Counties Investigation, Volume 2, Plates. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 98.California Department of Water Resources. 1965. Northeastern Counties Ground Water Investigation, Appendix C, Geology. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. Bulletin 98.BibliographyBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1960. Northeastern Counties Investigation. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 58.California Department of Water Resources. 1964. Quality of Ground Water in California 1961-62, Part 1: Northern and Central California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 66-62.Last update 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Mohawk Valley Groundwater BasinCalifornia Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.California Department of Water Resources. 1992. Lassen County Water Resources Assessment Study. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. Memorandum Report.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Dong AE, Tobin RL, Geological Survey (U.S.), California. Central Valley Regional Water Quality Control Board. 1973. Water Quality in the Middle Fork Feather River, California, May 1970 Through September 1971. Menlo Park, Calif.: U.S. Geological Survey. 55 p.Galloway JD, Brehme K, Jorgensen LR. 1922. Report to Mr. Karl Brehme on the Available Water at Grizzly Valley and at Gold Lake on the Watershed of the Middle Fork of the Feather River, Project #249, Jorgensen, Lars R. 18 leaves.Hill M. 1975. Geology of the Sierra Nevada: University of California Press. 232 p.Mathieson SA, Sarna-Wojcicki A, M. 1982. Ash Layer in Mohawk Valley, Plumas County, California, Correlated with the 0.45-m.y.-old Rockland Ash; Implications for the Glacial. Geological Society of America.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1,California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.Saucedo GJ, Wagner DL. 1992. Geologic Map of the Chico Quadrangle, California. California Division of Mines and Geology.United States Forest Service. 1970. River Plan, Middle Fork of the Feather, Plumas National Forest, California. San Francisco: Forest Service U.S. Dept of Agriculture. 11, 12, [11] leaves of plates.Yount JC, Harwood DS, Bradbury JP. 1993. Mohawk Lake or Mohawk Meadow? Sedimentary Facies and Stratigraphy of Quaternary Deposits in Mohawk Valley, Upper Middle Fork of the Feather River. Geological Society of America.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04