Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinSacramento Valley Groundwater Basin Yolo Subbasin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-21.67• County: Yolo, Solano• Surface Area: 256,000 acres (400 square miles)Boundaries & HydrologyThe Yolo Subbasin, located in the southern portion of the Sacramento Valley Basin primarily within Yolo County. It is bounded on the east by the Sacramento River, on the west by the Coast Range, on the north by Cache Creek, and on the south by Putah Creek. The basin is roughly bisected by an anticlinal structure, but otherwise is gently sloping from west to east with elevations ranging from approximately 400 feet at the base of the Coast Range to the west to nearly sea level in the eastern areas. Major cities within the subbasin include Davis, West Sacramento, Winters, and Woodland.Precipitation averages approximately 20 to 24 inches per year in the western portion of the subbasin, and approximately 18 to 20 inches per year in the eastern portion of the subbasin.Hydrogeologic InformationWater Bearing FormationsThe primary water bearing formations comprising the Yolo subbasin are sedimentary continental deposits of Late Tertiary (Pliocene) to Quaternary (Holocene) age. Fresh water-bearing units include younger alluvium, older alluvium, and the Tehama Formation (Olmstead, 1961 and DWR, 1978). The cumulative thickness of these units ranges from a few hundred feet near the Coast Range on the west to nearly 3000 feet near the eastern margin of the basin. Saline water-bearing sedimentary units underlie the Tehama formation and are generally considered the boundary of fresh water (Berkstresser, 1973).Younger alluvium includes flood basin deposits and Recent stream channel deposits. Flood basin deposits occur along the eastern margin of the subbasin in the Yolo Flood Basin. They consist primarily of silts and clays, but along the eastern margin of the subbasin may be locally interbedded with stream channel deposits of the Sacramento River. Thickness of the unit ranges from 0 to 150 feet. The flood basin deposits have low permeability and generally yield low quantities of water to wells. The quality of ground water produced from the basin deposits is often poor.Recent stream channel deposits consist of unconsolidated silt, fine- to medium-grained sand, gravel and occasionally cobbles deposited in and adjacent to active streams in the subbasin. They occur along the Sacramento River, Cache Creek, and Putah Creek. Thickness of the younger alluvium ranges from 0 to 150 feet.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinThe younger alluvium varies from moderately to highly permeable, but often lies above the saturated zone. Where saturated, the younger alluvium yields significant quantities of water to wells.Older alluvium consists of loose to moderately compacted silt, silty clay, sand, and gravel deposited in alluvial fans during the Pliocene and Pleistocene. Thickness of the unit ranges from 60 to 130 feet, about one- quarter of which is coarse sand and gravel. Permeability of the older alluvium is highly variable. Wells penetrating sand and gravel lenses of the unit produce between 300 and 1000 gpm. Adjacent to the Sacramento River, wells completed in ancestral Sacramento River stream channel deposits yield up to 4000 gpm. Wells completed in the finer-grained portions of the older alluvium produce between 50 and 150 gpm.The Tehama Formation is the thickest water-bearing unit underlying the Yolo subbasin, ranging in thickness from 1500 to 2500 feet. Surface exposures of the Tehama Formation are limited mainly to the Coast Range foothills along the western margin of the basin, as well as in the Plainfield Ridge. The Tehama consists of moderately compacted silt, clay, and silty fine sand enclosing lenses of sand and gravel, silt and gravel, and cemented conglomerate. Permeability of the Tehama Formation is variable, but generally less than the younger units. Because of its relatively greater thickness, however, wells completed in the unit can yield up to several thousand gallons per minute.Underlying the Tehama Formation are brackish to saline water-bearing sedimentary units, including the somewhat brackish sedimentary rocks of volcanic origin (Pliocene to Oligocene?) underlain by marine sedimentary rocks (Oligocene? to Paleocene) which are typically of low permeability and contain connate water (Olmstead, 1961). The upper contact of these units generally coincides with the fresh/saline water boundary. The contact is found near the Coast Range at depths as shallow as a few hundred feet. Near the eastern margin of the basin it reaches depths of nearly 3000 feet.Subsurface Flow ControlsThe geologic structure of the groundwater subbasin is dominated by an anticlinal ridge oriented northwest to southeast, which is expressed at the surface as the Dunnigan Hills and Plainfield Ridge. The anticlinal structure impedes subsurface flow from west to east. Subsurface groundwater outflow sometimes occurs from the Yolo subbasin into the Solano subbasin to the south. Subsurface outflow and inflow may also occur beneath the Sacramento River to the east with the South and North American subbasins. Subsurface groundwater inflow may occur from the west out of the Capay Valley Basin.Groundwater Level TrendsGroundwater levels are impacted by periods of drought due to increased groundwater pumping and less surface water recharge (e.g. in the late 1970’s and early 1990’s), but recover quickly in “wet” years. Long term trends do not indicate any significant decline in water levels, with the exception of localized pumping depressions in the vicinity of the Davis, Woodland and Dunnigan/Zamora areas. Past studies (Scott, 1975) have concluded that theCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinYolo subbasin is subject to overdraft, however the completion of Indian Valley Reservoir in 1976 provided significant relief in the form of additional available surface water (YCFCWCD, 2000).Groundwater StorageMany studies have been conducted to determine the groundwater storage within parts or all of Yolo County. Several of these studies refer to calculations completed by Scott and Scalmanini in their 1975 report, Investigations of Groundwater Resources, Yolo County. Groundwater storage capacity for the entire county for groundwater aquifer depths between 20 and 420 feet was calculated as 14,038,000 acre-feet based on subtotals from six separate study areas. Specific yields were calculated, based on well log information, for three separate depth intervals within six study areas, and ranged from 6.5% to 9.7%.Groundwater Storage Capacity. From the Scott and Scalmanini calculations it can be roughly estimated that the Yolo Subbasin, (defined in this report as a portion of the county) has a total storage capacity of 6,455,940 acre-feet for depths between 20 and 420 feet (see below).Table: Storage capacity was calculated based on Scott (1975) as follows:California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼￼Groundwater Basin (Scott, 1975)Cache CreekUpper Cache- Putah Plainfield Ridge Lower Cache- Putah ColusaYolo BypassTotals 447,000Estimated Storage Capacity within Yolo Subbasin1335,620 2,017,700240,800 2,733,055Calculated Gross Area Storage CapacityEstimated % area within Yolo 1 Subbasin20% 100%100% 95%(acres) (Scott, 1975) 45,800 1,678,10070,300 2,017,700 8,800 240,800 97,300 2,876,900 95,700 2,709,8000% 0 129,100 4,514,700 25% 1,128,765￼￼14,038,000 6,455,9401Represents the portion of each Groundwater Basin (as defined by Scott, 1975) that is contained within the Yolo Subbasin (as defined by the DWR). Percentages were estimated by DWR staff.Groundwater in Storage. Groundwater storage between the depths of 20 to 420 feet in 1974 for all of Yolo County was calculated to be 13,208,400 acre-feet (Scott, 1975). Based on the Scott report, groundwater storage within the Yolo Subbasin for 1974 is estimated at 6,074,220 acre-feet (see below).Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinTable: 1974 groundwater storage calculations based on Scott (1975):California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼GroundwaterBasin (Scott, Area1974 Calculated Storage (Scott, 1975)1,528,700 1,921,000Estimated % area withinYolo 1 Subbasin20% 100%100% 95%Estimated 1974 Storage within Yolo Subbasin1305,740 1,921,000189,400 2,543,5301975) (acres)Cache CreekUpper Cache- Putah Plainfield RidgeLower Cache- Putah45,800 70,3008,80097,300189,400 2,677,400 2,433,700Colusa 95,700Yolo Bypass 129,100 Totals 447,0000% 0 4,458,200 25% 1,114,550 13,208,400 6,074,220￼￼1Represents the portion of each Groundwater Basin (as defined by Scott, 1975) that is contained within the Yolo Subbasin (as defined by the DWR). Percentages were estimated by DWR staff.Groundwater Budget (Type C)Currently no groundwater budget has been calculated for the Yolo Subbasin (see comments below).Groundwater QualityGroundwater found within the subbasin is characterized as a sodium magnesium, calcium magnesium, or magnesium bicarbonate type. The quality is considered good for both agricultural and municipal uses, even though it is hard to very hard overall (generally over 180 mg/l CaCO3). Selenium and boron are found in higher concentrations locally (Evenson, 1985). Total dissolved solids range from a of 107 ppm to 1300 ppm and average 574 ppm, based on Title 22 data obtained from public supply water well samples (DHS, 2000).Localized impairments include elevated concentrations of boron (as high as 2 to 4 ppm) in groundwater along Cache Creek and in the Cache Creek Settling Basin area, increased levels of selenium present in the groundwater supplies for the City of Davis, and localized areas of nitrate contamination (YCFCWCD 1992) (Evenson, 1985).Water Quality in Public Supply WellsConstituent Group1Inorganics – Primary RadiologicalNitratesPesticidesVOCs and SVOCs Inorganics – SecondaryNumber of wells sampled2 6153 67 59 59 61Number of wells with a concentration above an MCL3 30 1 0 1 11￼￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater Basin1 A description of each member in the constituent groups and a generalized discussion of the relevance of these groups are included in California’s Groundwater – Bulletin 118 by DWR (2003).2 Represents distinct number of wells sampled as required under DHS Title 22 program from 1994 through 2000.3 Each well reported with a concentration above an MCL was confirmed with a second detection above an MCL. This information is intended as an indicator of the types of activities that cause contamination in a given basin. It represents the water quality at the sample location. It does not indicate the water quality delivered to the consumer. More detailed drinking water quality information can be obtained from the local water purveyor and its annual Consumer Confidence Report.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Well CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/Irrigation1Based on DWR data.Range: 150 – 4000+Total depths (ft) 1 Range: 40 - 600Range: 50 - 1500Average: 1500 (estimate)Average: 230 (estimate) Average: 400 (estimate)￼Active Monitoring Data￼AgencyDWR YCFC&WCDSacramento County USBRDHS DWRParameterGroundwater LevelsWater Quality Ground SubsidenceNumber of wells /measurement frequency 10 semi-annually4 monthly92 semi-annually1 monthly1 semi-annually12 semi-annually7 monthly133 annually1 continuously￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateR.D. 108 adopted AB3030 plan 2/95R.D. 2035 adopted AB3030 plan 4/95R.D. 2068 adopted AB3030 plan 1/97Yolo County Flood Control and Water Conservation District are drafting plan but not pursuant to AB3030R.D. 900, City of West Sacramento is not drafting AB3030 planYolo County Flood Control and Water Conservation DistrictCity of Woodland, City of Davis, City of West SacramentoR.D. 108, 900,2035, 2068￼￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinComments:Although groundwater budgets have been previously calculated for areas overlying the Yolo Subbasin, no groundwater budget has been calculated for the Yolo Subbasin as defined by this report.References CitedBerkstresser, C.F. Jr. Base of Fresh Ground-Water -- Approximately 3,000 micromhos -- in the Sacramento Valley and Sacramento-San Joaquin Delta, California. U.S. Geological Survey Water-Resource Inv. 40-73. 1973.California Department of Water Resources. Evaluation of Ground Water Resources: Sacramento Valley. Bulletin 118-6. August 1978.California Department of Water Resources. Groundwater Level Data. Websitehttp://well.water.ca.gov/Evenson, K.D. Chemical Quality of Ground Water in Yolo and Solano Counties, California. U.S. Geological Survey Water-Resource Investigations Report 84-4244. 1985.Olmstead, F.H., and Davis, G.H. Geologic Features and Ground-Water Storage Capacity of the Sacramento Valley, California. U.S. Geological Survey Water-Supply Paper 1497. 1961.Scott, V.H., and Scalmanini, J.C. Investigations of Groundwater Resources Yolo County, California. Department of Land, Air and Water Resources. Water Science and Engineering Paper 2006. University of California, Davis. September 1975.Yolo County Flood Control and Water Conservation District, Yolo County Water Plan. Prepared by Borcalli & Associates. September, 2000.Additional ReferencesBertoldi, G.L. Estimated Permeabilities for Soils in the Sacramento Valley, California. U.S. Geological Survey Water-Resources Investigations Report 51-73. 1974.Bryan, Kirk. Geology and Ground-Water Resources of the Sacramento Valley, California. U.S. Geological Survey Water-Supply Paper 495. 1923.California Department of Water Resources. Report to the California State Legislature on Putah Creek Cone Investigation. December 1955.California Department of Water Resources. Historical Ground Water Levels in Yolo County. District Report. December 1992.Helley, E.J., and Harwood, D.S. Geologic Map of the Late Cenozoic Deposits of the Sacramento Valley and Northern Sierran Foothills, California. U.S. Geological Survey Miscellaneous Field Studies Map MF-1790. 1985.Harwood, D.S., and Helley, E.J. Late Cenozoic Tectonism of the Sacramento Valley, California. U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 1359. 1987.Jenkins, M. Yolo County, California’s Water Supply System: Conjunctive Use Without Management. Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering. University of California, Davis. September 1992.Page, R.W. Base and Thickness of the Post-Eocene Continental Deposits in the Sacramento Valley, California. U.S. Geological Survey Water-Resource Investigations Report 45-73. 1974Page, R.W. Geology of the Fresh Ground-Water Basin of the Central Valley. California, with Texture Maps and Sections. U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 1401-C. 1986.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinThomasson, H.G., and others. Geology, Water Resources, and Usable Ground-Water Storage Capacity of Part of Solano County, California. U.S. Geological Survey Water-Supply Paper 1464. 1960.Yolo County Flood Control and Water Conservation District, Yolo County Water Plan Update (Draft). Prepared by Borcalli and Associates. 1992.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04