Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinSacramento Valley Groundwater Basin, Vina Subbasin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-21.57• County: Tehama, Butte• Surface Area: 125,640 acres (195 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Vina Subbasin comprises the portion of the Sacramento Valley groundwater basin bounded on the west by the Sacramento River, on the north by Deer Creek, on the east by the Chico Monocline and on the south by Big Chico Creek. Deer Creek and Big Chico Creek serve as hydrologic boundaries in the near surface. The subbasin is contiguous with the Los Molinos and West Butte subbasins at depth. The Chico Monocline forms a geographic boundary; however, a component of basin recharge is located east of the fault structure. Annual precipitation within the subbasin ranges from 18- to 22.5-inches, increasing to the east.Hydrogeologic InformationWater-Bearing FormationsThe aquifer system is comprised of continental deposits of Tertiary to late Quaternary age. The Quaternary deposits include Holocene stream channel deposits and Pleistocene Modesto Formation deposits, located along most stream and river channels, and alluvial fan deposits. The Tertiary deposits include the Tuscan Formation.Holocene Stream Channel Deposits. Stream channel deposits consist of unconsolidated gravel, sand, silt and clay derived from the erosion, reworking, and deposition of adjacent Tuscan Formation and Quaternary stream terrace alluvial deposits. The thickness varies from 1- to 80-feet (Helly and Harwood 1985). The unit represents the upper part of the unconfined zone of the aquifer and is moderately-to-highly permeable; however, the thickness and areal extent of the deposits limit the water- bearing capability.Holocene Basin Deposits. Basin deposits are the result of sediment-laden floodwaters that rose above the natural levees of streams and rivers to spread across low-lying areas. They consist primarily of silts and clays and may be locally interbedded with stream channel deposits along the Sacramento River. Thickness of these deposits can range up to 150 feet and they are observed primarily between Mud Creek and Rock Creek, west of Highway 99. These deposits have low permeability and generally yield low quantities of water to wells. The quality of groundwater produced from the unit is often poor (USBR 1960).Pleistocene Modesto Formation. The Pleistocene Modesto Formation (deposited between 14,000 to 42,000 years ago) consists of poorly indurated gravel and cobbles with sand, silt, and clay derived from reworking and deposition of the Tuscan Formation and Riverbank Formation. The Modesto Formation makes up the majority of the alluvial plain deposits except whereCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Sacramento Valley Groundwater Basinolder Riverbank Formation terrace deposits occur south of Pine Creek and the overlying basin deposits in the Nord area predominate. Thickness of the formation can range from less than 10 feet to nearly 200 feet across the valley floor (Helley and Harwood 1985).Pleistocene Riverbank Formation. The Riverbank Formation (older terrace deposits) consists of poorly-to-highly permeable pebble and small cobble gravels interlensed with reddish clay sands and silt. These deposits underlie the region between Pine Creek and Rock Creek. Thickness of the formation can range from less than 10 feet to nearly 200 feet across the valley floor (Helley and Harwood 1985).Pliocene Tuscan Formation. The Tuscan Formation is composed of a series of volcanic mudflows, tuff breccia, tuffaceous sandstone and volcanic ash layers. The formation is described as four separate but lithologically similar units, A through D (with Unit A being the oldest), which in some areas are separated by layers of thin tuff or ash units (Helley and Harwood 1985). Units A, B, and C are found within the subbasin and extend in the subsurface west of the Sacramento River.Unit A is the oldest water bearing unit of the formation and is characterized by the presence of metamorphic clasts within interbedded lahars, volcanic conglomerate, volcanic sandstone and siltstone. Unit B is composed of fairly equal distribution of lahars, tuffaceous sandstone, and conglomerate. Unit C consists of massive mudflow or lahar deposits with some interbedded volcanic conglomerate and sandstone. In the subsurface, these low permeability lahars form thick, confining layers for groundwater contained in the more permeable sediments of Unit B. Unit C is exposed as alluvial upland deposits west of the Chico Monocline, largely north of Singer Creek. South of Singer Creek, the alluvial upland deposits merge with younger alluvial fan and plain deposits.The Tuscan Formation reaches a thickness of 1,250 feet over older sedimentary deposits (DWR 2000). The dip of the formation averages approximately 2.5 degrees, east of the valley, and steepens sharply to 10 to 20 degrees southwestward towards the valley at the Chico Monocline. The formation flattens beneath valley sediments.Recharge AreasSurface exposure of the Tuscan Formation (Unit B) provides recharge to the subbasin within the subbasin boundaries along stream courses and east of the Chico Monocline fault structure.Groundwater Level TrendsAs part of a groundwater inventory analysis prepared for Butte County, the portion of the Vina Subbasin located within Butte County was evaluated for seasonal and long-term changes in groundwater levels for unconfined and confined aquifer systems. Long-term comparison of spring to spring groundwater levels in the northern part of the Butte County show a decline as a result of the 1976-77 and 1987-94 droughts, followed by a recovery of groundwater levels to pre-drought conditions (DWR 2001).California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinEvaluation of groundwater level data at the northern edge of the California Water Service area (just north of Chico) shows an average seasonal fluctuation in groundwater levels of approximately 10 feet during years of normal precipitation. Long-term comparison of spring to spring groundwater levels shows a decline in levels associated with the above drought periods with recovery to pre-drought conditions of the early 1970’s. Further long- term comparison of spring to spring groundwater levels indicates a 10- to 15- foot decline in groundwater levels since the 1950’s (DWR 2001).Areas unaffected by municipal water use reflect the natural groundwater table distribution and direction of movement. Year-round extraction of groundwater for municipal use in the Chico area causes several small groundwater depressions that tend to alter the natural southwesterly movement of groundwater in the area (DWR 2001). In the Chico area, groundwater levels in the unconfined portion of the aquifer system is about 5- to 7-feet during normal precipitation and up to approximately 16 feet during periods of drought. Annual fluctuation in the confined or semi- confined portion of the aquifer system is approximately 15- to 25-feet during normal years and up to approximately 30 feet during periods of drought. Long-term comparison of spring to spring groundwater levels for confined or semi-confined portions of the aquifer system indicates a 10 to 15-foot decline in groundwater levels since the 1950s.Groundwater StorageThe storage capacity of the subbasin was estimated based on estimates of specific yield for the Sacramento Valley as developed in DWR (1978). Estimates of specific yield, determined on a regional basis, were used to obtain a weighted specific yield conforming to the subbasin boundary. The estimated specific yield for the Vina Subbasin is 5.9 percent. The estimated storage capacity to a depth of 200 feet is approximately 1,468,239 acre-feet.Groundwater Budget (Type B)Estimates of groundwater extraction for the Vina Subbasin are based on surveys conducted by the California Department of Water Resources during the years 1993, 1994, and 1997. Surveys included landuse and sources of water. Estimate of groundwater extraction for agricultural use is estimated to be 130,000 acre-feet. Municipal and industrial use is approximately 20,000 acre-feet. Deep percolation of applied water is estimated to be 30,000 acre- feet.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. Calcium-magnesium bicarbonate and magnesium-calcium bicarbonate are the predominant groundwater types in the subbasin. Total dissolved solids range from 48- to 543-mg/L, averaging 285 mg/L (DWR unpublished data).Impairments. Impairments include localized high calcium and high nitrates and total dissolved solids in the Chico area.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinWater Quality in Public Supply WellsCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Constituent Group1Inorganics – Primary RadiologicalNitratesPesticidesVOCs and SVOCs Inorganics – SecondaryNumber of wells sampled2 5249 56 49 48 52Number of wells with a concentration above an MCL3 00 4 0 4 1￼￼1 A description of each member in the constituent groups anddiscussion of the relevance of these groups are included in California’s Groundwater – Bulletin 118 by DWR (2003).2 Represents distinct number of wells sampled as required under DHS Title 22 program from 1994 through 2000.3 Each well reported with a concentration above an MCL was confirmed with a second detection above an MCL. This information is intended as an indicator of the types of activities that cause contamination in a given basin. It represents the water quality at the sample location. It does not indicate the water quality delivered to the consumer. More detailed drinking water quality information can be obtained from the local water purveyor and its annual Consumer Confidence Report.Well CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)a generalized￼Municipal/IrrigationDomesticMunicipal/IrrigationAverage: 1212 (22 Well Completion Reports)Average: 139 (2215 Well Completion Reports)Average: 330 (715 Well Completion Reports)Number of wells /measurement frequency 23 wells semi-annually5 wells biennially 69Active Monitoring DataRange: 50 – 3850Total depths (ft)Range: 14 – 754Range: 36 –1000￼￼AgencyDWR DWRDepartment of Health ServicesParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water qualityMiscellaneous water quality￼Last update 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinBasin ManagementGroundwater management: Butte County adopted a groundwater management ordinance in 1996.Tehama County adopted a groundwater management ordinance in 1994.Water agenciesPublic Butte Basin Water User Association, Deer Creek ID, Stanford Vina Ranch ID, City of Chico, Tehama County Flood Control andCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼PrivateSelected ReferencesConservation District￼￼California Department of Water Resources. 1978. Evaluation of Groundwater Resources: Sacramento Valley. Department of Water Resources in cooperation with the United States Geological Survey. Appendix A. Bulletin 118-6.California Department of Water Resources. 2000. Geology and Hydrogeology of the Freshwater Bearing Aquifer Systems of the Northern Sacramento Valley, California. In Progress.California Department of Water Resources. 2001. Butte County Groundwater Inventory Analysis. Draft Report. Northern District.Helley EJ, Harwood DS. 1985. Geologic Map of the Late Cenozoic Deposits of the Sacramento Valley and Northern Sierran Foothills, California. USGS Map MF-1790.United States Bureau of Reclamation (USBR), 1960. Tehama-Colusa Service Area Geology and Groundwater Resources Appendix.BibliographyBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.Berkstressor CF. 1973. Base of Fresh Water in the Sacramento Valley and Sacramento-San Joaquin Delta, California. U.S. Geological Survey in Cooperation with California Department of Water Resources.Bertoldi GT, Johnson RH, Evenson KD. 1991. Groundwater in the Central Valley, California - - A Summary Report. Regional Aquifer System Analysis--Central Valley, California. USGS. Professional Paper 1401-A.Beyer LA. 1993. Sacramento Basin Province. USGS.Bryan K. 1923. Geology and Ground-water Resources of Sacramento Valley, California. USGS. 495.California Department of Pesticide Regulation. 1993. Sampling for Pesticide Residues in California Well Water, 1993 Well Inventory Database. California Environmental Protection Agency.California Department of Water Resources. 1958. Ground Water Conditions in Central and Northern California 1957-58. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 77-58.California Department of Water Resources. 1960. Northeastern Counties Investigation. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 58.California Department of Water Resources. 1964. Groundwater Conditions in Central and Northern California, 1961-62. California Department of Water Resources.California Department of Water Resources. 1964. Quality of Ground Water in California 1961-62, Part 1: Northern and Central California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 66-62.Last update 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinCalifornia Department of Water Resources. 1966. Precipitation in the Central Valley. Coordinated Statewide Planning Program. California Department of Water Resources, Sacramento District. Office Report.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. Progress Report Sacramento And Redding Basins Groundwater Study. California Department of Water Resources, Northern and Central Districts, in cooperation with the U.S. Geological Survey. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.California Department of Water Resources. 1987. Progress Report Sacramento and Redding Basins Ground Water Study. California Department of Water Resources, Northern and Central Districts, in cooperation with the U.S. Geological Survey.California Department of Water Resources. 1993. Ground Water Levels in the Sacramento Valley Ground Water Basin; Tehama County. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District.California Department of Water Resources. 1995. Sacramento Valley Groundwater Quality Investigation. California Department of Water Resouces, Northern District.California Department of Water Resources. 1998. California Water Plan Update. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 160-98, Volumes 1 and 2.Cherven VB, Edmondson WF. 1992. Structural Geology of the Sacramento Basin: Annual Meeting, Pacific Section AAPG, Sacramento, California, April 27, 1992-May 2,1992.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Fogelman RP. 1976. Descriptions and Chemical Analysis for Selected Wells in the Central Sacramento Valley, California. USGS. OF-76-472.Fogelman RP. 1982. Dissolved-solids Concentrations of Groundwater in the Sacramento Valley, California. USGS. HA-645.Fogelman RP. 1983. Ground Water Quality in the Sacramento Valley, California, Water Types and Potential Nitrate and Boron Problem Areas. USGS. HA-651.Fogelman RP, Rockwell GL. 1977. Descriptions and Chemical Analysis for Selected Wells in the Eastern Sacramento Valley, California. USGS. OF-77-486.Fogelman RP. 1978. Chemical Quality of Ground Water in the Central Sacramento Valley, California. USGS. Water Resources Investigations 77-133.Fogleman RP. 1979. Chemical Quality of Ground Water in the Eastern Sacramento Valley, California. USGS.Harwood DS, Helley EJ. 1982. Preliminary Structure Contour Map of the Sacramento Valley, California, Showing Major Late Cenozoic Structural Features and Depth to Basement. USGS.Harwood DS, Helley EJ. 1987. Late Cenozoic Tectonism of the Sacramento Valley. USGS.Harwood DS, Helley EJ, Doukas MP. 1981. Geologic Map of the Chico Monocline and Northeastern Part of the Sacramento Valley, California. USGS.Hawkins FF, Anderson l. 1985. Late Quaternary Tectonics of Part of the Northern Sierra Nevada, California. Geological Society of America.Hull LC. 1984. Geochemistry of Groundwater in the Sacramento Valley, California. Central Valley of California RASA Project. USGS. Professional Paper 1401-B.Lydon PA. 1969. Geology and Lahars of the Tuscan Formation, Northern California. The Geological Society of America.Mankinen EA. 1978. Paleomagnetic Evidence for a Late Cretaceous Deformation of the Great Valley Sequence, Sacramento Valley, California. USGS.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinMitten HT. 1972. Estimated Ground-water Pumpage in the Northern Part of the Sacramento Valley, California,1966-69. USGS.Mitten HT. 1973. Estimated Ground-water Pumpage in the Northern Part of the Sacramento Valley, California, 1970-71. USGS.Olmsted FH, Davis GH. 1961. Geologic Features and Ground Water Storage Capacity of the Sacramento Valley, California. USGS. Water Supply Paper 1497.Page RW. 1974. Base and Thickness of the Post-Eocene Continental Deposits in the Sacramento Valley, California. U.S. Geological Survey in cooperation with California Department of Water Resources. Water Resources Investigations 45-73.Page RW. 1986. Geology of the Fresh Groundwater Basin of the Central Valley, California, with Texture Maps and Sections. Regional Aquifer System Analysis. USGS. Professional Paper 1401-C.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.Poland JF, Evenson RE. 1966. Hydrogeology and Land Subsidence, Great Central Valley, California, Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. 239-247 p.Russell RD. 1931. The Tehama Formation of Northern California [Ph.D]: University of California.Saucedo GJ, Wagner DL. 1992. Geologic Map of the Chico Quadrangle, California. California Division of Mines and Geology.USGS. 1981. Water Resources Data for California; Volume 4, Northern Central Valley Basins and the Great Basin from Honey Lake Basin to Oregon State Line. USGS.Williamson AK, Prudic DE, Swain LA. 1985. Groundwater Flow in the Central Valley, California. USGS. OF-85-345.Williamson AK, Prudic DE, Swain LA. 1989. Groundwater Flow in the Central Valley, California. Regional Aquifer-System Analysis--Central Valley, California. USGS. Professional Paper 1401-D.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04