Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinSacramento Valley Groundwater Basin, Los Molinos Subbasin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-21.56• County: Tehama, Butte• Surface Area: 33,170 acres (52 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Los Molinos Subbasin comprises the portion of the Sacramento Valley groundwater basin bounded on the west by the Sacramento River, on the north by Mill Creek, on the east by the Chico Monocline, and on the south by Deer Creek. Mill Creek and Deer Creek serve as hydrologic boundaries in the near surface. The subbasin is hydrologically contiguous with Dye Creek and Vina subbasins at depth. The Chico Monocline serves as a geographical boundary with some areas of recharge located east of the boundary. Annual precipitation is approximately 18-inches.Water-Bearing FormationsThe aquifer system of the subbasin is comprised of continental deposits of late Quaternary to Tertiary age. The Quaternary deposits include Holocene stream channel deposits, Pleistocene Modesto Formation terrace deposits located along most stream and river channels, and Pleistocene fanglomerate deposits from the Cascade Range. The Tertiary deposits include the Tuscan Formation.Holocene Stream Channel Deposits. The western edge of the subbasin is bounded by Holocene stream channel deposits of the Sacramento River. These deposits consist of moderately to highly permeable unconsolidated gravel, sand, silt and clay derived from the erosion, reworking, and deposition of the adjacent Tuscan and Tehama formations (DWR 2000). The thickness varies from 1- to 80-feet (Helley and Harwood 1985). The unit represents the upper part of the unconfined zone of the aquifer and is moderately-to-highly permeable; however, the thickness and areal extent of the deposits limit the water-bearing capability.Pleistocene Modesto Formation. Pleistocene Modesto Formation deposits (deposited between 14,000 and 42,000 years ago) extend from Mill Creek to Deer Creek on the west side of the subbasin and along the courses of Mill Creek, Deer Creek, and Thomes Creek. The formation consists of undifferentiated terrace deposits of unconsolidated weathered and unweathered gravel, sand, silt and clay. Thickness of the unit can range from 0- to 150-feet (DWR 2000).Pleistocene Fanglomerate. Along with the Modesto Formation, the fanglomerate is a primary surficial deposit in the subbasin. The formation is an alluvial fan deposit derived from erosion and deposition of volcanic material from mudflows of the Tuscan Formation and consists of polylithic volcanic clasts set in a weathered tuffaceous matix. The fan deposits are poorly sorted and somewhat indurated to well cemented. The fanglomerate is being dissected by Mill Creek and Deer Creek. Thickness of the deposit isCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater Basinup to 150 feet (Ely 1994). The fanglomerate is not sufficiently thick to produce large quantities of groundwater (Olmsted and Davis 1961). Pliocene Tuscan Formation. The Tuscan Formation is the primary source of groundwater in the subbasin. The formation is composed of a series of volcanic mudflows, tuff breccia, tuffaceous sandstone and volcanic ash layers. The formation is described as four separate but lithologically similar units, A through D (with Unit A being the oldest), which in some areas are separated by layers of thin tuff or ash units (Helley and Harwood 1985). Units A, B, and C are found within the subbasin and extend in the subsurface west of the Sacramento River (DWR 2000).Unit A is the oldest water bearing unit of the formation and is characterized by the presence of metamorphic clasts within interbedded lahars, volcanic conglomerate, volcanic sandstone and siltstone. Unit B is composed of fairly equal distribution of lahars, tuffaceous sandstone, and conglomerate. Unit C consists of massive mudflow or lahar deposits with some interbedded volcanic conglomerate and sandstone. In the subsurface, these low permeability lahars form thick confining layers for groundwater contained in the more permeable sediments of Unit B.The Tuscan Formation reaches a thickness of 1,500 feet over older sedimentary deposits (DWR 2000). The dip of the formation averages approximately 2.5 degrees, east of the valley, and steepens sharply to 10- to 20-degrees southwestward towards the valley at the Chico Monocline (Olmsted and Davis 1961). The formation flattens beneath valley sediments.Groundwater Level TrendsReview of the hydrographs for long-term comparison of spring-spring groundwater levels indicates a slight decline associated with the 1976-77 and 1987-94 droughts, followed by a recovery to pre-drought conditions of the early 1970’s and 1980’s. Generally, groundwater level data show an average seasonal fluctuation of approximate 2 feet for normal and dry years. Overall, there does not appear to be any increasing or decreasing trends in groundwater levels.Groundwater StorageThe storage capacity of the subbasin was estimated based on estimates of specific yield for the Sacramento Valley as developed in DWR (1978). Estimates of specific yield, determined on a regional basis, were used to obtain a weighted specific yield conforming to the subbasin boundary. The estimated specific yield for the subbasin is 6.0 percent. The estimated storage capacity to a depth of 200 feet is approximately 397,740 acre-feet.Groundwater Budget (Type B)Estimates of groundwater extraction for the Los Molinos Subbasin are based on a field survey conducted by the California Department of Water Resources in 1994. Surveys included landuse and sources of water. Estimate of groundwater extraction for agricultural use is estimated to be 5,900 acre- feet. Municipal and industrial use is approximately 1,000 acre-feet. Deep percolation of applied water is estimated to be 3,000 acre-feet.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinGroundwater QualityGroundwater in Antelope, Dye Creek, Los Molinos, and Vina subbasins is characterized as calcium-magnesium bicarbonate and magnesium-calcium bicarbonate. Total dissolved solids (TDS) range from 119- to 558-mg/L, averaging 280 mg/L (DWR unpublished data).Water Quality in Public Supply WellsCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Constituent Group1Inorganics – Primary RadiologicalNitratesPesticidesVOCs and SVOCs Inorganics – SecondaryNumber of wells sampled2 66 6 4 3 6Number of wells with a concentration above an MCL3 00 0 0 0 0￼￼1 A description of each member in the constituent groups anddiscussion of the relevance of these groups are included in California’s Groundwater – Bulletin 118 by DWR (2003).2 Represents distinct number of wells sampled as required under DHS Title 22 program from 1994 through 2000.3 Each well reported with a concentration above an MCL was confirmed with a second detection above an MCL. This information is intended as an indicator of the types of activities that cause contamination in a given basin. It represents the water quality at the sample location. It does not indicate the water quality delivered to the consumer. More detailed drinking water quality information can be obtained from the local water purveyor and its annual Consumer Confidence Report.Well Production characteristics Well yields (gal/min)a generalized￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic IrrigationTotal depths (ft)Range: 31 – 340 Range: 27 – 740￼Active Monitoring DataAverage: 92 (311 Well Completion Reports) Average: 327 (42 Well Completion Reports)Number of wells /measurement frequency 3 wells semi-annually9￼AgencyDWRDepartment of Health ServicesParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water qualityLast update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinBasin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateSelected ReferencesCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼T ehama County Flood Control and Water Conservation DistrictT ehama County Flood Control and Water Conservation District, Stanford Vina Ranch ID, Los Molinos Mutual Water Co., Los Molinos Water Works￼￼California Department of Water Resources. 2000. Geology and Hydrogeology of the Freshwater Bearing Aquifer Systems of the Northern Sacramento Valley, California. In progress.Ely KE. 1994. An Evaluation of Aquifer Characteristics Within the Tuscan Formation, Northeastern Sacramento Valley, Tehama County, California. MS Thesis. (On file in Department of Water Resources, Groundwater Section, Red Bluff, CA.Helley EJ, Harwood DS. 1985. Geologic Map of the Late Cenozoic Deposits of the Sacramento Valley and Northern Sierran Foothills, California. USGS Map MF-1790.Olmsted FH, Davis GH. 1961. Geologic Features and Ground Water Storage Capacity of the Sacramento Valley, California. USGS. Water Supply Paper 1497.BibliographyBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.Berkstressor CF. 1973. Base of Fresh Water in the Sacramento Valley and Sacramento-San Joaquin Delta, California. U.S. Geological Survey in Cooperation with California Department of Water Resources.Bertoldi GT, Johnson RH, Evenson KD. 1991. Groundwater in the Central Valley, California - - A Summary Report. Regional Aquifer System Analysis--Central Valley, California. USGS. Professional Paper 1401-A.Beyer LA. 1993. Sacramento Basin Province. USGS.Bryan K. 1923. Geology and Ground-water Resources of Sacramento Valley, California. USGS. 495.California Department of Pesticide Regulation. 1993. Sampling for Pesticide Residues in California Well Water, 1993 Well Inventory Database. California Environmental Protection Agency.California Department of Water Resources. 1958. Ground Water Conditions in Central and Northern California 1957-58. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 77-58.California Department of Water Resources. 1960. Northeastern Counties Investigation. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 58.California Department of Water Resources. 1964. Groundwater Conditions in Central and Northern California,1961-62. California Department of Water Resources.California Department of Water Resources. 1964. Quality of Ground Water in California 1961-62, Part 1: Northern and Central California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 66-62.California Department of Water Resources. 1966. Precipitation in the Central Valley. Coordinated Statewide Planning Program. California Department of Water Resources, Sacramento District. Office Report.Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinCalifornia Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. Progress Report Sacramento And Redding Basins Groundwater Study. California Department of Water Resources, Northern and Central Districts, in cooperation with the U.S. Geological Survey. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1978. Evaluation of Groundwater Resources: Sacramento Valley. Department of Water Resources in cooperation with the United States Geological Survey. Appendix A. Bulletin 118-6.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.California Department of Water Resources. 1987. Progress Report Sacramento and Redding Basins Ground Water Study. California Department of Water Resources, Northern and Central Districts, in cooperation with the U.S. Geological Survey.California Department of Water Resources. 1993. Ground Water Levels in the Sacramento Valley Ground Water Basin; Tehama County. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District.California Department of Water Resources. 1995. Sacramento Valley Groundwater Quality Investigation. California Department of Water Resouces, Northern District.California Department of Water Resources. 1998. California Water Plan Update. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 160-98, Volumes 1 and 2.Cherven VB, Edmondson WF. 1992. Structural Geology of the Sacramento Basin: Annual Meeting, Pacific Section AAPG, Sacramento, California, April 27, 1992-May 2,1992.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Fogelman RP. 1976. Descriptions and Chemical Analysis for Selected Wells in the Central Sacramento Valley, California. USGS. OF-76-472.Fogelman RP, Rockwell GL. 1977. Descriptions and Chemical Analysis for Selected Wells in the Eastern Sacramento Valley, California. USGS. OF-77-486.Fogelman RP. 1978. Chemical Quality of Ground Water in the Central Sacramento Valley, California. USGS. Water Resources Investigations 77-133.Fogleman RP. 1979. Chemical Quality of Ground Water in the Eastern Sacramento Valley, California. USGS.Fogelman RP. 1982. Dissolved-solids Concentrations of Groundwater in the Sacramento Valley, California. USGS. HA-645.Fogelman RP. 1983. Ground Water Quality in the Sacramento Valley, California, Water Types and Potential Nitrate and Boron Problem Areas. USGS. HA-651.Harwood DS, Helley EJ. 1982. Preliminary Structure Contour Map of the Sacramento Valley, California, Showing Major Late Cenozoic Structural Features and Depth to Basement. USGS.Harwood DS, Helley EJ. 1987. Late Cenozoic Tectonism of the Sacramento Valley. USGS.Harwood DS, Helley EJ, Doukas MP. 1981. Geologic Map of the Chico Monocline and Northeastern Part of the Sacramento Valley, California. USGS.Hull LC. 1984. Geochemistry of Groundwater in the Sacramento Valley, California. Central Valley of California RASA Project. USGS. Professional Paper 1401-B.Lydon PA. 1969. Geology and Lahars of the Tuscan Formation, Northern California. The Geological Society of America.Mankinen EA. 1978. Paleomagnetic Evidence for a Late Cretaceous Deformation of the Great Valley Sequence, Sacramento Valley, California. USGS.Mitten HT. 1972. Estimated Ground-water Pumpage in the Northern Part of the Sacramento Valley, California,1966-69. USGS.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Sacramento Valley Groundwater BasinMitten HT. 1973. Estimated Ground-water Pumpage in the Northern Part of the Sacramento Valley, California, 1970-71. USGS.Page RW. 1974. Base and Thickness of the Post-Eocene Continental Deposits in the Sacramento Valley, California. U.S. Geological Survey in cooperation with California Department of Water Resources. Water Resources Investigations 45-73.Page RW. 1986. Geology of the Fresh Groundwater Basin of the Central Valley, California, with Texture Maps and Sections. Regional Aquifer System Analysis. USGS. Professional Paper 1401-C.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.Poland JF, Evenson RE. 1966. Hydrogeology and Land Subsidence, Great Central Valley, California, Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. 239-247 p.Russell RD. 1931. The Tehama Formation of Northern California [Ph.D]: University of California.Steele WC. 1980. Quaternary Stream Terraces in the Northwestern Sacramento Valley, Glenn, Tehama, and Shasta Counties, California. USGS.Tehama County Flood Control and Water Conservation District. 1996. Coordinated AB 3030 Groundwater Management Plan. Tehama County Flood Control and Water Conservation District.Tehama County Flood Control and Water Conservation District. 1999. Coordinated AB 3030 Groundwater Management Plan, First Annual Report. Tehama County Flood Control and Water Conservation District.US Geological Survey. 1981. Water Resources Data for California. Volume 4, Northern Central Valley Basins and the Great Basin from Honey Lake Basin to Oregon State Line. USGS.Williamson AK, Prudic DE, Swain LA. 1985. Groundwater Flow in the Central Valley, California. USGS. OF-85-345.Williamson AK, Prudic DE, Swain LA. 1989. Groundwater Flow in the Central Valley, California. Regional Aquifer-System Analysis--Central Valley, California. USGS. Professional Paper 1401-D.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04