Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Lower Lake Groundwater BasinLower Lake Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-30• County: Lake• Surface Area: 2,400 acres (4 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyLower Lake Basin is located at the southeast end of Clear Lake and includes the alluvial plains of Cache, Herndon, and Seigler Canyon Creeks. Copsey Creek also drains to Cache Creek from Excelsior Valley located to the south. The basin is bounded on the south by Plio-Pleistocene Cache Formation, Tertiary bedrock, and rocks of the Great Valley Sequence; on the north by the Cache Formation and Quaternary volcanics; and on the east by Tertiary rock of the Martinez and Tejon formations. Surficial Cache Formation and Martinez Formation deposits are located within the middle third of the basin north and northeast of the city of Lower Lake. Annual precipitation in the basin is approximately 27 inches.Hydrogeologic InformationWater-Bearing FormationsThe aquifer system of Lower Lake Basin is primarily composed of deposits of Quaternary alluvium and the Plio-Pleistocene Cache Formation (Upson 1955).Quaternary Alluvium. Alluvial deposits in the basin are approximately 50- to 75-feet thick and consists of clay, silt, and sand, with some gravel (DWR 1976). Irrigation wells constructed in the vicinity of alluvial deposits yield between 400- and 600-gpm with little drawdowns (Upson 1955). The alluvial plain of Herndon Creek likely consists of clay, clay and gravel, and some interbedded gravel stringers or layers. Wells installed to depths of approximately 75 feet yield up to 250 gpm with about 40 feet of drawdown (Upson 1955).Plio-Pleistocene Cache Formation. The Cache Formation is primarily composed of gravel, silt, and sand with the upper most sediments consisting of water-laid tuffs and tuffaceous sands intercalated with clay, marl, pebbly limestone, and diatomite (DOM 1953). The formation underlies younger alluvial deposits over a region of approximately two-thirds of the basin. The permeability in the formation is variable but generally low. Most of the strata are too high in clay or silt. Depth of the formation is unknown. Well yields are reported to range between 150 and 240 gallons per minute (Upson 1955).Recharge AreasGroundwater recharge is derived from precipitation and from seepage from Herndon Creek and Clear Lake (Upson 1955). Recharge also likely occurs from Copsey and Seigler Canyon creeks. Recharge of groundwater in the Cache formation is likely derived from the infiltration of rain that falls on the outcrop area (Upson 1955).California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Lower Lake Groundwater BasinGroundwater Level TrendsAnalysis Incomplete.Groundwater StorageStorage capacity is estimated to range from 3,000 to 4,000 acre-feet (Upson 1955). Additional storage capacity is available as part of the Cache Formation; however, thickness and specific yield of that formation is unknown.Groundwater Budget (Type B)Estimates of groundwater extraction for Lower Lake Basin are based on a survey conducted by the California Department of Water Resources in 1995. The survey included landuse and sources of water. Estimates of groundwater extraction for agricultural and municipal/industrial uses are 78 and 210 acre- feet respectively. Deep percolation from applied water is estimated to be 33 acre-feet.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. Bicarbonate type waters with mixed cationic character are found in the basin. Total dissolved solids (TDS) concentrations range from 290- to-1,230 mg/L, averaging 568 mg/L (DWR unpublished data).Impairments. Groundwater in the basin has localized high iron, manganese, calcium, sodium, ASAR, sulfate, and TDS. High boron concentrations may be an issue for irrigation.Water Quality in Public Supply WellsCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Constituent Group1Inorganics – Primary RadiologicalNitratesPesticidesVOCs and SVOCs Inorganics – SecondaryNumber of wells sampled2 31 5 1 0 3Number of wells with a concentration above an MCL3 00 0 0 0 2￼￼1 A description of each member in the constituent groups anddiscussion of the relevance of these groups are included in California’s Groundwater – Bulletin 118 by DWR (2003).2 Represents distinct number of wells sampled as required under DHS Title 22 program from 1994 through 2000.3 Each well reported with a concentration above an MCL was confirmed with a second detection above an MCL. This information is intended as an indicator of the types of activities that cause contamination in a given basin. It represents the water quality at the sample location. It does not indicate the water quality delivered to the consumer. More detailed drinking water quality information can be obtained from the local water purveyor and its annual Consumer Confidence Report.Last update 2/27/04a generalized
Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Lower Lake Groundwater BasinWell CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationRange: 3 – 100Total depths (ft)Range: 22 - 230 Range: 26 - 340￼Active Monitoring DataAverage: 37 (9 Well Completion Reports)Average: 78 (86 Well Completion Reports)Average: 113 (17 Well Completion Reports)Number of wells /measurement frequency 3 wells semiannually5 wells biennially￼AgencyDWRDepartment of Health ServicesParameterMiscellaneous water qualityMiscellaneous water qualityBasin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateReferences CitedLake County adopted a groundwater management ordinance in 1999.Highlands Mutual Water Company￼￼California Department of Water Resources (DWR). September 1976. Southwestern Sacramento Valley Ground Water Investigation. Draft Northern District Memorandum Report.California Division of Mines (DOM). (1953). Geology of Lower Lake Quadrangle, California. Bulletin 166.Upson JE., Kunkel F. 1955. Ground Water of the Lower Lake-MiddletownArea, Lake County, CA. USGS Water-Supply Paper 1297.Additional ReferencesBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1957. Lake County Investigation. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 14.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.California Department of Water Resources. 1998. California Water Plan Update. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 160-98, Volumes 1 and 2.Charpier Martin and Associates. 1987. Middletown Groundwater Recharge Enhancement Investigation for Lake County Flood Control and Water Conservation District.Last update 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Lower Lake Groundwater BasinDickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.McNitt JR. 1968. Geology of the Kelseyville Quadrangle, Sonoma, Lake and Mendocino Counties. California Divisions of Mines and Geology. Map Sheet 9.Ott Water Engineers Inc. 1987. Lake County Resource Management Plan Update. Lake County Flood Control and Water Conservation District.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.United States Bureau of Reclamation Mid Pacific Region. 1976. Four Counties Study, Appraisal Ground-water Geology and Resources Appendix for Yolo, Lake, and Napa Counties. United States Bureau of Reclamation Mid Pacific Region.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04