Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Egg Lake Valley Groundwater BasinEgg Lake Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-41• County: Modoc• Surface Area: 4,100 acres (6 square miles)Basin Boundary and HydrologyThe Egg Lake Valley Groundwater Basin is bounded to the south by Tertiary volcanics of Egg Lake Butte, to the east by Recent basalt, and on all other sides by Miocene basalt. The basin consists of Quaternary lake deposits (Gay 1968). Annual precipitation ranges from 19- to 21-inches.Hydrogeologic InformationHydrogeologic information was not available for the following:Water-Bearing Formations Groundwater Level Trends Groundwater Storage Groundwater BudgetGroundwater QualityWater Quality in Public Supply WellsCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Constituent Group1Inorganics – Primary RadiologicalNitratesPesticidesVOCs and SVOCs Inorganics – SecondaryNumber of wells sampled2 60 7 2 2 6Number of wells with a concentration above an MCL3 00 0 0 0 0￼￼1 A description of each member in the constituent groups anddiscussion of the relevance of these groups are included in California’s Groundwater – Bulletin 118 by DWR (2003).2 Represents distinct number of wells sampled as required under DHS Title 22 program from 1994 through 2000.3 Each well reported with a concentration above an MCL was confirmed with a second detection above an MCL. This information is intended as an indicator of the types of activities that cause contamination in a given basin. It represents the water quality at the sample location. It does not indicate the water quality delivered to the consumer. More detailed drinking water quality information can be obtained from the local water purveyor and its annual Consumer Confidence Report.Last update 2/27/04a generalized
Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Egg Lake Valley Groundwater BasinWell CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/Irrigation20 (1 Well Completion Report)Total depths (ft)300 (1 Well Completion Report)440 (1 Well Completion Report)￼Active Monitoring Data Agency ParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneouswater quality NKD – No Known DataBasin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateSelected ReferenceNumber of wells /measurement frequency NKDNKD￼￼The County of Modoc adopted a Groundwater Management Ordinance in 2000.None None￼Gay TE, Jr., Aune QA. 1968. Geologic Map of California, [Alturas Sheet]. California Division of Mines and Geology. Atlas.BibliographyBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.Last update 2/27/04