Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Cayton Valley Groundwater BasinCayton Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-45• County: Siskiyou• Surface Area: 1,300 acres (2 square miles)Basin Boundary and HydrologyThe Cayton Valley Groundwater Basin is a northeast trending basin located west of Fall River Valley and north of Lake Britton. The basin is bounded to the east by several northwest trending faults and Pliocene andesitic rocks of Soldier and Fort Mountains. The basin is bounded to the north and west by Miocene basalt and to the south by Quaternary pyroclastic rocks (Gay 1958). Annual precipitation ranges from 35- to 41-inches, increasing to the northwest.Hydrogeologic InformationHydrogeologic information was not available for the following:Water-Bearing Formations Groundwater Level Trends Groundwater StorageGroundwater Budget (Type B)The estimate of groundwater extraction is based on a 1995 survey conducted by the California Department of Water Resources. The survey included land use and sources of water. Groundwater extraction for municipal and industrial use is estimated to be 1 acre-foot. Deep percolation of applied water is estimated to be 210 acre-feet.Groundwater QualityWell CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationNKD – No known DataActive Monitoring Data Agency ParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneouswater quality NKD – No Known Data400 (1 well completion report)Total depths (ft)NKD230 (1 well completion report)￼￼Last update 2/27/04Number of wells /measurement frequency NKDNKD
Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Cayton Valley Groundwater BasinCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateSelected ReferencesShasta County adopted a groundwater management ordinance in 1998.None None￼￼￼California Department of Water Resources. 1963. Northeastern Counties Groundwater Investigation, Volume 1 and Volume 2. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 98.California Department of Water Resources. 1960. Northeastern Counties Investigation. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 58.California Department of Water Resources. 1964. Shasta County Investigation. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 22.California Department of Water Resources. 1965. Northeastern Counties Ground Water Investigation, Appendix C, Geology. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. Bulletin 98.California Department of Conservation, Division of Mines and Geology. 1966. Geology of Northern California Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1968. Water Well Standards-Shasta County, California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 74-8.California Department of Water Resources. 1982. Northeastern Counties Ground Water Update. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. Office Report.California Department of Water Resources. 1984. Eastern Shasta County Ground Water Study, California Department of Water Resources, Northern District.Gay TE, Jr., Aune QA. 1958. Geologic Map of California, [Alturas Sheet]. California Division of Mines and Geology.BibliographyCalifornia Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.Last update 2/27/04