Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Lake Britton Area Groundwater BasinLake Britton Area Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-46• County: Shasta• Surface Area: 14,060 acres (22 square miles)Basin Boundary and HydrologyLake Britton Groundwater Basin is located within a west-northwest trending valley in a region of several northwest trending faults. The basin is bounded to the south by Pleistocene basalt, to the west by Tertiary andesite, and to the north by Miocene basalt and Pliocene andesite (Gay 1968, Lydon 1969). The valley is drained by the Pit River. Annual precipitation ranges from 21- to 43-inches, increasing to the east.Hydrogeologic InformationHydrogeologic information was not available for the following:Water-Bearing Formations Groundwater Level Trends Groundwater StorageGroundwater Budget (Type B)The estimate of groundwater extraction for the Lake Britton Area Basin is based on 1995 survey conducted by the California Department of Water Resources. The survey included land use and sources of water.Groundwater extraction for municipal and industrial uses is estimated to be 5 acre-feet. Deep percolation of applied water is estimated to be 10 acre-feet.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Groundwater QualityWell CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationNKD – No Known DataRange: NKDTotal depths (ft)Range: 46 – 415 Range: NKDAverage: 133 (17 Well Completion Reports)￼Last update 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Lake Britton Area Groundwater BasinActive Monitoring Data Agency ParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneouswater quality Department of MiscellaneousHealth Services water qualityNKD - No Known DataBasin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateSelected ReferencesCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Number of wells /measurement frequency NKDNKD 2￼￼Shasta County adopted a groundwater management ordinance in 1998None None￼Gay TE, Jr., Aune QA. 1968. Geologic Map of California, [Alturas Sheet]. California Division of Mines and Geology. Atlas.Lydon PA, Gay TE, Jennings CW. 1969. Geologic Atlas of California [Westwood Sheet]. California Division of Mines and Geology.BibliographyBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources Bulletin 118-80.California Department of Water Resources. 1984. Eastern Shasta County Ground Water Study, California Department of Water Resources, Northern District.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.Last update 2/27/04