Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Grays Valley Groundwater BasinGrays Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-52• County: Lassen• Surface Area: 5,440 acres (8 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Grays Valley Groundwater Basin is an alluvial filled valley located at the base of Crater Lake Mountain to the west in southwest Lassen County. The basin is bounded by Recent basalt of Crater Lake Mountain to the east. The basin is bounded on all other sides by Pleistocene basalt of Bogard Buttes, Cal Mountain, and Cone Mountain (Lydon 1960). Annual precipitation ranges from 19- to 21-inches.Hydrogeologic InformationHydrogeologic information was not available for the following:Water-Bearing Formations Groundwater Level Trends Groundwater Storage Groundwater Budget Groundwater QualityWell CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)Municipal/Irrigation NKDTotal depths (ft)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Domestic NKD Municipal/Irrigation NKDNKD – No Known DataActive Monitoring Data Agency ParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneouswater quality NKD – No Known DataNumber of wells /measurement frequency NKDNKD￼￼Last update 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region Sacramento River Grays Valley Groundwater BasinBasin ManagementGroundwater management: No known groundwater management plans, groundwater ordinances, or basinadjudications.Water agenciesPublic None Private NoneSelected ReferencesLydon PA, Gay TE, Jennings CW. 1960. Geologic Atlas of California [Westwood Sheet]. California Division of Mines and Geology.BibliographyBailey, EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.Dickinson, WR, Ingersoll, RV, Grahm, SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Planert, M, Williams, JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼￼￼Last update 2/27/04