Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Dixie Valley Groundwater BasinDixie Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-53• County: Lassen• Surface Area: 4,870 acres (8 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Dixie Valley Groundwater Basin is an elongated east/west trending alluvial basin located south of Bald Mountain and west of Madeline Plains in western Lassen County. The basin is bounded to the south by Pleistocene basalt and on all other sides by Pliocene basalt (Lydon 1960). Indian Creek flows into the valley from the east. The valley is drained by Horse Creek which flows northwest to the Pit River. Annual precipitation in the basin ranges from 17- to 19-inches.Hydrogeologic InformationHydrogeologic information was not available for the following:Water-Bearing Formations Groundwater Level Trends Groundwater StorageGroundwater Budget (Type B)The estimate of groundwater extraction for the Dixie Valley Basin is based on a 1997 survey conducted by the California Department of Water Resources. The survey included land use and sources of water.Groundwater extraction for municipal and industrial uses is estimated to be 2 acre-feet. Deep percolation of applied water is estimated to be 420 acre-feet.Groundwater QualityWell CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)Municipal/Irrigation NKDTotal depths (ft)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Domestic NKD Municipal/IrrigationNKD – No Known DataActive Monitoring Data Agency ParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneouswater quality NKD – No Known DataNumber of wells /measurement frequency NKDNKD￼￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Dixie Valley Groundwater BasinCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateSelected ReferencesNo known groundwater management plans, groundwater ordinances, or basin adjudications.None None￼￼￼Lydon PA, Gay TE, Jennings CW. 1960. Geologic Atlas of California [Westwood Sheet]. California Division of Mines and Geology.Additional ReferencesBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.Last update 2/27/04