Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Redding Groundwater BasinRedding Groundwater Basin, Anderson Subbasin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-6.03• County: Shasta• Surface Area: 98,500 acres (154 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Anderson Subbasin comprises the portion of the Redding Groundwater Basin bounded on the west and northwest by bedrock of the Klamath Mountains, on the east by the Sacramento River, and on the south by Cottonwood Creek. Annual precipitation ranges from 27- to 41-inches, increasing to the north and west.Hydrogeologic InformationWater-Bearing FormationsThe Anderson Subbasin aquifer system is comprised of continental deposits of late Tertiary to Quaternary age. The Quaternary deposits include Holocene alluvium and Pleistocene Modesto and Riverbank formations. The Tertiary deposits include Pliocene Tehama and Tuscan formations. Helly and Harwood (1985) reports that the Tehama Formation interfingers with the Tuscan Formation in the region between Interstate Highway 5 and the Sacramento River north of the city of Red Bluff. The following descriptions are from Helley and Harwood (1985) unless otherwise noted.Holocene Alluvium. The alluvium consists of unconsolidated gravel, sand, silt and clay from stream channel and floodplain deposits. These deposits are found along stream and river channels. The thickness ranges up to 30 feet. This unit represents the perched water table and the upper part of the unconfined zone of the aquifer. Although the alluvium is moderately permeable, it is not a significant contributor to groundwater usage.Pleistocene Modesto and Riverbank Formations. The Modesto and Riverbank formations consist of poorly consolidated gravel with some sand and silt deposited during the Pleistocene time. They are usually found as terrace deposits near the surface along the Sacramento River and its tributaries. Modesto Formation deposits are observed along parts of Cottonwood Creek, Dry Creek, and along the Sacramento River. Riverbank terrace deposits are observed along all major creeks. The thickness ranges up to 50 feet. These deposits are moderately to highly permeable and yield limited domestic water supplies.Pliocene Tehama Formation. The Tehama Formation consists of locally cemented silts, sand, gravel, and clay of fluviatile origin derived from the Klamath Mountains and Coast Ranges and is the principal water-bearing formation west of the Sacramento River. The formation is exposed over approximately 60 to 70 percent of the subbasin surface area. Thickness of the formation ranges from 1,000 to 4,000 feet from the northern subbasin boundary at the Sacramento River to Cottonwood Creek in the vicinity of Interstate Highway 5 (DWR 1964). Much of the deposit west of Anderson has a uniform thickness of approximately 500 feet which thins to the westernCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Redding Groundwater Basinsubbasin boundary where the Great Valley Sequence daylights. The permeability of the formation is moderate to high with yields of 100- to 1,000-gpm.Pliocene Tuscan Formation. The Tuscan Formation is thought to interfinger with the Tehama Formation between the Sacramento River to the east and Interstate Highway 5. The formation consists of volcanic gravel and tuff-breccia, fine- to coarse-grained volcanic sandstone, conglomerate, tuff, tuffaceous silt and clay predominantly derived from andesitic and basaltic source rocks. The formation is described as four separate but lithologically similar units, Units A through D (with Unit A being the oldest), which in some areas are separated by layers of thin tuff or ash units.Unit A is the oldest water-bearing unit of the formation and is characterized by the presence of metamorphic clasts within interbedded lahars, volcanic conglomerate, volcanic sandstone and siltstone. Unit B is composed of a fairly equal distribution of lahars, tuffaceous sandstone, and conglomerate. Coarse cobble to boulder conglomerate predominates the deposit in the eastern and northern parts of mapped unit. Unit C consists of several massive mudflow or lahar deposits with some interbedded volcanic conglomerate and sandstone. Unit D consists of fragmental deposits characterized by large monolithologic masses of andesite, pumice, and fragments of black obsidian in a mudstone matrix. The unit has limited areal extents and may not occur within the Redding Basin.Permeability is moderate to high with yields of 100- to 1,000-gpm except for beds of tuff-breccia which are essentially impermeable.Recharge AreasRecharge to the principal formation is mostly by infiltration of streamflows at the margins of the subbasin. Infiltration of applied water and streamflows, and direct infiltration of precipitation are the main sources of recharge into the alluvium (Pierce 1983).Groundwater Level TrendsReview of hydrographs for long-term comparison of spring-spring groundwater levels indicates a slight decline in levels associated with the 1976-77 and 1987-94 droughts, followed by a gradual recovery to pre- drought conditions of the early 1970’s and 1980’s. Generally, the seasonal fluctuation ranges from 1- to 10-feet for normal and dry years. Overall, there does not appear to be any increasing or decreasing trends in groundwater levels.Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. The storage capacity for the entire Redding Basin is estimated to be 5.5 million acre-feet for 200 feet of saturated thickness over an area of approximately 510 square miles (Pierce 1983). Specific yield data for the Anderson Subbasin aquifer system is not available to estimate storage capacity at the subbasin level.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Redding Groundwater BasinGroundwater Budget (Type B)Estimates of groundwater extraction are based on surveys conducted by the California Department of Water Resources during 1994 and 1995. Surveys included land use and sources of water. Estimates of groundwater extraction for agricultural and municipal/industrial uses are 3,000, and 20,000 acre-feet respectively. Deep percolation of applied water is estimated to be 5,700 acre-feet.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. Groundwater in the basin is characterized as magnesium- sodium bicarbonate and sodium-magnesium bicarbonate type waters. Total dissolved solids concentrations range from 109- to 320-mg/L, averaging 194 mg/L (DWR unpublished data).Impairments. Localized areas with high iron, manganese, and nitrate occur in the subbasin.Water Quality in Public Supply WellsCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Constituent Group1Inorganics – Primary RadiologicalNitratesPesticidesVOCs and SVOCs Inorganics – SecondaryNumber of wells sampled2 1931 20 13 17 19Number of wells with a concentration above an MCL3 00 0 0 0 1￼￼1 A description of each member in the constituent groups anddiscussion of the relevance of these groups are included in California’s Groundwater – Bulletin 118 by DWR (2003).2 Represents distinct number of wells sampled as required under DHS Title 22 program from 1994 through 2000.3 Each well reported with a concentration above an MCL was confirmed with a second detection above an MCL. This information is intended as an indicator of the types of activities that cause contamination in a given basin. It represents the water quality at the sample location. It does not indicate the water quality delivered to the consumer. More detailed drinking water quality information can be obtained from the local water purveyor and its annual Consumer Confidence Report.Well CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)IrrigationDomestic IrrigationRange: 0 – 1800Total depths (ft)Range: 11 – 805 Range: 32 – 558Average: 46 (40 Well Completion Reports)Average: 140 (2239 Well Completion Reports)Average: 302 (48 Well Completion Reports)a generalized￼￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Redding Groundwater BasinActive Monitoring DataCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼AgencyDWR DWRDepartment of Health ServicesParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous Water Quality Miscellaneous Water QualityNumber of wells /measurement frequency 11 wells semi-annually6 69￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateReferences CitedShasta County adopted a groundwater management ordinance in 1998.Redding Area Water Committee, Anderson- Cottonwood ID, Clear Creek ID, City of Anderson, Keswick Community Service District, City of Redding, Rio Alto WD, Shasta Community Service District and Shasta County Water Agency, IGO-ONO C.S.D.￼￼California Department of Water Resources. 1964. Shasta County Investigation. Appendixes E through P. Bulletin 22.Helley EJ, Harwood DS. 1985. Geologic Map of the Late Cenozoic Deposits of the Sacramento Valley and Northern Sierran Foothills, California. USGS Map MF-1790.Pierce MJ. 1983. Ground Water in the Redding Basin Shasta and Tehama Counties California. USGS Water-Resources Investigations Report 83-4052.Additional ReferencesBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1964. Quality of Ground Water in California 1961-62, Part 1: Northern and Central California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 66-62.California Department of Water Resources. 1964. Shasta County Investigation. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 22.California Department of Water Resources. 1965. Upper Sacramento River Basin Investigation. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 150.California Department of Water Resources. 1966. Precipitation in the Central Valley. Coordinated Statewide Planning Program. California Department of Water Resources, Sacramento District. Office Report.California Department of Water Resources. 1968. Water Well Standards-Shasta County, California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 74-8.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. Progress Report Sacramento and Redding Basins Groundwater Study. California Department of Water Resources, Northern and Central Districts, in cooperation with the U.S. Geological Survey. Bulletin 118.Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Redding Groundwater BasinCalifornia Department of Water Resources. 1978. Evaluation of Groundwater Resources: Sacramento Valley. Department of Water Resources in cooperation with the United States Geological Survey. Appendix A. Bulletin 118-6.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.California Department of Water Resources. 1987. Progress Report Sacramento and Redding Basins Ground Water Study. California Department of Water Resources, Northern and Central Districts, in cooperation with the U.S. Geological Survey.California Department of Water Resources. 1995. Sacramento Valley Groundwater Quality Investigation. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District.California Department of Water Resources. 1996. Groundwater Levels in the Redding Groundwater Basin. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District.California Department of Water Resources. 1998. California Water Plan Update. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 160-98 Volumes 1 and 2.CH2M Hill. 1975. Redding Regional Water Supply Alternatives for Shasta County Water Agency, City of Redding, Enterprise Public Utility District, Cascade Community Services District, and Bella Vista Water District. Engineering Report.CH2M Hill. 2001. Redding Basin Water Resources Management Plan, Phase 2B Report, Prepared for Redding Area Water Council.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Diller JA. 1906. Description of the Redding Quadrangle (California). USGS. Report No. 138. 14 p.Evenson KD, Kinsey WB. 1985. Maps Showing Ground-Water Conditions in the Cottonwood Creek Area, Shasta and Tehama Counties, California, 1983-84. USGS. WRI 85-4184.Fogelman RP, Evenson KD. 1984. Water Resources Monitoring in the Cottonwood Creek Area, Shasta and Tehama Counties, California, 1982-1983. USGS. Water Resources Investigations 84-4187.Fraticelli LA, Albers JP, Irwin WP, Blake MC. 1987. Geologic Map of the Redding 1 x 2 Degree Quadrangle, Shasta, Tehama, Humboldt, and Trintity Counties, California. USGS. OF-87-257.Helley EJ, Jaworowski C. 1985. The Red Bluff Pediment; A Datum Plane for Locating Quaternary Structures in the Sacramento Valley, California. USGS.Hinds NEA. 1933. Geologic Formations of the Redding and Weaverville Districts, Northern California. California Journal of Mines and Geology 29(1):76-122.Ingersoll RV, Rich EI, Dickerson WR. 1977. Field Guide: Great Valley Sequence, Sacramento Valley.Johnson MJ, Houston ER, Neil JM. 1989. Test Holes for Monitoring Surface Water/Groundwater Relations in the Cottonwood Creek Area, Shasta and Tehama Counties, California. USGS. WRI 88-4090.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.Steele WC. 1980. Quaternary Stream Terraces in the Northwestern Sacramento Valley, Glenn, Tehama, and Shasta Counties, California. USGS.Strand RG. 1963. Geologic Atlas of California [Redding Sheet]. California Division of Mines and Geology.United States Army Corps of Engineers Sacramento District. 1978. Flood Hazard Information: Sacramento River and Cottonwood and Battle Creeks, Cottonwood-Bend Area, California. Sacramento, Calif.: United States Army Corps of Engineers Sacramento District.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region California’s Groundwater Redding Groundwater Basin Bulletin 118ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.￼Last update 2/27/04