Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Bear Valley Groundwater BasinBear Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-64• County: Colusa• Surface Area: 9,100 acres (14 square miles)Basin Boundary and HydrologyThe Bear Valley Groundwater Basin is an elongated north-south trending valley located adjacent to the Stony Creek Fault. The basin consists of Quaternary alluvium bounded by Mesozoic lower Cretaceous marine sedimentary rocks and the Knoxville Formation (Jennings 1960). The basin is drained to the south by Bear Creek. Annual precipitation ranges from 21- to 23-inches.Hydrogeologic InformationHydrologic information was not available for the following:Water-Bearing Formations Groundwater Level Trends Groundwater StorageGroundwater Budget (Type B)The estimate of the groundwater budget for Bear Valley Basin is based on a 1993 survey conducted by the California Department of Water Resources. The survey included land use and sources of water. No estimate was made for groundwater extraction. Deep percolation of applied water is estimated to be 12 acre-feet.Groundwater QualityWell CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)Municipal/Irrigation NKDTotal depths (ft)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Domestic NKD Municipal/IrrigationNKD – No Known DataActive Monitoring Data Agency ParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneouswater quality NKD – No Known DataNumber of wells /measurement frequency NKDNKD￼￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Bear Valley Groundwater BasinCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateSelected ReferencesColusa County adopted a groundwater management ordinance in 1998.None None￼￼￼Jennings CW, Strand RG. 1960. Geologic Map of California [Ukiah Sheet]. California Division of Mines and Geology.BibliographyBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Graham SA, Lowe DR, editors. 1993. Advances in Sedimentary Geology of the Great Valley Group, Sacramento Valley, California.Ingersoll RV, Rich EI, Dickerson WR. 1977. Field Guide: Great Valley Sequence, Sacramento Valley.McLaughlin RJ, Ohlin HN, Blome CD. 1983. Tectonostratigraphic Framework of the Franciscan Assemblage and Lower Part of the Great Valley Sequence in the Geysers- Clear Lake Region, California. American Geophysical Union, Eos, Transactions.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.Last update 2/27/04