Sacramento River Hydrologic RegionMiddle Fork Feather River Groundwater BasinMiddle Fork Feather River Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-87• County: Plumas• Surface Area: 4,340 acres (7 square miles)Basin Boundary and HydrologyThe Middle Fork Feather River Groundwater Basin consists of Quaternary lake and alluvial deposits. The basin is located within a region of northwest trending faults. A fault forms a basin boundary to the east. The basin is bounded to the north and south by Pliocene and Miocene volcanic rocks and to the east and west by Paleozoic marine deposits (Burnett 1962). The alluvial deposits in the basin are largely located along the North Fork Feather River which drains the basin to the southwest. Annual precipitation ranges from 39 to 47-inches, increasing to the west.Hydrogeologic InformationHydrogeologic information was not available for the following:Water-Bearing Formations Groundwater Level Trends Groundwater StorageGroundwater Budget (Type B)The estimate of groundwater extraction is based on a 1997 survey conducted by the California Department of Water Resources. The survey included land use and sources of water. Groundwater extraction for municipal/industrial use is estimated to be 4 acre-feet. Deep percolation of applied water is estimated to be 34 acre-feet.Groundwater QualityWater Quality in Public Supply WellsCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Constituent Group1Inorganics – Primary RadiologicalNitratesPesticidesVOCs and SVOCs Inorganics – SecondaryNumber of wells sampled2 20 3 0 0 2Number of wells with a concentration above an MCL3 00 0 0 0 0￼￼1 A description of each member in the constituent groups anddiscussion of the relevance of these groups are included in California’s Groundwater – Bulletin 118 by DWR (2003).2 Represents distinct number of wells sampled as required under DHS Title 22 program from 1994 through 2000.3 Each well reported with a concentration above an MCL was confirmed with a second detection above an MCL. This information is intended as an indicator of the types of activities that cause contamination in a given basin. It represents the water quality at the sample location. It does not indicate the water quality delivered to theLast update 2/27/04a generalized
Sacramento River Hydrologic RegionMiddle Fork Feather River Groundwater Basinconsumer. More detailed drinking water quality information can be obtained from the local water purveyor and its annual Consumer Confidence Report.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Well CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationNKD – No known dataNKDTotal depths (ft)Range: 23 – 400 NKD￼Active Monitoring Data Agency ParameterAverage 150Number of wells /measurement frequency NKDNKD￼Groundwater levelsMiscellaneous water quality￼NKD – No known dataBasin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateSelected ReferencesNo known groundwater management plans, groundwater ordinances, or basin adjudicationsNone None￼￼Burnett, J. L. and C. W. Jennings (1962). Geologic Map of California [Chico Sheet], California Division of Mines and Geology.California Department of Water Resources. 1963. Northeastern Counties Groundwater Investigation, Volume 1 and Volume 2. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 98.California Department of Water Resources. 1960. Northeastern Counties Investigation. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 58.California Department of Water Resources. 1965. Northeastern Counties Ground Water Investigation, Appendix C, Geology. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. Bulletin 98.California Department of Conservation, Division of Mines and Geology. 1966. Geology of Northern California Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1982. Northeastern Counties Ground Water Update. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. Office Report.Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic RegionMiddle Fork Feather River Groundwater BasinBibliographyCalifornia Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04