Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Antelope Creek Groundwater BasinAntelope Creek Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-91• County: Colusa• Surface Area: 2,040 acres (3 square miles)Basin Boundary and HydrologyThe Antelope Creek Groundwater Basin is located east of Black Mountain in Antelope Valley. The basin consists of Quaternary alluvium and is bounded on all sides by Upper Cretaceous marine deposits. Several northeast trending faults may transect the valley (Jennings 1960). The basin is drained to the north by Antelope Creek. Annual precipitation is approximately 18 inches.Hydrogeologic InformationHydrologic information was not available for the following:Water-Bearing Formations Groundwater Level Trends Groundwater StorageGroundwater Budget (Type B)The estimate of groundwater extraction is based on a 1993 survey conducted by the California Department of Water Resources. The survey included land use and sources of water. Groundwater extraction for municipal/industrial use is estimated to be 2 acre-feet. Deep percolation of applied water is estimated to be 1 acre-foot.Groundwater QualityWell CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)Municipal/Irrigation NKDTotal depths (ft)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Domestic NKD Municipal/Irrigation NKDNKD – No known dataActive Monitoring Data Agency ParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneouswater quality NKD – No Known DataNumber of wells /measurement frequency NKDNKD￼￼Last update 2/29/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic Region Antelope Creek Groundwater BasinCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateSelected ReferencesColusa County adopted a groundwater management ordinance in 1998.None None￼￼￼Jennings CW, Strand RG. 1960. Geologic Map of California [Ukiah Sheet]. California Division of Mines and Geology.BibliographyBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Ingersoll RV, Rich EI, Dickerson WR. 1977. Field Guide: Great Valley Sequence, Sacramento Valley.McLaughlin RJ, Ohlin HN, Blome CD. 1983. Tectonostratigraphic Framework of the Franciscan Assemblage and Lower Part of the Great Valley Sequence in the Geysers- Clear Lake Region, California. American Geophysical Union, Eos, Transactions.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.Last update 2/29/04