Sacramento River Hydrologic RegionNorth Fork Cache Creek Groundwater BasinNorth Fork Cache Creek Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 5-93• County: Lake• Surface Area: 3,470 acres (5 square miles)Basin Boundary and HydrologyThe North Fork Cache Creek Groundwater Basin is a north-south trending basin located in north Lake County consisting of Quaternary alluvium and stream terrace deposits. The basin is bounded by Mesozoic ultrabasic intrusive rocks in the north. Other sides of the basin are bounded by Franciscan Formation metasediments and Franciscan volcanic and metavolcanic rocks (Jennings 1960). The valley is drained to the south by North Fork Cache Creek. Annual precipitation ranges from 23- to 25-inches, increasing to the south.Hydrogeologic InformationHydrogeologic information was not available for the following:Water-Bearing Formations Groundwater Level Trends Groundwater Storage Groundwater Budget Groundwater QualityWell CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)Municipal/Irrigation NKDTotal depths (ft)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Domestic NKD Municipal/IrrigationNKD – No known data.Active Monitoring Data Agency ParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water qualityNumber of wells /measurement frequency NKDNKD￼￼￼Last update 2/27/04
Sacramento River Hydrologic RegionNorth Fork Cache Creek Groundwater BasinCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateSelected ReferenceLake County adopted a groundwater management ordinance in 1999.None None￼￼￼Jennings CW, Strand RG. 1960. Geologic Map of California [Ukiah Sheet]. California Division of Mines and Geology.BibliographyBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.McLaughlin RJ, Ohlin HN, Blome CD. 1983. Tectonostratigraphic Framework of the Franciscan Assemblage and Lower Part of the Great Valley Sequence in the Geysers- Clear Lake Region, California. American Geophysical Union, Eos, Transactions.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.Last update 2/27/04