Hydrologic Region South Coast Simi Valley Groundwater BasinSimi Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 4-9• County: Ventura• Surface Area: 12,100 acres (19.0 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThis groundwater basin underlies Simi Valley in southeastern Ventura County. The basin is bounded on the north and northeast by the Santa Susana Mountains and the Simi fault and on the south and southwest by the Simi Hills. Ground surface elevation of the valley ranges from 700 to 1,100 feet above sea level (CSWRB 1956). Surface runoff discharges into the Arroyo Simi and flows west to join Arroyo Los Posas. Average annual precipitation ranges from 16 to 20 inches.Hydrogeologic InformationWater Bearing FormationsThe primary water-bearing unit in this basin is alluvium. Groundwater is generally unconfined but as grain size decreases towards the western end of the basin, clay lenses in the alluvium cause localized confinement. The average specific yield for the Simi Valley Groundwater Basin is 8.6 percent (CSWRB 1956), the average well yield for the basin is 394 gpm, and the depth to water producing zones is typically 5 to 25 feet (Panaro 2000a).Pleistocene to Holocene Alluvium. The alluvium consists of gravels, sands, and clays with a maximum thickness of 730 feet (DWR 1959). The alluvium becomes shallow and constricted at the point where Arroyo Simi exits the western part of the valley (CSWRB 1956).Restrictive StructuresThe northern boundary of the basin is defined by the Simi fault, which may act as a barrier to subsurface inflow from the north.Recharge AreasPercolation of direct precipitation, inflow of minor streams, minor subsurface inflow from surrounding semi-permeable formations, and irrigation return provide recharge to the basin (Panaro 2000a).Groundwater Level TrendsGroundwater generally moves westward through the basin following the course of Arroyo Simi (DWR 1959). During periods of overdraft, the slope of the groundwater surface can reverse in the western part of the basin and groundwater may flow in an easterly direction. Hydrographs of wells in the Simi Valley Groundwater Basin show that water levels have typically remained the same or risen since 1980.Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. The storage capacity for this basin is estimated at about 180,000 af (CSWRB 1956; DWR 1975; Panaro 2000a).California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region South Coast Simi Valley Groundwater BasinThis estimate is consistent with an area of about 12,100 acres, an average thickness of about 175 feet, and an average specific yield of about 8.6 percent.Groundwater in Storage. The basin was estimated at 95 percent full in 1999, with about 172,000 af in storage (Panaro 2000a; 2000b).Groundwater Budget (Type A)Limited data are available from Ventura County for water budget information. Recharge includes underflow of about 3,900 af/year and irrigation return of 800 to 1,500 af/year (Panaro 2000a). Pumping is estimated to be less than 5,500 af/year (Panaro 2000a).Groundwater QualityCharacterization. Groundwater produced from Quaternary alluvium ranges from calcium sulfate to calcium-sodium sulfate (DWR 1959).Impairments. There are some problems with VOCs in shallower portions of the basin. Analysis of water from one public supply well shows a TDS concentration of 1,580 mg/L.Water Quality in Public Supply WellsCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Constituent Group1Inorganics – Primary RadiologicalNitratesPesticidesVOCs and SVOCs Inorganics – SecondaryNumber of wells sampled2 44 4 4 1 4Number of wells with a concentration above an MCL3 03 1 0 0 3￼￼1 A description of each member in the constituent groups anddiscussion of the relevance of these groups are included in California’s Groundwater – Bulletin 118 by DWR (2003).2 Represents distinct number of wells sampled as required under DHS Title 22 program from 1994 through 2000.3 Each well reported with a concentration above an MCL was confirmed with a second detection above an MCL. This information is intended as an indicator of the types of activities that cause contamination in a given basin. It represents the water quality at the sample location. It does not indicate the water quality delivered to the consumer. More detailed drinking water quality information can be obtained from the local water purveyor and its annual Consumer Confidence Report.Well CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationRange: Average: 394 gal/min (Panaro 2000b)Total depths (ft)Range: Average: Range: Average:a generalized￼￼Last update 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region South Coast Simi Valley Groundwater BasinActive Monitoring DataCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼AgencyCity of SimiDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsParameterGroundwater levelsTitle 22 water qualityNumber of wells /measurement frequency 13/weekly (Dubrick 2001)1￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateReferences CitedCurrently there is no formal management of the basin (Panaro 2000b).The main source of water for the District is through Calleguas Municipal Water District.Ventura County Water District No. 8 Southern California Water Company￼￼California Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1959. Water Quality and Water Quality Problems, Ventura County. Bulletin 75. 195 p._____. 1975. California’s ground water. Bulletin 118. 135 p.California State Water Resources Board (CSWRB). 1956. Ventura County Investigation.Bulletin 12. Two Volumes.Dubrick, C. City of Simi: Oral Communication with M. Stuhlman (DWR), October 2001.Panaro, D. 2000a. Fox Canyon Groundwater Management Agency: Written Communication to R.R. Davis (DWR), March 2000._____. 2000b. Fox Canyon Groundwater Management Agency: Written Communication to B.C. Moniz (DWR), December 2000.Additional ReferencesCalifornia Department of Public Works (CDPW). 1933. Ventura County Investigation. Division of Water Resources. Bulletin 46. 244 p.Jennings, C.W., and Strand, R.G. 1969. Geologic Map of California: Los Angeles Sheet, Olaf P. Jenkins Edition: California Division of Mines and Geology, scale 1:250,000, 1 sheet.California Department of Public Works (CDPW). 1933. Ventura County Investigation. Division of Water Resources. Bulletin 46, 244 p.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.Last update 2/27/04