Hydrologic Region South CoastSevem Oaks Valley Groundwater BasinSeven Oaks Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 8-8• County: San Bernardino• Surface Area: 4,080 acres (0.6 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThis basin underlies a mountain valley in the upper reach of the Santa Ana River. The basin is bounded on the east by Big Meadows Valley Groundwater Basin along the Slide Peak fault (Rogers 1967) and elsewhere by impermeable crystalline rocks of the San Bernardino Mountains. The valley is drained by the Santa Ana River and receives an average annual precipitation ranging from 24 to 36 inches.Hydrogeologic InformationWater Bearing FormationsGroundwater in the basin is found in alluvium that typically consists of clay, silt, sand, and gravel that reaches at least 50 feet thick.Restrictive StructuresThe Slide Peak and Santa Ana faults are mapped as cutting through basin materials (Rogers 1967); however, it is not known whether or not these faults impede groundwater movement.Recharge AreasRecharge is probably derived principally from percolation of precipitation and stream flow in the Santa Ana River.Groundwater Level TrendsNo information is available.Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. The total storage capacity is estimated at 14,000 af (DWR 1975).Groundwater in Storage. No information is available. Groundwater Budget (Type C)No information is available.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. No information is available. Impairments. No information is available.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region South CoastSevem Oaks Valley Groundwater BasinWell CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationRange:Total depths (ft)Range: Range:￼Active Monitoring DataAverage:Average: Average:Number of wells /measurement frequency1￼AgencyDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water quality Title 22 water quality￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management: Water agencies￼Public San Bernardino County PrivateReferences CitedCalifornia Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1975. California’s Ground Water. Bulletin 118. 135 p.Rogers, T. H. 1967. Geologic Map of California, San Bernardino Sheet. Single map sheet, scale 1:250,000.Additional ReferencesCalifornia Department of Public Works (DPW). 1934. South Coastal Basin Investigation, Ground Water Storage Capacity of Valley Fill. Bulletin 45. 279 p.ErrataSubstantive changes made to the basin description will be noted here.￼Last update 2/27/04