Hydrologic Region South CoastSan Dieguito Valley Groundwater BasinSan Dieguito Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 9-12• County: San Diego• Surface Area: 3,560 acres (5.6 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe San Dieguito Groundwater Basin underlies Osuna Valley and the lower portion of San Dieguito Valley in central coastal San Diego County. The basin is bounded by the Pacific Ocean to the west and elsewhere by nonwater-bearing parts of the La Jolla Group (Strand 1962). The San Dieguito River drains this valley west to the Pacific Ocean. Average annual precipitation ranges from 7 to 11 inches.Hydrogeologic InformationWater Bearing FormationsThe water-bearing materials that form this basin are composed of Quaternary age alluvium, which reaches 180 feet thick near the Pacific Ocean (Izbicki 1983). In addition, groundwater is produced from the La Jolla Group and Santiago Peak Volcanics beneath and adjacent to the basin (Izbicki 1983). Holocene age alluvium, which is composed of unconsolidated gravel, sand, silt, and clay, has a maximum thickness of more than 150 feet near the Pacific Ocean and an average specific yield of about 13 percent (Izbicki 1983). Groundwater in this unit is unconfined and wells yield an average of 700 gpm, but reach 1,800 gpm (Izbicki 1983).Older alluvium, likely Pleistocene in age, is composed of gravel, sand, silt, and clay that is partially cemented and weathered; wells in this unit yield as much as 75 gpm (Izbicki 1983).Recharge AreasRecharge of the alluvial aquifer is chiefly by percolation of flow in the San Dieguito River (DWR 1959). Additional sources of recharge include percolation of precipitation to the valley floor, underflow beneath Hodges Dam, and underflow through the La Jolla Group sediments (Izbicki 1983).Groundwater Level TrendsHistorically, groundwater levels have been near the ground surface with groundwater moving westward toward the ocean (Ellis and Lee 1919; DWR 1959). By 1957, pumping depressions had created an inland flow of seawater (DWR 1959). During 1979 through 1983, water levels at one well in the central part of the basin ranged from about 1 to 5 feet below ground surface.Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. The basin is estimated to have a storage capacity of 52,000 af (Izbicki 1983) and 63,000 af (DWR 1975).Groundwater in Storage. Unknown. Last update 2/27/04California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼
Hydrologic Region South CoastSan Dieguito Valley Groundwater BasinGroundwater Budget (Type A)Underflow beneath Hodges Dam is estimated to be a minimum of 15af/yr, and underflow through the La Jolla Group is about 600 af/yr (Izbicki 1983). Return from irrigation is estimated to be 160 to 210 af/yr (Izbicki 1983).Groundwater QualityCharacterization. Water pumped from alluvium in this basin is of variable character, but is sodium chloride character near the ocean (Izbicki 1983). TDS content ranges from about 500 mg/L in the norteastern part of the basin to more than 5,000 mg/L near the coast (DWR 1967, 1983)Impairments. This basin has high sulfate, chloride, and TDS concentrations that cause inferior ratings for domestic and irrigation use for most of the basin (DWR 1967).California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Well CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)￼Municipal/IrrigationRange: to 1,800 gal/minTotal depths (ft)Domestic Range: Municipal/Irrigation Range:Active Monitoring DataAverage: 700 gal/min (Izbicki 1983)Average: Average:Number of wells /measurement frequency￼￼AgencyDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsParameterGroundwater levelsTitle 22 water quality￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management: Water agenciesPublic PrivateReferences Cited￼￼California Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1959. San Dieguito River Investigation. Bulletin No. 72. 174 p.________. 1967. Ground Water Occurrence and Quality: San Diego Region. Bulletin No. 106-2. 235 p.________. 1975. California’s Ground Water. Bulletin 118. 135 p.________. 1983. San Diego Cooperative Ground Water Studies, Reclaimed Water Use PhaseI. Southern District Report. 84 p.Last update 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region South CoastSan Dieguito Valley Groundwater BasinEllis, A. J., and C. H. Lee. 1919. Geology and ground waters of the western part of San Diego County, California. U.S. Geological Survey Water Supply Paper 446. 321 p.Izbicki, John A. 1983. Evaluation of the San Dieguito, San Elijo, and San Pasqual Hydrologic Subareas for Reclaimed Water Use, San Diego County, California. U. S. Geological Survey Water-Resources Investigations Report 83-4044. 131 p.Strand, R. G. 1962. Geologic Map of California, San Diego-El Centro Sheet. Olaf P Jenkins Edition. California Division of Mines and Geology. 1 Sheet. Scale 1:250,000.Additional ReferencesCalifornia Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1973. Preliminary Evaluation of Groundwater Basins in San Dieguito Investigation. Preliminary report. 20 p.Kennedy, M. P. 1973. Bedrock Lithologies, San Diego Coastal Area, California. In Ross, A. and Dowlen, R.J., eds. Studies on the Geology and geologic hazards of the Greater San Diego Area, California. San Diego Association of Geologists and the Association of Engineering Geologists. p. 9-17.ErrataSubstantive changes made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Last update 2/27/04