Hydrologic Region Colorado River Canebrake Valley Groundwater BasinCanebrake Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 7-46• County: San Diego• Surface Area: 5,420 acres (8.5 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThis basin underlies Canebrake Valley and Inner Pasture in eastern San Diego County. The basin is bounded by nonwater-bearing crystalline rocks of the Tierra Blanca to the north and east, of the In Ko Pah Mountains to the south, and of the Sawtooth Mountains to the west. The valley is drained eastward toward Carrizo Valley by Canebrake and North Washes in the southern and central parts of the valley and by an unnamed creek in the northern part of the valley. Annual precipitation ranges from about 10 to 16 inches.Hydrogeologic InformationWater Bearing FormationsHolocene alluvium and Pleistocene age terrace and nonmarine sedimentary deposits are mapped as the surficial deposits in this valley (Rogers 1965). Water-bearing materials of this basin probably consist of alluvium composed of boulders, gravel, sand, silt, and clay.Recharge AreasRecharge to the basin is likely from percolation of runoff from the surrounding mountains through alluvial fans and stream channels.Groundwater Level TrendsUnknown.Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. Unknown.Groundwater in Storage. Unknown.Groundwater Budget (Type C)Budget information is not available.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. Rising water sampled in 1953 was sodium-calcium bicarbonate in character and had a TDS content of 709 mg/L (DPW 1954).Impairments. Unknown.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region Colorado River Canebrake Valley Groundwater BasinWell CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Municipal/IrrigationDomesticMunicipal/Irrigation Range:Active Monitoring Data Agency ParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneouswater quality Department of Title 22 waterHealth Services and quality cooperatorsBasin ManagementGroundwater management: Water agenciesPublic PrivateReferences CitedRange: 9-125 gal/minTotal depths (ft)Range: 115 – 679 ft.Average: (Well Completion Reports)Average: (Well Completion Reports) Average:Number of wells /measurement frequency￼￼￼￼￼Rogers, T. H. 1965. Geologic Map of California: Santa Ana Sheet. Olaf P. Jenkins Edition. California Department of Conservation, Division of Mines and Geology. Scale 1: 250,000.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.Last update 2/27/04