Hydrologic Region Colorado River Iron Ridge Area Groundwater BasinIron Ridge Area Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 7-50• County: San Bernardino• Surface Area: 5,250 acres (8.2 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThis groundwater basin underlies a valley in San Bernardino at the northern boundary of the Colorado Desert Region County. The basin is bounded by nonwater-bearing rocks of the Iron Ridge Mountains on all sides (Rogers 1967). The West Calico fault bounds the eastern portion of the basin. Annual average precipitation ranges from about 4 to 8 inches.Hydrogeologic InformationWater Bearing FormationsGroundwater is found in unconsolidated younger Quaternary alluvial deposits and the underlying unconsolidated to semi-consolidated older Tertiary to Quaternary alluvial deposits. Maximum depth of the valley fill is at least 400 feet (DWR 1954).Restrictive StructuresThe West Calico fault bounds the basin on the east sides (Rogers 1967); however it is unknown whether or not this fault is a barrier to groundwater movement.Recharge AreasRecharge to the basin is chiefly from the infiltration of runoff through alluvial deposits at the base of the surrounding mountains.Groundwater Level TrendsNo information available.Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. Unknown. Groundwater in Storage. Unknown.Groundwater Budget (Type C)No budget information available.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. Unknown. Impairments. Unknown.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last updated 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region Colorado River Iron Ridge Area Groundwater BasinWell CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)Municipal/Irrigation Range:Total depths (ft)Domestic Range: Municipal/Irrigation Range:Active Monitoring DataCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼￼￼AgencyDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water quality Title 22 water qualityAverage:Average: Average:Number of wells /measurement frequency￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management: Water agenciesPublic PrivateReferences Cited￼￼Rogers, T. H. 1967. Geologic Map of California, San Bernardino Sheet. Single Map Sheet, Scale 1:250,000.Additional ReferencesCalifornia Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1954. Ground Water Occurrence andQuality Colorado River Basin Region. Water Quality Investigations Report No. 4. . 1975. California’s Ground Water. Bulletin 118. 135 p.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.￼Last updated 2/27/04