Hydrologic Region Colorado River Pleasant Valley Groundwater BasinPleasant Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 7-52• County: Riverside• Surface Area: 9,670 acres (15.1 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThis basin underlies Pleasant Valley in northeastern Riverside County. The basin is bounded by nonwater-bearing rocks of the Lost Horse Mountains on the west, of the Hexie Mountains on the northeast, and of the Little San Bernardino Mountains on the south (Rogers 1965). Annual average precipitation ranges from about 8 to 10 inches.Hydrogeologic InformationWater Bearing FormationsIn this basin, groundwater is found in unconsolidated younger Quaternary alluvial deposits and the underlying unconsolidated to semi-consolidated older Tertiary to Quaternary alluvial deposits.Restrictive StructuresThe Dillon Shear and Blue Cut faults traverse the central portion of the basin (Rogers 1965; Jennings 1967); however, it is unknown whether or not these faults are barriers to groundwater movement.Recharge AreasRecharge to the basin is derived chiefly from the infiltration of runoff through alluvial deposits at the base of the surrounding mountains.Groundwater Level TrendsUnknown.Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. Unknown. Groundwater in Storage. Unknown.Groundwater Budget (Type C)No budget information available.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. Unknown. Impairments. Unknown.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last updated 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region Colorado River Pleasant Valley Groundwater BasinWell CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)Municipal/Irrigation Range:Total depths (ft)Domestic Range: Municipal/Irrigation Range:Active Monitoring DataCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼￼￼AgencyDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water quality Title 22 water qualityAverage:Average: Average:Number of wells /measurement frequency￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management: Water agenciesPublic PrivateReferences Cited￼￼Jennings, C. W. 1967. Geologic Map of California: Salton Sea Sheet. Olaf P. Jenkins Edition. California Department of Conservation, Division of Mines and Geology. Scale 1: 250,000.Rogers, T. H. 1965. Geologic Map of California, Santa Ana Sheet. Single Map Sheet, Scale 1:250,000.Additional ReferencesCalifornia Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1954. Ground Water Occurrence and Quality Colorado River Basin Region. Water Quality Investigations Report No. 4.. 1975. California’s Ground Water. Bulletin 118. 135 p. ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.￼Last updated 2/27/04