Hydrologic Region Colorado River Collins Valley Groundwater BasinCollins Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 7-55• County: Riverside, San Diego• Surface Area: 7,080 acres (11.1 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThis basin underlies Collins, Fig Tree, and Yucca Valleys in southern Riverside and northeastern San Diego Counties. The valley is bounded by nonwater-bearing rocks of the Santa Rosa Mountains to the north and east and of Elder and Palms Peaks to the west. The valley is drained by Indian and Coyote Creeks southeastward toward Borrego Valley. Annual average precipitation ranges from 8 to 12 inches.Hydrogeologic InformationWater Bearing FormationsHolocene alluvium and Pleistocene age terrace and nonmarine sedimentary deposits are mapped as the surficial deposits in this valley (Rogers 1965). Water-bearing materials of this basin probably consist of alluvium composed of boulders, gravel, sand, silt, and clay.Restrictive StructuresSplays of the Coyote Creek fault and the San Jacinto fault zone are mapped in this basin; however, it is not known whether or not these faults impede groundwater flow through the basin.Recharge AreasRecharge to the basin is likely from percolation of runoff from the surrounding mountains through alluvial fans and stream channels.Groundwater Level TrendsUnknown.Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. Unknown. Groundwater in Storage. Unknown.Groundwater Budget (Type C)Groundwater budget information is not available.Groundwater Quality Characterization. Unknown.Impairments. Unknown.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
Hydrologic Region Colorado River Collins Valley Groundwater BasinWell CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationRange: to 1,500 gal/minTotal depths (ft)Range: to 410 ft. Range: to 780 ft.￼Active Monitoring DataAverage:Average: Average:Number of wells /measurement frequency￼AgencyDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water quality Title 22 water quality￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management: Water agenciesPublic PrivateReferences Cited￼￼Rogers, T. H. 1965. Geologic Map of California: Santa Ana Sheet. Olaf P. Jenkins Edition. California Department of Conservation, Division of Mines and Geology. Scale 1: 250,000.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.Last update 2/27/04