North Lahontan Hydrologic Region Sweetwater Flat Groundwater BasinSweet water Flat Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 6-107• County: Mono• Surface Area: 4,700 acres (7 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologySweetwater Flat groundwater basin is located at the eastern base of the Sierra Nevada and straddles the California - Nevada State Line in northern Mono County. The basin rises to over 7,000 feet in the upland areas and is less than 6,200 feet in the valley. Sweetwater Flat lies generally in a north-south direction and terminates at the California - Nevada State Line. The East Walker River flows along the eastern side of Sweetwater Flat and is the confluence of many streams draining the eastern slopes of the Sierra Nevada. The East Walker River exits the basin and eventually drains into Walker Lake, Nevada. Frypan Creek and Green Creek are other important tributaries in the Sweetwater Flat groundwater basin.Average annual precipitation in the basin ranges from 12 inches to 24 inches, increasing from valley floor to the upland areas.Hydrogeologic InformationWater Bearing FormationsThe primary water-bearing formations are recent valley sediments.Recent Valley Sedimentary DepositsDue to the lack of published data the descriptions of the Sweetwater Flat groundwater basin hydrogeology is limited. The principal source of groundwater in the Sweetwater Flat groundwater basin is from basin-fill deposits. Division of Mines and Geology map, Walker Lake Sheet, indicate alluvium in the northern portions of the basin. The southeastern portion and the southern apex of the basin are primarily Pliocene volcanics and Pleistocene nonmarine.Due to lack of borehole data, descriptions of materials are not available.Groundwater Level TrendsNo published data was found for the Sweetwater Flat groundwater basin.Groundwater StorageNo published data was found for the Sweetwater Flat groundwater basinGroundwater Budget (Type C)Due to lack of groundwater budget data, inflows, including natural, applied, and artificial recharge and outflows including urban and agricultural extraction have not been included.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. No published data was found for the Sweetwater Flat basin.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
North Lahontan Hydrologic Region Sweetwater Flat Groundwater BasinImpairments. No published data was found for the Sweetwater Flat groundwater basin.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Well CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)Municipal/Irrigation Range:Total depths (ft)Domestic Range: Municipal/Irrigation Range:Active Monitoring Data￼￼￼AgencyDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water quality Title 22 water qualityAverage: UnknownAverage: Unknown Average: UnknownNumber of wells /measurement frequencyNo wells monitored at this timeNo wells monitored at this time No wells monitored at this time￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management: Water agenciesPublic PrivateReferences CitedNone identified Bridgeport Public Works￼￼Jennings, O.P. and Koenig, J.B., 1963, Geologic map of California: California Division of Mines and Geology, Geologic Map Series Walker Lake Sheet, scale 1:250,000.California Department of Water Resources, 1991, Walker River Atlas: Sacramento, Calif.California Department of Water Resources, 1964, Bulletin 64, West Walker River Investigation: Sacramento, Calif.California Department of Water Resources, 1960, Report on Bridgeport Valley Ground-Water Investigation, Sacramento, CalifErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.Last update 2/27/04