North Lahontan Hydrologic Region (6) Surprise Valley Groundwater BasinSurprise Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 6-1• County: Modoc and Lassen, CA, and Washoe, NV• Surface Area: 228,460 acres (CA) (357 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologySurprise Valley is a complexly faulted graben filled with alluvial and lacustrine sediments. The valley is bounded on all sides by block-faulted structures. The Surprise Valley fault is on the west side, and Hays Canyon fault is on the east side. To the south the valley is bounded topographically by a block-faulted horst. The northern half of the eastern side of the valley is bounded by an irregularly block faulted region. The basin is approximately 50 miles long and 12 miles wide.The margins of the valley are covered with coalesced alluvial fan and near- shore deposits. The central portion of the valley floor consists of basin and lake deposits. The basin is closed and has no hydrologic outlet. Most of the streams draining into Surprise Valley originate along the eastern slopes of the Warner Mountains and empty into the Upper, Middle, and Lower Alkali lakes. These lakes are shallow and alkaline and usually become dry in summer months. The surface water flows are adjudicated in most streams. Annual precipitation in the basin ranges from 13- to 17 inches, increasing to the north.Hydrogeologic InformationWater-Bearing FormationsThe water-bearing formations consist of Holocene alluvium and alluvial fan deposits, Pleistocene near-shore deposits, and Pliocene to Pleistocene lake deposits. The following summary of the water-bearing formations is from DWR (1965).Holocene Alluvial Fans. The alluvial fan deposits consist of unconsolidated to partly consolidated, poorly stratified gravel, sand, and silt with clay lenses.They are found near the surface with thicknesses ranging to 1,000 feet and are important recharge areas for the valley. The alluvial fans slope toward the valley floor and coalesce to form a continuous alluvial apron around much of the valley. These deposits form the principal aquifers in the basin and are capable of yielding large quantities of confined and semi-confined groundwater to wells. The fans are generally coarser at the mountain front and finer toward the basin center.Holocene Alluvium Deposits. Intermediate alluvial deposits are found along stream channels on the eastern side of the valley and along the flatter distal portions of alluvial fan deposits in the northern, western, and southern portions of the basin. The alluvium consists of poorly sorted sand and silt with some lenses of gravel and clay. Sand, gravel, and cobbles are predominant along stream channels. The thickness of the deposits range up to 50 feet. The alluvium is moderately permeable and is capable of providing good quantities of water to shallow wells.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
North Lahontan Hydrologic Region (6) Surprise Valley Groundwater BasinSurprise. They consist of poorly consolidated gravel, sand, and silt deposited as deltas and terraces. They are coarser-grained along the margins of the valley and become finer-grained toward the center ranging up to 5,000 feet in thickness. These deposits have moderate to high permeability and are capable of yielding large amounts of water to wells.Pleistocene to Holocene Lake Deposits. The lake deposits consist of unconsolidated to semi-consolidated fine sand, silt, and clay. The thickness of the deposits range up to 5,000 feet in the central portion of Middle Alkali Lake. The permeability is low but may be sufficient for limited development of water for stock purposes.Recharge AreasRecharge to groundwater on the west side of the valley is from infiltration of surface water into the apexes of the alluvial fans located below the mouths of canyons along the base of the Warner Mountains. In the extreme northern portion of the valley, surface water from the north infiltrates coarse stream deposits and recharges underlying groundwater bodies. As these recharge areas are all within the valley floor area, no true upland recharge areas exist along the western and northern sides of the valley (DWR 1963).Groundwater Level TrendsSection incomplete.Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. Groundwater storage capacity to a depth of 400 feet is estimated to be approximately 4,000,000 acre-feet (DWR 1963).Groundwater Budget (Type B)Estimates of groundwater extraction for the basin are based on a survey conducted by the California Department of Water Resources during 1997. The survey included land use and sources of water. Estimates of groundwater extraction for agricultural and municipal/industrial uses are 41,000 and 290 acre-feet, respectively. Deep percolation from applied water is estimated to be 6,600 acre-feet.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. Calcium bicarbonate type waters occur on the western edge of the basin and sodium bicarbonate type waters occur easterly. Calcium to sodium bicarbonate water occurs west of Lower and Middle Alkali Lakes. Total dissolved solids range from 87- to 1,800-mg/L, averaging 224 mg/L.Impairments. Poor quality water of sodium sulfate to sodium sulfate chloride character is present east of Middle Alkali Lake and along the southern and western edges of Upper Alkali Lake. Some thermal waters along the Surprise Valley and Lake City fault zones have high ASAR, highCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼The near-shore deposits are highly permeable terraces, beaches, spits and deltas formed in ancient LakePleistocene Near-shore Deposits.Last update 2/27/04
North Lahontan Hydrologic Region (6) Surprise Valley Groundwater Basinconcentrations of sulfate, sodium, boron, fluoride, and arsenic and total dissolved solids concentrations greater than 1,000 mg/L.Water Quality in Public Supply WellsCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Constituent Group1Inorganics – Primary RadiologicalNitratesPesticidesVOCs and SOCs Inorganics – SecondaryNumber of wells sampled2 21 4 0 1 2Number of wells with a concentration above an MCL3 00 0 0 0 0￼1 A description of each member in the constituent groups and a generalized discussion of the relevance of these groups are included in California’s Groundwater – Bulletin 118 by DWR (2003).2 Represents distinct number of wells sampled as required under DHS Title 22 program from 1994 through 2000.3 Each well reported with a concentration above an MCL was confirmed with a second detection above an MCL. This information is intended as an indicator of the types of activities that cause contamination in a given basin. It represents the water quality at the sample location. It does not indicate the water quality delivered to the consumer. More detailed drinking water quality information can be obtained from the local water purveyor and its annual Consumer Confidence Report.Well Production CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)￼IrrigationDomestic IrrigationRange: 350 – 2,500Total depths (ft)Range: 60 – 580 Range: 100 – 812Average: 1,383 (154 Well Completion Reports)Average: 199 (161 Well Completion Reports)Average: 347 (154 Well Completion Reports)Number of wells /measurement frequency16 wells /semi-annually 26 wells/ semi-annually 11 wells4 wells￼Active Monitoring Data￼AgencyDWRSoil Conservation ServiceDWRDepartment of Health ServicesParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water quality￼Last update 2/27/04
North Lahontan Hydrologic Region (6) Surprise Valley Groundwater BasinCalifornia’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Basin ManagementGroundwater ManagementWater Agencies PublicPrivateReferences CitedModoc County adopted a groundwater management ordinance in 2000Surprise Valley Management District, enacted 1995￼￼￼California Department of Water Resources. 1963. Northeastern Counties Groundwater Investigation, Volume 1, Text. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 98. 224 p.California Department of Water Resources. 1963. Northeastern Counties Investigation, Volume 2, Plates. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 98.California Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1965. Northeastern Counties Ground Water Investigation. Appendix C, Geology, Bulletin 98.Additional ReferencesBader JS. 1969. Ground Water Data as of 1967, North Lahontan Subregion, California. USGS. Open File Report.Bailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.Barker CE. 1996. Resource Assessment of the Bureau of Land Management's Winnemucca District and Surprise Resource Area, Northwest Nevada and Northeast California; Geochemical Analysis and Thermochronologic Modeling to Evaluate Conceptual Petroleum Plays. USGS. OF-96-0051.Bedinger MS. 1990. Studies of Geology and Hydrology in the Basin and Range Province, Southwestern United States, for Isolation High-Level Radioactive Waste; Evaluation of the Regions. USGS. 84-745.California Department of Water Resources. 1960. Surprise Valley Water Quality Investigation. California Department of Water Resources, Division of Resources Planning.California Department of Water Resources. 1961. Geology and Geohydrology of Surprise Valley, Modoc and Lassen Counties. California Department of Water Resources, Division of Resources Planning.California Department of Water Resources. 1964. Quality of Ground Water in California 1961-62, Part 1: Northern and Central California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 66-62.California Department of Water Resources. 1965. Northeastern Counties Ground Water Investigation, Appendix C, Geology. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. Bulletin 98.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.California Department of Water Resources. 1982. Northeastern Counties Ground Water Update. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. Office Report.California Department of Water Resources. 1983. Artificial Groundwater Recharge in Surprise Valley. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. Office Report.Last update 2/27/04
North Lahontan Hydrologic Region (6) Surprise Valley Groundwater BasinCalifornia Department of Water Resources. 1986. Surprise Valley Ground Water Basin, Water Quality Study. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District.California Department of Water Resources. 1992. Lassen County Water Resources Assessment Study. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. Memorandum Report.California Department of Water Resources. 1993. Ground Water Basin Study - Statewide Basin Plan Update (Surprise Valley, Madeline Plains, and Long Valley Ground Water Basins). California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. Memorandum Report.California Department of Water Resources. 1998. California Water Plan Update. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 160-98 Volumes 1 and 2.California Division of Oil and Gas. 1974. Geothermal Hotline. California Division of Oil and Gas 4(3): 6.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Gay TE, Jr., Aune QA. 1968. Geologic Map of California [Alturas Sheet]. California Division of Mines and Geology. Atlas.Grim J. 1994. Geologist's Trip Report - Surprise Valley, Modoc County, California. Soil Conservation Service. File Code 210-16.Kramer JC. 1980. California Department of Water Resources Progress Report; Groundwater Condition Update, Northeast Counties, July 8, 1980, Plus Some Department of Water Resources Bulletin 98 Statigraphic Columns and Cross Sections for Northeastern Counties, Geologic Guide to the Modoc Plateau and the Warner Mountains. Geological Society Sacramento: 124-148.Phillips KN, Van Denburgh AS. 1971. Hydrology and Geochemistry of Abert, Summer, and Goose Lakes, and Other Closed-Basin Lakes in South-Central Oregon. USGS. 502-B.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.Reed JE, Bedinger MS, Langer WH, Ireland RL, Mulvihill DA. 1984. Maps Showing Ground- Water Units, Withdrawl, and Levels Springs and Depth to Ground-water, Basin and Range Province, Northern California. USGS. WRI 83-4115-A. 11 p.Reheis M. 1999. Extent of Pleistocene Lakes in the Western Great Basin. USGS. MF-2323.Sinclair WC, Loeltz OJ. 1963. Ground-Water Conditions in the Fernley-Wadsworth Area, Churchill, Lyon, Storey and Washoe Counties, Nevada. USGS. 1619-AA.Thompson TH, Chappell R. 1983. Maps Showing Distribution of Dissolved Solids and Dominant Chemical Type in Ground Water, Basin and Range Province, Northern California. USGS. WRI 83-4115-B.U. S. Geological Survey. 1981. Water Resources Data for California; Volume 4, Northern Central Valley Basins and the Great Basin from Honey Lake Basin to Oregon State Line. USGS.White DE. 1955. Violent Mud Volcano Eruption of Lake City Hot Springs, Northeastern California. Geological Society of America 66(9): 1109-1130.Whitehead RL. 1994. Ground Water Atlas of the Unites States: Segment 7, Idaho, Oregon, Washington. USGS. HA-730-H.Willden CR. 1961. Preliminary Geologic Map of Humboldt County, Nevada. USGS. MF- 0236.Williams TR, Bedinger MS. 1983. Selected Geologic and Hydrologic Characteristics of the Basin and Range Province, Western United States: Pleistocene Lakes and Marshes. USGS. OF-83-751.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
North Lahontan Hydrologic Region (6) Surprise Valley Groundwater BasinWilliams TR, Bedinger MS. 1984. Selected Geologic and Hydrologic Characteristics of the Basin and Range Province, Western United States: Pleistocene Lakes and Marshes. USGS. I-1522-D.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04