North Lahontan Hydrologic Region (6) Willow Creek Groundwater BasinWillow Creek Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 6-3• County: Lassen• Surface Area: 11,700 acres (18 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Willow Creek Groundwater Basin is bounded by Pleistocene to Plio- Pleistocene basalt of Horse Lake Mountain to the north, Mesozoic granitic rocks of Deans Ridge to the west, and by Pleistocene basalt of Susanville Peak and Antelope and Tunnison mountains to the south.Willow Creek originates from artesian springs in the northwestern part of the valley and flows southeasterly through the valley to Honey Lake Basin. Groundwater generally flows southeasterly in the valley. Annual precipitation ranges from 21 to 23-inches.Hydrogeologic InformationWater-Bearing FormationsThe water-bearing formations are composed of Holocene sedimentary deposits and basin deposits, Pleistocene to Holocene basalt, and Pliocene lake deposits. The following summary is from DWR (1963).Holocene Sedimentary Deposits. The Holocene sedimentary deposits consist of intermediate alluvium and alluvial fans underlying most of the southwestern half of the valley to a thickness of 250 feet. The intermediate alluvium consists of unconsolidated silt, sand, and lenses of gravel that are moderately permeable with moderate water yields. The alluvial fan deposits consist of unconsolidated gravel, sand, and clay that are moderate to high in permeability and yield moderate to large amounts of water to wells.Holocene Basin Deposits. These deposits consist of unconsolidated clay, silt, sand, and organic muck and underlie the northeastern part of the valley. The deposits have low permeability and yield small supplies of groundwater to stock and domestic wells.Pleistocene to Holocene Basalt. These deposits consist of highly fractured basalt containing zones of scoria with moderate to high permeability. The lavas form areas of recharge and act as aquifers beneath the southeastern and possibly the northern portions of the basin.Pliocene Lake Deposits. These deposits consist of beds of consolidated shale, sandstone, diatomite, and lenses of gravel and underlie several hundred feet of younger sediments in the valley. The permeability is generally low with yields sufficient only for domestic and stock purposes. Gravel lenses within these deposits are moderately permeable and can provide moderate quantities of semiconfined groundwater.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
North Lahontan Hydrologic Region (6) Willow Creek Groundwater BasinGroundwater Level TrendsGroundwater levels declined 2- to 10-feet during the early 1990s and have recovered as of 1999.Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. No published information was found for groundwater storage in the basin.Groundwater Budget (Type B)Estimates of groundwater extraction are based on surveys conducted by the California Department of Water Resources during 1997. Surveys included land use and sources of water. Estimates of groundwater extraction for agricultural and municipal/industrial uses are 1,900 and 5 acre-feet, respectively. Deep percolation from applied water is estimated to be 1,200 acre-feet.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. Bicarbonate-type waters occur throughout the basin. The concentration of total dissolved solids ranges from 90- to 1,200-mg/L, averaging 401 mg/L (DWR unpublished data).Well Production Characteristics Well yields (gal/min)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Domestic IrrigationNo known dataTotal depths (ft)Range: 80 – 580 Range: 201 – 606￼Active Monitoring Data Agency ParameterDWR Groundwater levelsDWR Miscellaneous water qualityReferences CitedAverage: 213 (32 Well Completion Reports)Average: 382 (5 Well Completion Reports)Number of wells /measurement frequency7 wells/semi-annually 4￼￼California Department of Water Resources. 1963. Northeastern Counties Groundwater Investigation, Volume 1, Text. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 98. 224 p.California Department of Water Resources. 1963. Northeastern Counties Investigation, Volume 2, Plates. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 98.Additional ReferencesBader JS. 1969. Ground Water Data as of 1967, North Lahontan Subregion, California. USGS. Open File Report.Last update 2/27/04
North Lahontan Hydrologic Region (6) Willow Creek Groundwater BasinBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.Bedinger MS. 1990. Studies of Geology and Hydrology in the Basin and Range Province, Southwestern United States, for Isolation High-Level Radioactive Waste; Evaluation of the Regions. USGS. 84-745.California Department of Water Resources. 1960. Honey Lake and Willow Creek Valleys Water Quality Investigations. California Department of Water Resources, Division of Resources Planning.California Department of Water Resources. 1960. Northeastern Counties Investigation. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 58.California Department of Water Resources. 1965. Northeastern Counties Ground Water Investigation, Appendix C, Geology. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. Bulletin 98.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.California Department of Water Resources. 1992. Lassen County Water Resources Assessment Study. California Department of Water Resources, Northern District. Memorandum Report.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Grose TLT, McKee EH. 1986. Potassium-argon Ages of Late Miocene to Late Quaternary Volcanic Rocks in the Susanville-Eagle Lake Area, Lassen County, California. USGS.Handman EH, Londquist CJ, Maurer DK. 1990. Ground-water Resources of Honey Lake Valley, Lassen County, California, and Washoe County Nevada. USGS. 90-4050.Lydon PA, Gay TE, Jennings CW. 1969. Geologic Atlas of California [Westwood Sheet]. California Division of Mines and Geology.Mariner RH, Presser TS, Evans WC. 1977. Chemical Composition Data and Calculated Aquifer Temperature for Selected Wells and Springs for Honey Lake Valley, California. USGS. OFR-76-783.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.Rockwell GL. 1990. Surface-Water Hydrology of Honey Lake Valley, Lassen County, California and Washoe County, Nevada. USGS. OF-90-177.Rockwell GL. 1993. Surface-Water Hydrology of Honey-Lake Valley, Lassen County, California, and Washoe County, Nevada. USGS. HA-726.Rockwell GL, Friebel MF, Webster MD, Anderson SW. 1998. Water Resources Data for California, Water Year 1997; Volume 4, Northern Central Valley Basins and the Great Basin from Honey Lake Basin to Oregon State Line. USGS.U. S. Geological Survey. 1981. Water Resources Data for California; Volume 4, Northern Central Valley Basins and the Great Basin from Honey Lake Basin to Oregon State Line. USGS.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04