North Lahontan Hydrologic Region Pine Creek Valley Groundwater BasinPine Creek Valley Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 6-92• County: Lassen• Surface Area: 9,530 acres (15 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Pine Creek Valley Groundwater Basin is an alluvial filled valley located in southwest Lassen County at the base of Crater Lake Mountain to the south and southeast. The basin is bounded by Recent basalt of Crater Lake Mountain to the north. The basin is bounded on all other sides by Pleistocene basalt of Bogard Buttes, South Valley Butte, and Campbell, Antelope, and Logan mountains. Annual precipitation ranges from 29- to 33-inches.Hydrogeologic InformationNote: This basin summary was prepared using available published information and data. In addition, a comprehensive literature search was conducted using California, Oregon and Nevada Water Resources, and Mines and Geology web sites, UC and UNR Library sites, and The Resources Agency Library. The searches were made using basin names linked to keywords such as geology, groundwater, hydrogeology, and references to the regional geology. Because no local area hydrogeologic data are available, this basin description is incomplete. Where no local area references or site specific data/publications were found, regional references are listed to provide a regional framework for the basin or subbasin.Water-Bearing FormationsSection incomplete.Groundwater Level TrendsSection incomplete.Groundwater StorageSection incomplete.Groundwater BudgetSection incomplete.Groundwater QualitySection incomplete.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
North Lahontan Hydrologic Region Pine Creek Valley Groundwater BasinWell Production Characteristics Well yields (gal/min)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationNo known dataTotal depths (ft)68 (1 well completion report)No data￼Active Monitoring DataNo dataNumber of wells /measurement frequency 00 1￼AgencyDepartment of Health ServicesParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water qualityMiscellaneous water quality￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management: Water agenciesPublic PrivateAdditional References￼￼Bach AJ. 1991. Pleistoncen Glacial History of Pine Creek, East-Central Sierra Nevada.Bailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.Bedinger MS. 1990. Studies of Geology and Hydrology in the Basin and Range Province, Southwestern United States, for Isolation High-Level Radioactive Waste; Evaluation of the Regions. USGS. 84-745.California Bureau of Sanitary Engineering, California Regional Water Quality Control Board Lahontan Region. 1952. Pine Creek Survey. Berkeley: California Bureau of Sanitary Engineering. 25 p.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.Dickinson WR, Ingersoll RV, Grahm SA. 1979. Paleogene Sediment Dispersal and Paleotectonics in Northern California. Geological Society of America Bulletin 90:1458- 1528.Lydon PA, Gay TE, Jennings CW. 1969. Geologic Atlas of California [Westwood Sheet]. California Division of Mines and Geology.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.Last update 2/27/04