North Lahontan Hydrologic Region Horse Lake Groundwater BasinHorse Lake Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 6-97• County: Lassen• Surface Area: 3,800 acres ( square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Horse Lake Groundwater Basin is located south of Madeline Plains and east of Eagle Lake. The basin encompasses Horse Lake and is bounded to the southeast by Pleistocene volcanic basalt and on all other sides by Pliocene basalt with outcrops of Pleistocene basalt (Gay 1960). Faulting in the region transects the basin in both northwest and north-northeast directions. The primary water-bearing formation in the basin is Holocene alluvium. Annual precipitation is approximately 13- to 19-inches, increasing to the south.Hydrogeologic InformationHydrogeologic information was not available for the following:Groundwater Level Trends Groundwater Storage Groundwater Budget Groundwater QualityWell CharacteristicsWell yields (gal/min)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationNKD – No known data.Active Monitoring Data Agency ParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water qualityNKDTotal depths (ft)687 (1 Well Completion Report)￼￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management:Water agencies PublicPrivateNo known groundwater management plans, groundwater ordinances, or basin adjudications.None NoneNumber of wells /measurement frequency NKDNKD￼￼￼Last update 2/27/04
North Lahontan Hydrologic Region Horse Lake Groundwater BasinSelected ReferencesLydon PA, Gay TE, Jennings CW. 1960. Geologic Atlas of California [Westwood Sheet]. California Division of Mines and Geology.California Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1963. Bulletin No. 98, Northeastern Counties Groundwater Investigation, Volume 1, Text, California Department of Water Resources: 224.California Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1963. Bulletin No. 98, Northeastern Counties Investigation, Volume 2, Plates, California Department of Water Resources.California Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1965. Bulletin No. 98, Northeastern Counties Ground Water Investigation, Appendix C: Geology, California Department of Water Resources, Northern District.BibliographyBailey EH. 1966. Geology of Northern California. California Division of Mines and Geology. Bulletin 190.California Department of Water Resources. 1975. California's Ground Water. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118.California Department of Water Resources. 1980. Ground Water Basins in California. California Department of Water Resources. Bulletin 118-80.Planert M, Williams JS. 1995. Ground Water Atlas of the United States, Segment 1, California, Nevada. USGS. HA-730-B.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04