South Lahontan Hydrologic Region Harrisburg Flats Groundwater BasinHarrisburg Flats Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 6-74• County: Inyo• Surface Area: 24,900 acres (38.9 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThe Harrisburg Flats Groundwater Basin underlies a northwest-trending intermontane valley in the Panimint Range of central Inyo County. Elevation of the valley floor ranges from about 4,800 feet above sea level at the north end of the valley and increases to about 5,300 feet at Emigrant Pass at the south end. The basin is bounded by nonwater-bearing rocks of the southern Panamint Range. The surrounding mountains range in elevation from about 5,500 to 7,500 feet. The basin lies within Death Valley National Park (Jennings 1958; USGS 1986, 1988).Average annual precipitation ranges from about 6 to10 inches. Runoff from the surrounding mountains drains northwest into Emigrant Canyon and Death Valley (Jennings 1958; USGS 1986).Hydrogeologic InformationWater Bearing FormationsQuaternary alluvium forms the water-bearing material within the basin and includes unconsolidated younger alluvial deposits and underlying unconsolidated to semi-consolidated older alluvial deposits (DWR 1964).Recharge and Discharge AreasRecharge of the basin is chiefly from the percolation of runoff through alluvial deposits at the base of the surrounding mountains and from the infiltration of precipitation that falls to the valley floor. Groundwater moves northwestward and discharges as underflow to Emigrant Canyon (USGS 1986).Groundwater Level TrendsThere are no historical records of wells or groundwater levels in the basin.Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. Unknown. Groundwater in Storage. Unknown.Groundwater Budget (C)Groundwater budget information is not available.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. Groundwater character for three springs near the north end of the basin varies between calcium-sodium bicarbonate or sodium- calcium bicarbonate.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
South Lahontan Hydrologic Region Harrisburg Flats Groundwater BasinImpairments. The quality of the groundwater is suitable for all beneficial uses. TDS content ranges from about 270 to 420 mg/L.Well Production characteristics Well yields (gal/min)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationActive Monitoring DataAgencyDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water qualityTitle 22 water qualityNumber of wells /measurement frequency1Total depths (ft)￼￼￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management: Water agenciesPublic PrivateReferences Cited￼￼California Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1964. Ground Water Occurrence and Quality Lahontan Region. Bulletin No.106-1. 439 p.Jennings, C.W. 1958. Geologic Map of California: Death Valley Sheet. Olaf P. Jenkins Edition. California Department of Conservation, Division of Mines and Geology. Scale 1: 250,000.U.S. Geological Survey. 1986. Emigrant Canyon, California. 7.5’ Quadrangle. Provisional Edition. Scale 1: 24,000.U.S. Geological Survey. 1988. Emigrant Pass, California. 7.5’ Quadrangle. Provisional Edition. Scale 1: 24,000.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.Last update 2/27/04