South Lahontan Hydrologic Region Middle Park Canyon Groundwater BasinMiddle Park Canyon Groundwater Basin• Groundwater Basin Number: 6-80• County: Inyo• Surface Area: 1,740 acres (2.7 square miles)Basin Boundaries and HydrologyThis groundwater basin underlies Middle Park Canyon in the southern Panamint Range of southern Inyo County. The basin is bounded by nonwater-bearing rocks of the Panamint Range (Jennings 1958; Jennings and others 1962). Annual precipitation averages 8 to 10 inches.Hydrogeologic InformationWater Bearing FormationsQuaternary alluvium is the water-bearing material within the basin and includes unconsolidated younger alluvial deposits and underlying unconsolidated to semi-consolidated older alluvial deposits (DWR 1964). Such alluvium likely consists of fine- to coarse-grained sand, pebbles, and boulders with variable amounts of silt and clay.Restrictive StructuresUnknown.Recharge AreasRecharge to the basin is most likely from percolation of precipitation and runoff from the surrounding mountains.Groundwater Level TrendsUnknown.Groundwater StorageGroundwater Storage Capacity. Unknown. Groundwater in Storage. Unknown.Groundwater Budget (Type C)No information is available.Groundwater QualityCharacterization. Unknown. Impairments. Unknown.California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼Last update 2/27/04
South Lahontan Hydrologic Region Middle Park Canyon Groundwater BasinWell Production characteristics Well yields (gal/min)California’s Groundwater Bulletin 118￼￼Municipal/IrrigationDomestic Municipal/IrrigationActive Monitoring DataAgencyDepartment of Health Services and cooperatorsParameterGroundwater levelsMiscellaneous water qualityTitle 22 water qualityNumber of wells /measurement frequencyTotal depths (ft)￼￼￼Basin ManagementGroundwater management: Water agenciesPublic PrivateReferences Cited￼￼California Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1964. Ground Water Occurrence and Quality Lahontan Region. Bulletin No.106-1. 439 p.Jennings, C.W. 1958. Geologic Map of California: Death Valley Sheet. Olaf P. Jenkins Edition. California Department of Conservation, Division of Mines and Geology. Scale 1: 250,000.Jennings, C. W. , J. L. Burnett, B. W. Troxel. 1962. Geologic Map of California: Trona Sheet. Olaf P. Jenkins Edition. California Department of Conservation, Division of Mines and Geology. Scale 1: 250,000Additional ReferencesCalifornia Department of Water Resources (DWR). 1975. California’s Ground Water. Bulletin 118. 135 p.Hunt, C.B. , T.W. Robinson, W.A. Bowles, and A.L. Washburn. 1966. Hydrologic Basin Death Valley California. U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 494 – B. 137 p.Mendenhall, W.C., 1909. Some Desert Watering Places in Southeastern California and Southwestern Nevada. U. S. Geological Survey, Water-Supply Paper 224. 98 p.Miller, G. A., 1977. Appraisal of the Water Resources of Death Valley, California-Nevada. U. S. Geological Survey, Open-File Report 77-728. 68 p.ErrataChanges made to the basin description will be noted here.Last update 2/27/04